<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Top Todo App of 2016</title>
	  <link>/blog//Top-Todo-App-of-2016</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-19T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Top-Todo-App-of-2016</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/b/ba/Wunderlist_Logo.png" alt="Wunderlist Logo" /></p>

<p>There are a multitude of todo apps nowadays. Finding the right tool to keep your day organised is rather an individual choice - but there are definitely some apps which outshine others in terms of their features. The best apps offer advanced features such as notifications, reminders, lists and sublists and the list goes on. </p>

<h2 id="wunderlist">Wunderlist</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/vmpiDq5.png" alt="Wunderlist Main Screen" /></p>

<p>My vote for the best Todo application goes to Wunderlist. The name Wunderlist may be rather familiar to you considering it has been around since 2011. Though Wunderlist adopts a freemium model, I can safely say that the free version itself has plentiful of features that can satisfy any average user. </p>

<p>The best part of Wunderlist is its multi-platform support. The app is available on Windows, macOS, iOS, Android, Windows Phone, Kindle and Chromebook. Wunderlist also offers extensions on your favourite browsers: Chrome, Firefox and Safari. No matter where you are, you are always in sync. Add something on your Mac and it immediately shows up on your mobile phones.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/2OEZVgz.png" alt="Wunderlist ToDo" /></p>

<p>The second feature that makes Wunderlist the right tool for you is reminders. For every task that you add, you can specify both the due date and a reminder. This is my most used feature of Wunderlist as reminders ensure I am up to all my tasks even when I am not checking the app. Reminders are offered via the app as well as a personal email sent right to your inbox.</p>

<p>Todos added can also be specified to be recurring (daily, weekly, monthly, yearly or custom basis) and it is really simple to keep track of repeating tasks. Under each todo, Wunderlist also offers the support to add sub-tasks and notes. One thing the app does not offer is priority levels. You can also star important tasks which you can use to signify the priority. For more levels of priority, you can create individual priority lists and assign tasks to those. Alternatively, my recommendation is use Wunderlist tags. By appending “#tag_name” to tasks we can tag the task under a certain category. For priority levels for example, we can use <code class="highlighter-rouge">#high</code>, <code class="highlighter-rouge">#medium</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">#low</code>.</p>

<p>A huge plus of Wunderlist is its collaborative feature. I personally love using this feature whenever I am travelling with my friends or family. I simply create a shared list and all my friends or family members can easily edit the lists. They can also comment on the tasks I have added, making communication across the app really simple and easy.</p>

<p>The difference between the free version of Wunderlist and the Pro version is not stark, but it may make a difference for power users. Under the free version, we can add up to 5mb of files as attachments to tasks, assign up to 25 people, create up to 25 subtasks and choose from 20 backgrounds. The Pro version offers unlimited file size, assignments, subtasks and up to 30 backgrounds to choose from. Wunderlist Pro costs $4.99/month, but it seems that the basic or free version will easily satisfy the average user.</p>

<p>Wunderlist’s features and great looking user interface certainly makes it one of the most compelling todo apps today. Use it and let us know your comments below!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Top Email Clients for the New Mac</title>
	  <link>/blog//Top-Email-Clients-for-Mac</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-19T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Top-Email-Clients-for-Mac</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="apple-mail">Apple Mail</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/hm3hIAU.png" alt="Apple Mail" /></p>

<p><img src="https://support.apple.com/library/content/dam/edam/applecare/images/en_US/osx/yos_mail_conversations.png" alt="Apple Mail" /></p>

<p>Apple’s built in client, Mail, offers a neat interface for managing multiple email accounts at once. From experience, it integrates smoothly with all the popular service providers such as Google, Yahoo, Outlook and Office Enterprise accounts. It also offers markup capabilities to edit your PDF or image attachment right within the client. Spotlight on macOS also includes Mail attachments and emails into search. Mail comes installed by default on all new Macs.</p>

<h2 id="spark">Spark</h2>

<p><img src="https://sparkmailapp.com/img/new/index/all_devices.png" alt="Spark" /></p>

<p>Spark won “Best of 2016” award. Spark places itself as a client for users looking productivity. It has a Smart Inbox which allows you to focus on the most important emails by categorising new emails into  Personal, Notifications and Newsletters. Spark’s snooze feature helps you to get rid of emails that are not urgent. </p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/hZ07VF2.png" alt="Smart Search" /></p>

<p>My favourite feature of Spark is its smart search that support natural language. If you are looking for attachments from John, your colleague, simply typing “attachments from John” will bring the relevant results to you in an instant. Spark offers smart notifications, which helps you filter email notifications to only those of high priority. Signature support is also great in Spark as you just need to quickly swipe or choose between your frequently used signatures. </p>

<p>Spark offers an “Undo Send” feature which allows a delay of 5 seconds before sending the email. This may be useful for those who often send hurried emails as you can stop sending the email and continue edits. However, currently Spark does not allow for variable delay and it is fixed to 5 seconds.</p>

<p>Something that really stands out in Spark is its Quick Replies. You can quickly reply to any email with a preset of emotions such as Like, Thanks, Agree etc. And beyond all the hoard of features, Spark has a great UI that keeps you coming back to it. Spark comes free on both the Mac App Store for Macs and the iTunes Store for iOS devices. It’s definitely worth a try for all new users.</p>

<h2 id="airmail"> Airmail</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/kAhWBrC.png" alt="Airmail" /></p>

<p>I have been a loyal user of Airmail for about two years now. I made the switch from Apple’s Mail to Airmail primarily because of the Snooze function it offerred back then. At that time, Airmail seemed to be the best option as other alternatives (such as Spark) were not present. But a word of warning is that Airmail offers tons of preferences and settings which may not be for the average user. </p>

<p>Like Spark, Airmail has many of the features discussed. I personally like the “Undo Send” function which offers up to 120 seconds delay before sending an email which you clicked Send. It has already proved to be a crucial function in several scenarios.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/faZx1p1.png" alt="Markdown - Airmail" /></p>

<p>Airmail contains several themes which may appeal to different individuals. Also, Airmail offers crafting emails in Markdown, a popular language for blogging nowadays. It provides a immediate preview of the email by having a split screen view. With Markdown, you can easily create lists, and even embed your code blocks.</p>

<p>Airmail supports integrations with several productivity apps such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Calendar</li>
  <li>Reminders</li>
  <li>OmniFocus</li>
  <li>Wunderlist</li>
  <li>Todoist</li>
</ul>

<p>and many others!</p>

<p>While Airmail is not free, it comes at an affordable price of US$9.99.)</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What is Markdown?</title>
	  <link>/blog//What-is-Markdown</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-18T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//What-is-Markdown</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Markdown is a markup language that can be easily converted to HTML or other formats. The best part of Markdown is that you can write it in plaintext format, yet format it using certain special characters such as hyphens (<code class="highlighter-rouge">-</code>), quotes etc. Even this post was rendered with Markdown. Let’s see how we can craft posts with Markdown.</p>

<h2 id="headings">Headings</h2>

<p>Similar to HTML, Markdown supports six levels of headings, from H1 to H6. To achieve different headings, we simply use the <code class="highlighter-rouge">#</code> to denote the level. For example:</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge"># Hello</code> yields a H1 header while <code class="highlighter-rouge">## Hello</code> yields a H2 header. Here’s a demo:</p>

<h1 id="h1-header">H1 header</h1>

<h2 id="h2-header">H2 header</h2>

<h3 id="h3-header">H3 header</h3>

<h4 id="h4-header">H4 header</h4>

<h5 id="h5-header">H5 header</h5>

<h6 id="h6-header">H6 header</h6>

<h2 id="bold-italics-underline-and-strikethrough">Bold, Italics, Underline and Strikethrough</h2>

<p>To give sufficient emphasis we can use the following syntax:</p>

<p>```markdown
Text can be made bold by using a <strong>double asterisks</strong> or <strong>double underscores</strong> at both the start and end of the text segment.</p>

<p>Text can be made italics by using a single asterisk or single underscore at both the start and end of the text segment.</p>

<p>To combine both bold and italics, we can use both the above notations like <em><strong>this</strong></em>.</p>

<p>To make a strikethrough, we can use two tildes at the start and end of the text segment ~~like this~~.
```</p>

<p>Text can be made bold by using a <strong>double asterisks</strong> or <strong>double underscores</strong> at both the start and end of the text segment.</p>

<p>Text can be made italics by using a single asterisk or single underscore at both the start and end of the text segment.</p>

<p>To combine both bold and italics, we can use both the above notations like <em><strong>this</strong></em>.</p>

<p>To make a strikethrough, we can use two tildes at the start and end of the text segment ~~like this~~.</p>

<h2 id="making-lists">Making Lists</h2>

<p>Lists are one of the most needed features for anyone writing anything! Markdown offers a nifty feature for making lists that is super easy to write.</p>

<h3 id="ordered-numbered-lists">Ordered (Numbered) Lists</h3>

<p>To make numbered lists, we simply start with <code class="highlighter-rouge">1. </code> and markdown interprets whatever comes after as the first point of the list. You can create nested lists with three spaces followed by a number.</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
1. Hello World
2. This is a numbered list.
   3. This is a nested numbered list.
</code>
The above gives us the following result:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Hello World</li>
  <li>This is a numbered list.
    <ol>
      <li>This is a nested numbered list.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="unordered-lists">Unordered Lists</h3>

<p>To make unordered lists, we can use asterisks (*), minuses (-), pluses (+).</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
* Unordered point 1
+ Unordered point 2
- Unordered point 3
</code></p>

<p>The above will now translate to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Unordered point 1</li>
  <li>Unordered point 2</li>
  <li>Unordered point 3</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="combining-ordered-and-unordered-lists">Combining Ordered and Unordered Lists</h3>

<p>To combine and nest ordered and unordered lists, we just need to add trailing spaces before the next point followed by a number/asterisk/minus/plus.</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
1. Ordered point 1
2. Ordered point 2
   * Unordered point nested under point 2
3. Ordered point 3
   1. Ordered point 1 under point 3
</code>
Result:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Ordered point 1</li>
  <li>Ordered point 2
    <ul>
      <li>Unordered point nested under point 2</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Ordered point 3
    <ol>
      <li>Ordered point 1 under point 3</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="adding-links">Adding Links</h2>

<p>Hyperlinks are one of the most commonly used features in any document, blog etc. Adding links in Markdown is really simple too!</p>

<p>To add a hyperlink on a text, we use both square brackets <code class="highlighter-rouge">[]</code> and round brackets <code class="highlighter-rouge">()</code>.</p>

<p>First we put the text we want to hyperlink into the square brackets, in this example, Google: <code class="highlighter-rouge">[Google]</code>. Next, we hyperlink by adding the actual web address in between round brackets right after the square brackets, like this:</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
[Google](http://www.google.com)
</code></p>

<p>Rendering the markdown, we get this:</p>

<p><a href="http://google.com">Google</a></p>

<h2 id="adding-images">Adding Images</h2>

<p>Adding images is very similar to adding links. All we need to do is to add an exclamation mark in front of the square brackets. The alt text for the image goes into the square brackets and web address into the round brackets. Suppose we want to display the Google logo, we do this:</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
![Google Logo](https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/2f/Google_2015_logo.svg/2000px-Google_2015_logo.svg.png)
</code></p>

<p>And this renders as:</p>

<p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/2f/Google_2015_logo.svg/2000px-Google_2015_logo.svg.png" alt="Google Logo" /></p>

<h2 id="blockquotes">Blockquotes</h2>

<p>Blockquotes are handy to specify sections which have been to quoted from another source. They are commonly used in emails where you can highlight the point you are addressing with regards to a previous email. To add a block quote, you use the <code class="highlighter-rouge">&gt;</code> sign.</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
&gt; This is a blockquote.
&gt; This is the second line of the blockquote.
</code></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is a blockquote.
This is the second line of the blockquote.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="adding-code">Adding Code</h2>

<p>Markdown supports adding code and syntax-highlighting. This is a joy for any programmer or developer. I am personally a heavy user of this feature to make my notes/articles. To add a code block, we wrap the code with three backticks: “```” .</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>This is a general code block as there is no language specified.</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>We can add code blocks by specifying the language as well. We do this by adding the language name right after the first “```”. For example, lets add a Python code block.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span class="sb">```</span>python
def print_hello_world():
    print("Hello World!");
    
print_hello_world();
<span class="sb">```</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Writing the above renders into:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hello_world</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="k">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">"Hello World!"</span><span class="p">);</span>
    
<span class="n">print_hello_world</span><span class="p">();</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Similarly, Markdown supports an astonishing variety of languages!</p>

<p>Sometimes, you just want to highlight a specific word like <code class="highlighter-rouge">this</code>. That’s called inline code. To add inline code, we just use one backtick.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span class="sb">`inline code`</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>gives us <code class="highlighter-rouge">inline code</code>.</p>

<h2 id="adding-tables">Adding Tables</h2>

<p>Yup, there is support for adding tables too! Now you can easily add tables with markdown to all your emails instead of creating them elsewhere and painstakingly copying them over to ensure in-tact formatting.</p>

<p>We use fences to make tables in markdown. A typical markdown table looks like this:</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">markdown
| Fruits    | Cost   | Quantity  | Total |Supplier   |
| :-------- |-------:| ---------:|------:|:---------:|
| Apples    | $2     |   160     |$320   |XYZ Company|
| Oranges   | $3     |   120     |$360   |ABC Company|
| Pears     | $4     |   100     |$400   |123 Company|
</code></p>

<p>Colons help us align the content within the columns. You can also add emphasis (bold, italics, strikethrough) in the tables.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Fruits</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Cost</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Quantity</th>
      <th style="text-align: right">Total</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Supplier</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Apples</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$2</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">160</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$320</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">XYZ Company</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Oranges</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$3</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">120</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$360</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">ABC Company</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Pears</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$4</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">100</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">$400</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">123 Company</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>As you can it is a really neat way to make tables! Placing the colon on either sides of the dividing line indicates how the content for the column will be aligned. Colon on left helps left-align (see column <code class="highlighter-rouge">Fruits</code>). Colon on the right helps right-align (see columns <code class="highlighter-rouge">Cost</code>, <code class="highlighter-rouge">Quantity</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">Total</code>). Colons on both sides centers the column’s content (see column <code class="highlighter-rouge">Supplier</code>).</p>

<h2 id="horizontal-line-breaks">Horizontal Line Breaks</h2>

<p>To have horziontal lines as dividers, we can use three asterisks (*), hyphens (-) or underscores (_).</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown">Horizontal line 1:
<span class="p">
***
</span>
Horizontal line 2:
<span class="p">
---
</span>
Horizontal line 3:
<span class="ge">__</span>_</code></pre></figure>

<p>renders as:</p>

<p>Horizontal line 1:</p>

<hr />

<p>Horizontal line 2:</p>

<hr />

<p>Horizontal line 3:
___</p>

<p>And that’s it folks! Markdown is a handy and simply language to learn that can help to save loads of time for plaintext lovers. Already planning on which Markdown editor to use? A new article is coming right on that. Meanwhile, give Markdown a try and share your comments below 👇🏼!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Data Science Student Challenge 2016 Experience</title>
	  <link>/blog//Data-Science-Student-Challenge-Experience</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-03-29T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Data-Science-Student-Challenge-Experience</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="about-the-challenge--our-product">About the Challenge &amp; Our Product</h2>

<p>Recently, I had the opportunity to participate in the Data Science Student Challenge which was co-organised and sponsored by Microsoft.</p>

<p>I took part in this event together with my friends Alvian, Chris &amp; Ida. We worked tirelessly over just 24 hours to build a full-fledged working application which integrates the concepts of machine learning and data science. And the result of our effort was “Prosper”.</p>

<p>The following extract is from our Github page.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="no">Prosper</span> <span class="n">stands</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="no">Property</span> <span class="no">Resale</span> <span class="no">Price</span> <span class="no">Forecaster</span><span class="o">.</span>

<span class="no">It</span> <span class="n">is</span> <span class="n">essentially</span> <span class="n">an</span> <span class="n">application</span> <span class="n">that</span> <span class="n">can</span> <span class="n">predict</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">future</span> <span class="n">resale</span> <span class="n">value</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">your</span> <span class="n">flat</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="k">in</span> <span class="no">Singapore</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">!</span> <span class="no">Sounds</span> <span class="n">exciting?</span>

<span class="no">We</span> <span class="n">have</span> <span class="n">combined</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">power</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="no">Microsoft</span> <span class="no">Azure</span><span class="err">'</span><span class="n">s</span> <span class="no">Machine</span> <span class="no">Learning</span> <span class="n">capabilities</span> <span class="n">together</span> <span class="n">with</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">resale</span> <span class="n">flat</span> <span class="n">data</span> <span class="n">from</span> <span class="n">http</span><span class="ss">:/</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">data</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">gov</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sg</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="n">utilise</span> <span class="n">over</span> <span class="mi">15</span> <span class="n">years</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">data</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="mi">480</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mo">000</span> <span class="n">data</span> <span class="n">points</span> <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">an</span> <span class="n">astonishing</span> <span class="mi">95</span><span class="o">%</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">error</span> <span class="n">margin</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="o">+-</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="o">%</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="n">accuracy</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">prediction</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">price</span><span class="o">.</span>

<span class="no">As</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="n">pro</span> <span class="n">analytics</span> <span class="n">feature</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="no">Prosper</span> <span class="n">also</span> <span class="n">provides</span> <span class="n">a</span> <span class="n">suggestion</span> <span class="n">on</span> <span class="k">when</span> <span class="n">you</span> <span class="n">should</span> <span class="n">be</span> <span class="n">selling</span> <span class="n">your</span> <span class="n">flat</span> <span class="n">based</span> <span class="n">on</span> <span class="n">your</span> <span class="n">expected</span> <span class="n">annual</span> <span class="n">growth</span> <span class="n">rate</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">flat</span> <span class="n">price</span><span class="o">.</span> <span class="no">Hence</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">application</span> <span class="n">tries</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="n">maximise</span> <span class="n">your</span> <span class="n">profit</span> <span class="n">given</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="n">expected</span> <span class="n">growth</span> <span class="n">price</span> <span class="n">per</span> <span class="n">annum</span><span class="o">.</span>

<span class="no">This</span> <span class="n">application</span> <span class="n">runs</span> <span class="n">using</span> <span class="no">Java</span> <span class="n">and</span> <span class="n">you</span> <span class="n">can</span> <span class="n">download</span> <span class="n">it</span> <span class="n">from</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="no">Releases</span> <span class="n">page</span><span class="o">.</span>

<span class="no">Prosper</span> <span class="n">was</span> <span class="n">developed</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="mi">24</span> <span class="n">hours</span> <span class="k">in</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="no">National</span> <span class="no">University</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="no">Singapore</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="no">NUS</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="no">Data</span> <span class="no">Science</span> <span class="no">Student</span> <span class="no">Challenge</span> <span class="n">supported</span> <span class="n">by</span> <span class="no">Mircosoft</span><span class="o">.</span>

<span class="no">Prosper</span> <span class="n">managed</span> <span class="n">to</span> <span class="n">secure</span> <span class="n">the</span> <span class="mi">5</span><span class="n">th</span> <span class="n">place</span> <span class="n">among</span> <span class="n">dozens</span> <span class="n">of</span> <span class="n">teams</span> <span class="n">at</span> <span class="no">NUS</span> <span class="no">Data</span> <span class="no">Science</span> <span class="no">Student</span> <span class="no">Challenge</span> <span class="mi">2016</span><span class="o">.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Below are some screenshots of the application. You can download and give Prosper a try <a href="https://github.com/harishv7/Prosper/releases">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="experience">Experience</h2>

<p>While it was extremely tiring, it was really a fulfilling experience. In that intense 24 hours, I actually learnt so much skills. It also proved that to learn something new, we only needed the determination and the dedication to pursue it.</p>

<p>Alvian has always been interested in the topics of data science and machine learning. Naturally, he was able to lead our discussion and ideas prior to the building of the actual application. I was in charge of developing the desktop client to communicate with the APIs provided by Microsoft Azure.</p>

<p>Initially, I tried using simple AJAX calls through a website. However, it did not work due to some error relating to the blockage of “Cross-Origin Requests”. After about 2 hours and going through multiple StackOverflow questions, we decided to change track. I never thought my experience in a previous module, CS2103 Software Engineering, will help me. I used the good old legacy language Java as it was stable and what everyone in my team knew best. Our technology stack was essentially JavaFX to design the layout the GUI and pure Java for the backend logic.</p>

<p>Both Ida and Chris helped me and Alvian to get the building of the application done. Meanwhile, Alvian started training the model for our app with the data provided by <a href="https://data.gov.sg/developer">https://data.gov.sg/developer</a>.</p>

<p>After getting through the initial round, my team was selected for the finals where we had to present to a panel of judges. It was really a tough experience. Imagine 24 hours++ without sleep and still needing the energy to be able to present lively to the audience in front of you.</p>

<p>While we did not obtain the top 3 prizes, I was definitely overjoyed to have my team in the 5th place considering that we were all just sophomores in NUS without much experience in these field. I definitely look forward to participating in the next challenge.</p>

<h2 id="screenshots">Screenshots</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/UyzzCLM.png" alt="Image1" />
<img src="http://i.imgur.com/eWqAGKg.png" alt="Image2" /></p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Gamecraft 2015!</title>
	  <link>/blog//Gamecraft-2015</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-06T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Gamecraft-2015</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/KnFi8cM.png " alt="TwistedMaze Logo" style="width: 200px;" /></p>

<p>I recently participated in Gamecraft 2015. This is my 2nd time participating this is “game-hackathon”. This time my team consisted of Al, Ted, Chris &amp; myself. The theme for this year was “Twist”. As usual, the interpretation of this theme in relation to the game was left open to us.</p>

<p>One of the first things that came to my mind was a maze that twists. As I was imagining this idea, I suddenly had this inspiration from this book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Maze_Runner">The Mazerunner</a>. It is a book where a group of “hostages” have to escape from a ever-changing labyrinth. There has also been a movie released with the same name.</p>

<p>I suggested this idea and we tried brainstorming a few ideas before settling and finalising on this one. After this decision, we focused our efforts towards the game development. Me and Chris took on the roles of the game design where we made the shifting maps for the maze and the necessary sprites.</p>

<p>Ted was the sound engineer and gather suitable sounds for use in the game. Al, being the lead programmer of the group, devoted his attention to the game physics and the actual coding of the game.</p>

<p>We utilised Unity for the game and eventually (after 24 hrs) managed to come up with a finished game, TwistedMaze. TwistedMaze is available for download (both Mac and Windows versions) at <a href="https://github.com/harishv7/TwistedMaze/releases">GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>Future work on porting the game to Android and iOS is currently being discussed.</p>

<p>Hope you enjoy playing the game as much as we enjoyed creating it. :)</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Hey Siri, Give me a hint!</title>
	  <link>/blog//Hey-Siri,-Give-me-a-hint!</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-08-29T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Hey-Siri,-Give-me-a-hint!</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Visited Apple’s events page today and was greeted by this:</p>

<p><img src="assets/AppleEvent/webpage.png" alt="Apple's Events Page" /></p>

<p>And true enough, Siri responded with it’s usual level of cuteness:</p>

<hr />

<div class="images">
<img class="siri" align="left" src="http://imgur.com/F6PcUgU.png" />
<img class="siri" align="middle" src="http://imgur.com/C44CeZq.png" />
<img class="siri" align="right" src="http://i.imgur.com/cPPGI8Y.png" />
<br />
<img class="siri" align="left" src="http://i.imgur.com/Nm4rD5C.png" />
<img class="siri" align="middle" src="http://i.imgur.com/3YCMIUk.png" />
<img class="siri" align="right" src="http://i.imgur.com/rfc5tdG.png" />
<br />
<img class="siri" align="left" src="http://i.imgur.com/yjFhbHU.png" />
<img class="siri" align="middle" src="http://i.imgur.com/10ELJWN.png" />
<img class="applelogo" align="right" src="/blog/assets/AppleEvent/apple.png" />
</div>

<style>
.images{
    text-align:center;
}
.applelogo{
	width:160px;
	height: 240x;
	padding-top: 50px;
}
.siri{
	width: 160px;
		height: 284px;
		display:inline-block;
}
</style>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Orbital 2015</title>
	  <link>/blog//Orbital-2015</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-08-19T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Orbital-2015</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5EjaKFa.png" alt="Friendezvous" /></p>

<p>After 3 months of hard work, the Orbital programme came to a close on 19th Aug 2015. It was a great experience and I picked up many skills of both front and back end development. I did the project with Al who was very supportive during the 3 months though he was on vacation.</p>

<p>The project’s inspiration came from our shared experiences in daily college life. Many of the times we tend to organise meetings manually. A typical process goes like this (A,B,C are persons).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A–&gt;B: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? <br />
B–&gt;A: Yup, that’ll be good I guess. <br />
A–&gt;C: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? <br />
C–&gt;A: Oh no, I don’t think I’ll be free. How about some other day? <br />
A (thinks to him/herself): Darn, got to ask B and C for another timing again! <br /></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As shown above, the typical manual process is tedious where we often WhatsApp or message one another for free slots and try to match it all up for a common time to meet. In the point of view of the meeting administrator, it is a rather painstaking process when he/she has to repeatedly ask the team members for a suitable time to meet.</p>

<p>To solve this issue, I suggested to Al that we should maybe develop a platform which can make the organising of meetings simpler and redefine the ways of doing so. And from there, Friendezvous was born. Friendezvous is an amalgamation of the words Friend and Rendezvous (a meeting at an agreed time and place). So essentially Friendezvous refers to meetings with friends, colleagues etc. And we decided on a relevant tagline as well: “Organising meetings, redefined.”.</p>

<p>I think I should describe a little of the technical aspects of Friendezvous as well. Friendezvous was built using the good old LAMP stack. We used PHP and MySQL along with front-end technologies/frameworks such as HTML, CSS, jQuery, jQuery UI, Bootstrap (modified), Angular JS. The development itself was not the difficult part. The hardest part of this journey was to think as an user of this platform. How would an user using Friendezvous feel about the workflow of this app? Is it too complicated? Can we improve on the workflow to minimise the number of steps/clicks an user is required to make to achieve an objective? These are the various questions which were running on our minds all the time. After all, software/app development is not just about blinding writing code.</p>

<p>There is much more to that.</p>

<p>We are dealing with real life users here. Then, we decided to conduct a survey to analyse the perception of our target audience towards the platform. We did it with a closed circle of friends and received very positive feedback. It was definitely a morale booster to our idea and efforts. More than anything, we were passionate about what we did. Even if we made a positive difference in a single person’s life, it would mean a lot to us.</p>

<p>Orbital Splashdown, where all the teams (from beginner, intermediate &amp; advanced levels) came together to showcase their work, was held on 19th August 2015. It was exhilarating to see so many applications built by students like myself. I was inspired by many apps, with their technical aspects as well as the business models they were planning to develop.</p>

<p>I was extremely joyful when the visitors to my booth exclaimed “Wow, that is one app I think I would use!” or “This is an excellent app bro!”. They were also impressed at the various features like notification tracking and location suggestions Friendezvous offered.</p>

<p>On the whole, Orbital 2015 was an exciting journey. I am going to make it a point to develop an application every summer. I find fulfilment in learning so many technologies.</p>

<p>As for Friendezvous, currently it is available here: <a href="http://friendezvous.herokuapp.com">Friendezvous</a>.</p>

<p>Development is very active and Al and myself aim to launch Friendezvous as a commercial platform soon (in about 3-5 months). After which, we are planning on porting this towards an Android and iOS application as well.</p>

<p>Do try Friendezvous if you can and send me your comments in the comment box on my blog or to my <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#097;&#114;&#105;&#115;&#104;&#050;&#048;&#055;&#064;&#108;&#105;&#118;&#101;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>

<p>Details on the Orbital programme is <a href="http://orbital.comp.nus.edu.sg/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Virtual Reality - Google Cardboard</title>
	  <link>/blog//Virtual-Reality</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-07-12T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Virtual-Reality</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I got a Google Cardboard yesterday. The Google Cardboard comes as a laser-cut template (which you have fold and fix yourself), two 45mm biconvex lenses, 2 neodymium magnets, 2 pairs of velcro and a rubberband.</p>

<p>It’s really simple to fold and use and all you’ve to do is to download a VR app onto the phone and slot it into the font of the Cardboard.</p>

<p>A great thing about the Google Cardboard is that it utilises the magnetic switch as a trigger. So while using an app, using the ‘button’ will allow you to interact the same way as you touch your phone’s screen. As compared to other VR devices, such as the VR One, the magnetic switch is something exclusive to the Cardboard.</p>

<p>There are many apps such as the Cardboard app (which allows you to watch movies, use Google Earth etc.), VR Roller Coaster (which takes you on a ride through the roller coaster) and the apps are definitely growing in number in the App Store.</p>

<p>Virtual Reality is definitely here to stay and it’s development excites me. It opens up many new and different possibilities that people have only dreamt of. We can start to enjoy experiences which previously required us to be physically present elsewhere. The nascent virtual reality is rapidly developing.</p>

<p>Whether virtual reality is good or bad, that depends. There will always be people who might use VR technologies to enjoy in the world they want, without any grasp of reality. But on the other hand, VR’s potential can surely bring quality and happiness to many lives. For now, let’s hope that VR will bring us a more enjoyable future in the coming years!</p>

<p><a href="#images">Below</a> are pictures of the Google Cardboard.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

<hr />

<div id="images">
<img class="cardboard" src="/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image2.jpeg" />
<img class="cardboard" src="/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image3.jpeg" />
<img class="cardboard" style="height:450px" src="/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image6.jpeg" />
</div>

<style type="text/css">
	.cardboard{
		width: 500px;
		border-radius: 15%;
	}
</style>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Clean & Green Hackathon 2015</title>
	  <link>/blog//Clean-&-Green-Hackathon</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-06-22T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Clean-&-Green-Hackathon</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://www.cgs.sg/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/For-Event-Subpages.jpg" /></p>
<p>Image Credits: http://www.cgs.sg/events/calendar/hackathon/workshop/</p>

<p>I participated in the Clean &amp; Green Hackathon this weekend. This is second hackathon I participated in after Gamecraft (Organised by NUS Games Development Group) last year. It was particularly a very enriching experience. Held on a larger scale (nation-wide) and open to all ideas and hacks (including hardware, software, apps, games etc.) and people from all age groups, I was able to understand what to expect in a hackathon.</p>

<p>Unlike a continuous 24 hours hackathon, we were allowed to go home and return the next morning. It took place over a period of 3 days, starting from Friday (Ideation and pitching) till Sunday (when the judging and prize presentation was held).</p>

<p>I got to know many people from different backgrounds and learn a lot from their ideas as well. Some were just there for the pure fun of it, to exchange ideas and make good friends. Some ideas were just excellent and gave me many new insights into further development of my own idea.</p>

<p>This time, my team (Kenny, Yong Zhi &amp; myself) came up with the idea of a web &amp; mobile ready platform called “The Greenlist”. It is basically a peer-to-peer connecting app where one can post his/her old items (eg: laptops, handphones, toys, books, furniture etc.) up for donation.</p>

<p>Anyone who needs this item but are willing to have it secondhand (and for free) can simply claim this item, and thereafter proceed to collect the item from the donor themselves. Each successful donation earns the donor some reward points which can then be redeemed for vouchers. To fund the operating costs (which are minimal), we proposed</p>
<ol>
    <li>In-App Advertising</li>
    <li>In-App Purchases (Eco-friendly items etc.)</li>
    <li>Sponsorship for vouchers</li>
    <li>Optional donation before claiming an item</li>
</ol>
<p>Once the idea was formed, we made a prototype both for the web and mobile platform (using Justinmind software).</p>

<p>On Sunday, as the group leader, I made the pitch for our idea and gave a demo of our prototype. Given only 3 minutes for the pitch, it was crucial to make the most out of each and every second to create an everlasting impression of the idea &amp; product/service. Though nervous, having take some public speaking training and course in NUS allowed me to focus on the pitch and do my best.</p>

<p>One of the learning points was that I realised that I might have focused too much on the demo of the prototype itself. I should have instead allocated a major part towards helping the audience understand and appreciate the relevance and usefulness of the app in their lives.</p>

<p>Also, the idea is crucial in a hackathon (even more than the prototype)! An effective idea will definitely win people over.</p>

<p>Though, my team did not win, we were thankful for the experience. This hackathon gave me some crucial experience that will help me do better in the forthcoming hackathons I will be participating.</p>

<p>“The Greenlist” project is hosted <a href="https://github.com/harishv7/thegreenlist">here</a>.</p>

<p>The Clean &amp; Green Hackathon event was covered by Channel NewsAsia and the coverage <a href="http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/ideas-to-solve-littering/1931422.html?cid=fbsg">available here</a>.</p>

<p>The photos of the Hackathon are <a href="https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.842836635769622.1073741869.310427622343862&amp;type=3">available here</a>.</p>

<p>More details on the teams and ideas which won and competition details are <a href="http://www.upsingapore.com/events/clean-green-hackathon-2015/#hackathonhome">here</a>.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Gamecraft 2014</title>
	  <link>/blog//Gamecraft-2014</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-05T18:18:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Gamecraft-2014</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I recently took part in Gamecraft 2014, organised by NUS Games Development Group (GDG). My first so-called “hackathon” experience. Glad to have worked with great teammates, Alvian, Chris &amp; Tio. Learnt a lot from one another.</p>

<p>In the given 24 hours and under the theme of “Contact”, we had to design and build a working game! This was a tough task, since we had to ideate within a short span of time and build a working prototype.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, some of my teammates had prior experience with platforms such as Gamemaker and Unity which allowed us to have a clear vision of how exactly are we going to execute our gameplan.</p>

<p>Below is the link to final copy of the 2D game, titled “ConTag”, which also won us the 2nd Prize in Gamecraft 2014!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/o2snaeg836jelzr/AAD-Lxa5URgMqDPM-J8G1cr9a?dl=0">Download ConTag</a></p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
