<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Most Powerful Thing in the World</title>
	  <link>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-20T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Have you ever wondered what is the most powerful thing in the world?</p>

<p>Well, its not money, not wealth, maybe love, but really I think its an idea.</p>

<p>Yup, an idea. Every single day, we see ideas that change and craft the world. From the phone in your hand to the computer you’re reading this blog on, every thing around us took root from the idea that came up in someone’s brain.</p>

<p>But when you think about it, an idea isn’t something tangible. Not any physical product you can touch and understand. Nevertheless, you can feel it. And if an idea is powerful enough, it can change the world for the better, or for the worse.</p>

<p>I particularly felt galvanised watching Inception. Inception is basically about implanting someone else’s idea into a target’s subconscious, deep enough, that it changes their way of thinking. Well, an idea seems like a simple thing. But the potential and the potency of an idea goes beyond itself. It creates a chain reaction so complex that without that single idea in a person’s brain, the world might have been different.</p>

<p>The idea right now, in your head is something so powerful. Make sure it is put to good use. To make a change for the better.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you really want something, all the Universe conspires in helping you achieve it. -The Alchemist, Paulo Coelho</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a quote I always remember. What you are, who you are is defined by your ideas, your actions. If you have a good idea, and truly believe in it, then give it your best shot. Make your ideas come alive.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
