<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>NOC Interview (Round 1)</title>
	  <link>/website//NOC-Interview-Round-1</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-05-25T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//NOC-Interview-Round-1</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I went for the NOC interview a few weeks back, just before my final examinations for semester 2. As it was mentioned in the confirmatione email, it was agroup interview indeed. My session was on the morning of Thursday and had about 8 people including me.</p>

<p>We were divided into 2 groups and given a hypothetical situation to discuss upon. In my case, we were given 2 simple business models (not as complex as you think) and then we had to discuss which business model will be more successful in the long run. The interviewers were very friendly and approachable. It is crucial to note that the interviewers are NOT looking for a correct answer. In fact, there is no right or wrong answer and it depends entirely upon how you feel. As long as you and your groupmates agree upon a common model and explain in as much detail as possible why it is the better one, you would have done your job.</p>

<p>In such group interview situations, the best way to make an impression is to try and lead the discussion from the start, which I did. So, instead of sitting around and looking at each other in awkward silence, initate the discussion and the overview. It was a good thing that all members of my team agreed uniformly on the model I had in mind. Then, immediately after settling the main topic of discussion, I tried to model the scope of the discussion by listing out the relevant factors to the topic. After which, I decided on the factors I will be presenting and the subsequent allocation of the other factors for my group members to present.</p>

<p>Overall the presentation went very well and at the end of the discussion it seemed that the interviewers did agree with our choice of model. I was happy to receive the news that I have successfully passed the first stage of the selection and am current anticipating the second round of interview coming soon in August/September.</p>

<p><strong>Points I learnt: </strong>
You are being noted once you step into the interview room. Everything that you say and do will have an impact on the impression the interviewers have on you.
Learn to be concise. It’s not necessary to talk as much as possible to show that you are good. Being concise will show that you have a clear mind and are focused on what you are doing.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>I need an Internship!!</title>
	  <link>/website//I-need-an-Internship</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-09T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//I-need-an-Internship</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Every computer engineer who is passionate about what he does will want to create or inspire a change that makes a difference in this world. Many a times, these inspirations, to even start, does not come from just pure academics, but rather from the practical experiences we gain.</p>

<p>Recently, I came across the this post which shows the best places where we can develop ourselves and get the inspiration we have always been looking for.</p>

<p>As listed on Business Insider, the top tech internships are offered by:</p>

<p>Google
Qualcomm
Microsoft
Intel
Cisco
IBM
Amazon
Apparently, the interview difficulty in getting the internship increases as we climb the list. Well, at the same time the salary increases (ranges between $5k – 6k) too. So you get what you work for despite the stiff competition.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it is not only the best tech giants that can provide good internships. A good internship is one where we can learn to the fullest, about the process of not only creating ideas, but implementing it into a practical solution that yields tangible and visible results.</p>

<p>The best place where we can get such an experience will definitely be the start-up sectors. Here is where true entrepreneurship flourishes. Here is where we can learn the nitty gritty details of kicking off from the ground, to flying the plane, and landing at the destination. And here is where, you learn to unveil the entrepreneur in you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.aminariana.com/essays/ultimate-internship">Related article</a></p>

<p>Let’s take the unconventional path to do the greater good in the world. Where’s the fun when everyone wants to the conventional things in life. Risk-taking and courage are truly the qualities of the successful leaders we see today.</p>

<p>A small quote from Apple:
<img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg" />Image Credits: <a href="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg">staticflickr.com</a></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
