<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Ask NOC - Honestbee & Shopback Sharing Session</title>
	  <link>/blog//askNOC-Session-Review</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-28T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//askNOC-Session-Review</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Recently, I attended 2 talks during askNOC. There were two invited guests: Jonathan Low from Honestbee and Henry Chan from Shopback. Both companies are startups, having only been in the market for around a year or so. Today’s sharing was largely focused on their business and how they overcame the various challenges.</p>

<p>Honestbee is a concierge and online delivery service for grocery shopping. So essentially, customers can place orders online for groceries or items found at common supermarkets such as NTUC. The ‘bees’ from the company are actuallly people who will shop the necessary items and deliver them to you in an hour. I personally found this a great idea for a number of reasons.</p>

<p>Firstly, there is a huge incentive for consumers to use this product because there are no additional costs. The items are bought at the same prevailing price at the supermarket. Secondly, consumers can order from the convenience of their home. Thirdly, as mentioned by Jonathan, this is an asset light model. There are no storage or warehouse involved. Every purchase is made directly at the supermarket which means storage is well taken care of. Essentially, the only services that they are providing will be the shopping and delivery of items. They are able to grow well with the use of technology. For example, internally they use an Android app that allows ‘bees’ to receive orders. Nevertheless, Jonathan mentioned that currently it is still exists as a manual process. This can definitely be automated to reduced much of the overhead costs. An order can immediately be routed to a free ‘bee’ together with the list of items etc. Doing so will help save time and manpower costs as well as allow them to garner good analytics into the demographics and patterns of their customers.</p>

<p>Talking about how Honestbee works, Jonathan also provided some good insights into the business model. They utilise a revenue share model. Taking an example of an order of $100, they will be able to obtain a 20% commission. Out of this $20, their overall profit is only $10 as shown below.
$20-$5(shopper cost)-$5(delivery  cost) = $10</p>

<p>There are several teams in Honestbee which work together. These include: business, customer service, product (engineering, design, data), operations teams. He emphasised the crucial need for each of these teams to work hand in hand and communicate effectively.</p>

<p>Jonathan also shared the various challenges he faced. Factoring in the customer acquisition costs, each customer only turns profitable from the fifth order onwards. Also, he mentioned the poor visibility they have on stock availability. This is especially true due to their reliance on the supermarket to have the various products they are looking for.
Also, delivery costs are only minimised with economies of scale.</p>

<p>The second talk was by Henry Chan from Shopback. Shopback is based on the idea of customers getting cashbacks on their online purchases. Henry provided some great insights on e-commerce as a whole. He pointed out that e-commerce in Southeast Asia has a very low penetration rate which essentially means a huge growth opportunity for the next 5-6 years. One of the key markets to tap on will be Indonesia where online shopping and mobile penetration rates are growing rapidly. Henry also emphasised that entrepreneurs must be willing to learn and have the hunger to achieve and that expanding your business is all about having the right people around you. This pointed out the importance of networking, about having good contacts in the business world.</p>

<p>When asked how his business adapts to smaller markets where technology is generally less advanced, he said that such a situation is indeed a good opportunity where you can have greater expansion and tap deeper into the market.</p>

<p>One of the interesting questions was if both the founders give employees stock options. I felt that this is a great way to align employees’ interests together with the company’s goals. While stock options may not guarantee any value, this orientation towards a common goal is crucial in my opinion.</p>

<p>Lastly, both of them provided an important tip for budding entrepreneurs:Don’t be shy in validating your idea. One of them even mentioned, that they requested people in Starbucks to test drive their prototype and gain feedback. I am sure validation is a crucial part every new product has to achieve and this must be done early in the prototyping stage itself.</p>

<p>Learnt a lot from this session and definitely looking forward to the next session.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Lessons from Entrepreneurs</title>
	  <link>/blog//Lessons-from-Entrepreneurs</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-02T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Lessons-from-Entrepreneurs</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Over the past semester, I undertook a module in NUS known as “Journey of the Innovator” (CP2201). More than just a module, it was conducted in an interesting and engaging seminar style. Each week, many lessons on entrepreneurship were shared and in one of the weeks, 3 startup founders were invited to share their views and insights into entrepreneurship.</p>

<h2 id="klinify">Klinify</h2>

<p>The first talk was by Krish, the CEO and Founder of Klinify. Personally, I found Klinify’s mission to “provide the freedom of paper with the power of digital technology” intriguing. It aims to propagate a change within the medical industry and empower doctors to harness the strengths of technology to further improve the medical services being delivered. During his talk, Krish mentioned some importants points on entrepreneurship that he has learnt thus far. I have combined those pointers, together with my learning points from the talk:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Focus on a specific sector: Klinify’s target audience are very specific. It is specifically targeted at the providers of medical service, doctors. While their ultimate goal is to extend the platform of Klinify globally, their current milestone is to establish themselves in Singapore and in Asia.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Klinify offers hybrid storage: This might be a little technical. Conventionally, a patients records (in paper) are only available physcially in the hospital. However, by digitalizing medical recors, now patient records are both available locally and on the cloud. By sharing it on the cloud, the medical records are now more accessible than ever. This could even offer a centralised patient records system to help doctors view and understand the patient’s medical history well before treatment.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Reasons for Klinify’s potential success: Klinify does not aim to change doctors’ natural way of doing things. Their workflow remains the same. Doctors are still able to write like they do on paper. They have customised templates. They can attach photos and even annotate. All these features help doctors to transition from their current pen-and-paper workflow to the digital platform with ease.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Some concerns on Klinify: Security. Technology rules today’s world. However, the growth of technology has brought about potential incentives for people to expose data. Medical records are meant to be private. In an event of a security breach, millions of medical records can be leaked. However, during the talk, Krish did mention their focus to ensure the safety and privacy of patient records. And only a strong defence system can deter such security compromises.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lomotif">Lomotif</h2>

<p>The second talk was by Paul from Lomotif. Lomotif is essentially a mobile application that allows users to create a video from their stash of videos and even add songs to it. After using it, a clear winning point of Lomotif was the usability factor. It was very simple to use and even a novice mobile user will be able to use it easily. 
Some pointers from Paul:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Market saturation: There will be a point in time when your target market becomes saturated. And Paul mentions that we should definitely anticipate this. To overcome this, we need to try and leverage on another market. I think this can be done in a couple of ways. Various markets are segmented by factors such as age, culture and perception. Hence, an expansion into another market requires a change in the app / technology that addresses one or more of these factors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Some interesting features of Lomotif: It’s collaborative, expressive and fun. This fun factor is one of the main reasons which helps Lomotif stand out from its competitors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>3 Crucial Factors:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>Good Team</li>
      <li>Customer Acquisition</li>
      <li>Making your customers happy.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="investing-note">Investing Note</h2>

<p>The third talk was by Shanison from InvestingNote. InvestingNote is a social network site targeted specifically at investors in Singapore and in the regional space.</p>

<p>Upon using the InvestingNote platform, I like the user-friendly interface and the summarised view of stocks/shares and other information. Personally, I believe that such a social-platform can be of great use to investors. Facilitating communication among investors is something new I have seen and if brought about to the target market correctly, I believe this can be a good success.</p>

<p>I feel the above pointers are critical in ensuring the success of the start-up. While it may be true that most start-ups fail eventually, I think keeping the above pointers in mind will definitely aid them to beat the market.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
V.Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Entrepreneurship - Yay or Nay?</title>
	  <link>/blog//Entrepreneurship-Yay-or-Nay</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-08-24T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Entrepreneurship-Yay-or-Nay</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Today was an exciting day. Having taken the CP2201 module, Journey of the Innovator, today was the first 2 talks by self-made entrepreneurs and businessmen, Steve Melhuish from PropertyGuru and Samuel Lim from Reebonz.</p>

<p>The entire session focused on how they built their business from scratch and the hurdles they went through.</p>

<h3 id="several-important-points-were-highlighted-throughout-the-session-such-as">Several important points were highlighted throughout the session, such as:</h3>

<ol>
  <li>For an entrepreneur, his focus should be on innovation.</li>
  <li>Having a solid business model is crucial. The growth in online traffic (for web/mobile based businesses) helps to convert losses to profits.</li>
  <li>Think big, and expand big.</li>
  <li>Professionalise your business and scale appropriately.</li>
  <li>Invest in a good team with good leaders (CFO, CTO, CEO etc.).</li>
  <li>With the best content and most traffic you can make it to be #1 in the market.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="firstly-to-summarise-my-learning-from-propertyguru">Firstly, to summarise my learning from PropertyGuru:</h3>
<p>The idea of PropertyGuru was to allow transparency of information in the property market by placing the entire market online to solve a real-world issue: Everyone needs a home!</p>

<p>Several growth tactics were used to leverage on the growing population in emerging countries, rising smartphone and broadband penetration rates and increasing trend of online marketplaces and online transactions.</p>

<ul>
  <li>It is crucial to ensure that there is ongoing PR to keep the publicity going with the media, so that people are aware of you and your business.</li>
  <li>Pick the ideal investor who is not only interested in the money made by the business, but rather willing to support the business with growth and opportunities. A strategic investor should bring intelligent information to provide insight on the current situation of the market.</li>
  <li>Size and Valuation</li>
  <li>Pitch Documents: Keep some documents ready at hand, both a 2-page document and a 20-page version, to pitch to others.</li>
  <li>Competitive tension: If many investors are interested, we can potentially increase the valuation of the business. Get as many parties interested as possible.</li>
  <li>A good M&amp;A lawyer: It is important to have a good Mergers &amp; Acquisition (M&amp;A) lawyer to prevent ‘unwanted’ takeovers.</li>
</ul>

<p>A business today will face challenges on different levels, such as:
- Scaling (Revenue &amp; Costs involved)
- Increasing levels of competition: No longer limited to the local scale, but rather we are competing on a regional or even global scale.
- Staying nimble</p>

<p>Some great quotes I found during the presentation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Good companies meet needs, Great companies create markets”</p>

  <p>“As an entrepreneur always be paranoid of competitors and them taking away your market!”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-second-part-of-the-presentation-was-focused-on-reebonz">The second part of the presentation was focused on Reebonz:</h3>

<p>Important points for aspiring entrepreneurs:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Little cash/capital is no longer a worry today. Innovation is largely valued and ideas can be executed with web/mobile apps which have minimal costs.</li>
  <li>Focus on market adoption. Even if your ideas are novel and you have your product ready, the market must be ready to adopt it.</li>
  <li>For a business to survive in the long run, we need to adapt to the market landscape.</li>
  <li>Focus on cutting loss. Ideas may need to change, don’t fall in love with your idea.</li>
  <li>Growth is dependent on cash/capital. Find and learn to manage venture capital.</li>
  <li>Stay true to your core beliefs and idea. Build the business model around this idea.</li>
  <li>Adopt niche areas, where you can differentiate from other businesses.</li>
  <li>Value and invest in customer relationships. This will help in gaining faster adoption and long-term customers.</li>
  <li>Maximise existing resources to create value.</li>
</ul>

<p>Some great quotes from the second-half of the session:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You don’t need the best team, but the right team”</p>

  <p>“The hardest about evolving a business model is keeping true to your core brand idea”</p>

  <p>“Instead of finding places where there is already competition, find niche areas where you can dominate the business”</p>

  <p>“See opportunities in problems”</p>

  <p>“Get a MVP, or beta model and launch it. Only then you will receive feedback on what the market wants.”</p>

  <p>“Only the paranoid survives” – Quoted from Andrew Grove, Co-Founder of Intel</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All in all, a very fruitful session that stirred up the entrepreneur within me. The world needs change, and only innovation can drive that change. And entrepreneurs can lead that innovation. In that regard, I am motivated to become an entrepreneur myself to help make positive difference in the world.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
