<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>I Need an Internship!</title>
	  <link>/blog//I-need-an-Internship</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-09T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//I-need-an-Internship</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Every computer engineer who is passionate about what he does will want to create or inspire a change that makes a difference in this world. Many a times, these inspirations, to even start, does not come from just pure academics, but rather from the practical experiences we gain.</p>

<p>Recently, I came across the this post which shows the best places where we can develop ourselves and get the inspiration we have always been looking for.</p>

<p>As listed on Business Insider, the top tech internships are offered by:</p>

<p>Google
Qualcomm
Microsoft
Intel
Cisco
IBM
Amazon
Apparently, the interview difficulty in getting the internship increases as we climb the list. Well, at the same time the salary increases (ranges between $5k – 6k) too. So you get what you work for despite the stiff competition.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it is not only the best tech giants that can provide good internships. A good internship is one where we can learn to the fullest, about the process of not only creating ideas, but implementing it into a practical solution that yields tangible and visible results.</p>

<p>The best place where we can get such an experience will definitely be the start-up sectors. Here is where true entrepreneurship flourishes. Here is where we can learn the nitty gritty details of kicking off from the ground, to flying the plane, and landing at the destination. And here is where, you learn to unveil the entrepreneur in you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.aminariana.com/essays/ultimate-internship">Related article</a></p>

<p>Let’s take the unconventional path to do the greater good in the world. Where’s the fun when everyone wants to the conventional things in life. Risk-taking and courage are truly the qualities of the successful leaders we see today.</p>

<p>A small quote from Apple:
<img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg" />Image Credits: <a href="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg">staticflickr.com</a></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
