<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me/</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>NUS Third Year | First Semester in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-Third-Year-First-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-12-11T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-Third-Year-First-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2> CG3207: Computer Architecture </h2>

<p>CG3207 was one of the most informative, educational modules I have taken.</p>

<p>This module answered many of the questions which was always running in my head: “How computers function so smoothly managing several tasks simultaneously?”, “How do the building blocks of computers actually come together in building a computer?”, “How does a processor function?” etc.</p>

<p>That being said, it was definitely and undoubtedly a challenging module. It requires some fine skills in Assembly and Verilog/VHDL. The course structure is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>15% Quiz (3 quizzes, Happens during lecture itself)</li>
  <li>45% Labs (Comprises 4 Lab Projects - 1 individual, 3 group)</li>
  <li>40% Finals</li>
</ul>

<p>There are 3 quizzes which occurs during the lecture period itself. They mostly comprise simple questions which test your understanding of 2-3 chapters. The challenging part comes during the labs which take up significant amount of time. Each of the group project are linked which eventually results in a complete processor.</p>

<p>The finals consists of several short-answer questions with a slight emphasis on the last few chapters: Arithmetic for Computers, Memory System Principles, Pipelining, Advanced Processor Design.</p>

<p>Overall a great module. Challenging due to the time involvement for the various group projects.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CG3002: Embedded Systems Design Project </h2>

<p>This is one of signature modules in Computer Engineering. This design project, done in a group of six, is really heavy in terms of the time commitment it requires.</p>

<p>In this project, we were required to build a <strong>indoor</strong> navigation system for the visually challenged. We were given some equipment to begin with such as Arduino Mega, Raspberry Pi (version 1), sensors (infrared, ultrasound etc.), IMU.</p>

<p>It was definitely a new experience for me in putting together software and hardware to achieve an embedded system.</p>

<p>Grading is split into a few checkpoints with the two of the milestones as the major component. This project is definitely not something which can be done by one or two people. Every member in your group must be fully involved, cooperative and motivated to complete the project due to the several tight deadlines you will encounter along the way. Coupled with deadlines from other modules, my team (along with other teams) spent several days staying late at college (sometimes overnight too).</p>

<p>A piece of advice for team formation is to have members specialised in various fields such as software, hardware and firmware. It’s crucial to have a kind of leader who can manage deadlines aptly.</p>

<p>Overall a great experience in building the project despite the various tight deadlines which spiked our stress levels at times.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> EG2401: Engineering Professionalism </h2>

<p>This module mainly serves to build upon the professional work ethics an engineer should uphold in his/her career. There are 4 main sections revolving around the topics of ethical theories, academic research ethics, plagiarism and professional code, engineering and environmental concerns &amp; intellectual property (copyrights, patents, trademarks).</p>

<p>The module is graded as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Continual Assessment - 50% (Tutorial Participation - 20%, Research Project - 30%)</li>
  <li>Final Exam - 50%</li>
</ul>

<p>As seen, the module has an extra emphasis on the participation during tutorials. The research project mainly involves some research on current fields/topics on engineering with an analysis of the ethics involved in those fields.</p>

<p>The final exam (closed-book) consists of some structured and essay questions covering the various concepts/practices etc. taught during lectures.</p>

<p>Overall, a relatively manageable module.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CS3244: Machine Learning </h2>

<p>This was one of the modules I looked forward most. Though it was pretty different from what I expected, it was somewhat enriching in providing a good overview and understanding of what the field of machine learning is all about and how it is used widely in almost every aspect of our technologies today.</p>

<p>I was surprised by the significant amount of math involved in this field initially. The math involved mostly Calculus and Linear Algebra. Coming from a Computer Engineering background I was not very familiar with the parts on Linear Algebra.</p>

<p>This semester machine learning was widely revised under the new professor Prof Kan Min Yen. Prof Min mentioned this syllabus is vastly different from the what was taught in previous semesters. There was equal emphasis on both theory and practical aspects of machine learning.</p>

<p>Prof Min followed the content taught at Caltech by Prof Abu Mostafa. It was easy to revise lecture content by watching the Caltech lectures available on YouTube for most of the chapters. The grading of the module comprises the following components:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Midterm: 20%</li>
  <li>3 Homework assignments (2 written @ 10%, 1 programming mini project @ 15%): 35%</li>
  <li>Participation (via IVLE forums, tutorials): 5%</li>
  <li>Final Exam: 40%</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall a challenging module due to the math involved as well as the abstract concepts which take some amount of time to understand and appreciate.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> EE3204: Computer Networks </h2>

<p>This module mainly serves as an introduction to computer networks and their developments over the past few decades. The module is divided into 2 main parts by 2 lecturers. Part 1 focuses on introduction of network concepts and ethernet layer. Part 2 covers majorly on the transport and network layers of OSI network architecture and TCP/IP.</p>

<p>I found this module to be pretty interesting as it explained how the Internet, something we depend upon for our daily activities, actually functions. The module was graded as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Socket Programming Lab (20%)</li>
  <li>Midterm 1 (15%)</li>
  <li>Midterm 2 (15%)</li>
  <li>Final Exam (50%)</li>
</ul>

<p>The module was pretty manageable. Consistency in keeping up with lecture topics was an important factor to do well in the exams and labs.</p>

<p>Cheatsheet available <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obclFxSDBXdENRVjA">here</a>.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆</p>

<p>This semester was a test of my time-management, leadership skills and determination. Managing the workload of the various modules together with the application for ATAP/Industrial Attachment was definitely not an easy task.</p>

<p>Looking forward to my 6 months internship next semester!</p>

<p>Till next time, cheers.</p>

<p><em>Harish V</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS Second Year | Second Semester in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-Second-Year-Second-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-06-09T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-Second-Year-Second-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2> CS2010: Data Structures &amp; Algorithms II </h2>

<p>This module is one of my favourite modules in this semester. Usually CS2010 is taught by Prof Steven Halim, but it was Dr Brown this semester who is teaching this module for the first time in NUS. Dr Brown was really great and funny as well. He tried to bring across the concepts taught very well and in my opinion one of the coolest professors I have seen. Once I required an extension to one of the important lab assignments and he was so chill about it and totally understands students’ positions. Also, this is a must-take module for any computer science person as it introduces the key algorithms that has made the tech world around us possible.</p>

<p>The course weight he is divided into assignments, labs, lecture quizzes, mid term and final exams. Yes, the weightage is pretty diversified across the various components. It’s important to be consistent in this module as the further weightage for each lab or assignment would also vary depending on the difficulty. The rough breakdown of the course weightage is:</p>

<ul>
  <li>In-lecture exercises (8%) – Mini-assignments done during lecture</li>
  <li>Lab exercises (12%) – Similar to assignments but shorter and easier</li>
  <li>Four Assignments (40%) – Weighted differently depending on difficulty</li>
  <li>Exams (40%) – Midterm + Final</li>
</ul>

<p>The course structure is basically an introduction to trees, heaps, hash tables in the first half followed by a heavy focus on graphs in the second half.</p>

<p>Overall a great and crucial module to take for  any computer science or engineering student.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: A</p>

<hr />

<h2> EE2024: Programming for Computer Interfaces </h2>

<p>This module was one of the heaviest, if not, the heaviest module I have ever taken. The course mainly focuses on Assembly language in the first half and low-level C programming for computer interfaces in the second half. Both halves consist of a related project done in pairs. While the first project is largely manageable, the second project is huge and is extremely time intensive. In fact, I don’t remember doing anything other than this module in the last 3-4 weeks of the semester. My partner and myself came to NUS at 10am and left at 10pm daily for these weeks. It was an extremely challenging period.</p>

<p>Tip for projects is to 1) Start early &amp; 2) Use the resources around you to learn fully (both online &amp; offline).</p>

<p>While this module is definitely useful as it gives great in depth understanding of how devices around us were programmed and interfaced, the content was so heavy that I couldn’t get enough time to appreciate everything I learnt. Nevertheless, the module helped me understand the importance of several technologies such as UART, master-slave protocols etc and their applications.</p>

<p>Final exams were slightly hard as expected. Nevertheless, Prof Rajesh went through all the past year papers one by one during the last few weeks as solutions to the papers are not released. That really helped to clarify a lot of the learning gaps and also on the expectations for the final paper.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆☆</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: A-</p>

<hr />

<h2> CG2271: Real-Time Operating Systems </h2>

<p>Overall a great module. Took this under Prof Tulika. This is actually the CEG counterpart module of the CS version of Operating Systems. Hence most of the focus was on the lower level areas.</p>

<p>The module is structured into labs, midterms and finals. Also, there is a small component for tutorial attendance. Most of the earlier labs are manageable. However, as we moved along into the later parts, I found the labs to be harder not because of the concepts but mostly the debugging of programs and identifying where we went wrong. Hence, it became a little time-intensive too. Labs are done in pairs using a Spark fun (Arduino) kit.</p>

<p>Attending lectures (or watching webcasts) is important to help in the understanding. I actually enjoyed this module quite a bit. And after the module was completed, I began appreciating the use of many of the concepts I have learnt. Concepts such as semaphores, mutexes are so crucial and they are being used everywhere around us.</p>

<p>Final exams were pretty hard as compared to the midterms, but manageable.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: A</p>

<hr />

<h2> ST2334: Statistics </h2>

<p>Statistics is a useful and slightly easier than the other modules I took this semester. However, easier means others will also find it easy. I guess the competition for the module was a little high.</p>

<p>The notes were pretty self explanatory out of the times and there are plenty of problems to practice. Both midterms and final exams were pretty okay.</p>

<p>Module structure is mostly based on IVLE quizzes, tutorial attendance, tutorial participation, midterms and finals. Important tip for this module is to be consistent. And the lecturer did make sure we are consistent by giving online quizzes each week and tutorials on alternate weeks.</p>

<p>Cheatsheets I used for the mid-terms are <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obZ0RWQkJGYUlLOVE">here</a>.</p>

<p>Cheatsheets I used for the final exams are <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1oba2UyN2QzRFVRaVU">here</a>.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: B+</p>

<hr />

<h2> CG2023: Signals &amp; Systems </h2>

<p>Signals and Systems was an intimidating module for me at first. Looking at so much math and complex terms didn’t help in motivating myself to study. However as time went by, I realised it wasn’t that hard after all. The only requirement to do well in this module is the investment of time. Understanding of the concepts comes over time and dedication  to read the notes again and again. Do this till you understand. Whenever I felt unsure, I used the recommended textbook to write down a few problems and solve then to check my understanding.</p>

<p>For midterms and finals, it is very crucial to practice a lot of the past year papers to clarify on the difficulty level and on what is expected.</p>

<p>The professors were also kind and helpful whenever we approach them with questions. For this module, we just need the discipline to sit down and invest some time in the understanding of the concepts taught.</p>

<p>Cheatsheets I used for the mid-terms are <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obc0NZNUp5T0JoSnM">here</a>.</p>

<p>Cheatsheets I used for the final exams are <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obMk5kWU5mdk1LM0E">here</a>.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: A</p>

<p>As usual, it was the most hectic semester I’ve had. Till next time, cheers.</p>

<p><em>Harish V</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS Second Year | First Semester in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-Second-Year-First-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-22T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-Second-Year-First-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>The past semester is definitely the busiest semester I have been through. There was literally no time for anything else other than studies and projects. Part of the reason (as you will see), is that I took 8 modules this time. However, one of them, CP3108B - Orbital has already been completed. Two of the other modules CP2201 and CFG1001 lasted only for the first half of the semester, thankfully. This allowed for a slightly relaxed timetable in the second half of the semester.</p>

<p>Right now, I am really glad that I managed to do my best through the semester. And for those who are anticipating such a semester, I felt you might find a review of the modules handy. So here it is:</p>

<hr />

<h2> CP 2201: Journey of the Innovator </h2>

<p>This is a module about entrepreneurship and is worth 2 MCs. The grading is also in the form of Completed Satisfactorily (CS) or Completed Unsatisfactorily (CU) which means that the grade obtained will not affect the current CAP you have.</p>

<p>Personally, I found this module to be very engaging and entertaining. It provided me with what I wanted to learn about entrepreneurship. Each week, there were invited guest speakers who share their experience on entrepreneurship. A typical outline of the module looks like this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Week 1: Introduction to module and some basic information</li>
  <li>Week 2: Guest speakers from PropertyGuru and Reebonz with Q&amp;A</li>
  <li>Week 3: Guest speakers from upcoming startups: Klinify, Lomotif and InvestingNote with Q&amp;A</li>
  <li>Week 4: Guest speakers from Red Dot Ventures and Golden Gate Venture with Q&amp;A</li>
</ul>

<p>Each week, there will be a short assignment which requires some reflection on various aspects of entrepreneurship as well as the guest speakers and the companies.</p>

<p>All in all a great module to learn from entrepreneurship.</p>

<p>PS: Oh did I mention that there is a buffet dinner and networking session for 30 mins weekly?</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CS2101: Effective Communication for Computing Professionals </h2>

<p>This is a twinned module with CS2103T (see below). Basically, this module teaches you to write and present your ideas in an effective manner. Communication skills, writing skills and presentation skills are the 3 most crucial skills required to do well.</p>

<p>I found this module good as I was able to pick up on the above-mentioned skills. However, there are a number of continual assessments for this module since there are no final exams. This means you will be kept busy almost every week.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, some of the CAs are simple activities like doing a reflection on communication or your oral presentations. Some of the assessments I remember doing are:
- Reflection on Communication Skills &amp; Commenting on others’ reflections
- Oral Presentation 1 (OP1)
- Writing a Project Proposal
- Writing of a Progress Report on the software project
- Oral Presentation 2 (OP2)
- Reflection 2 on OP2 &amp; Commenting on others’ reflections
- Writing of a Project Manual (Developer and User Guide)</p>

<p>To do well in this module, it is crucial to have the enthusiasm and appreciation for what you are doing. Of course, that will also help you to be more participative in your class (participation is also counted for grading). Also, I cannot emphasise enough on having a good team who can support you in these tasks. This is definitely not a one-man-army type of module for you to do alone. Effective teamwork is important in bringing out the best in most parts of the module.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CS2013T - Software Engineering </h2>

<p>I have been looking forward to this module for some time. Personally, I love software engineering and development.</p>

<p>This module was personally very enriching and I got to learn a lot in terms of the various software engineering principles. That being said, this is one of the most hectic modules. As a team of 4, we were tasked to build a desktop-based task manager from scratch which had a primary input through the keyboard. By task manager, I mean a productivity software akin to popular ones like Google Keep, Todoist, Wunderlist, Any.do etc.</p>

<p>The grading of the module was divided into 3 main areas: Project (50%), Final Exam (40%) and Participation (10%). As such, the project hold the majority of the weightage and that makes this module different from conventional ones. We apply what we learn. Every week, the lecture introduces new principles and concepts relevant to software engineering. Much of these knowledge can be immediately applied to the project we are doing.</p>

<p>CS2103T is also twinned with CS2101 (as described above). Hence, many of the things we do such as developer’s guide, user guide etc. are relevant to the project. The use of version control (Git or GitHub) is extremely crucial for the project and came in really handy. We are prone to introduce bugs/errors when 3-4 people “operate” on the code simultaneously. Having revision control allowed such to keep track of these changes and simply revert our changes if we found them to be buggy later on.</p>

<p>The participation segment is the easiest to score and you should definitely score the full 10% here. Points can be earned through the proper completion of pre-tutorial and in-tutorial activities, answering questions in lectures, successful completion of weekly lectures quizzes on IVLE etc. There is maximum cap of 200 points which means that any points exceeding the 200th mark will not contribute to the participation points for grading.</p>

<p>The final exam tests the skills we have learnt throughout the semester. If you have learnt and applied these concepts well for the software project, it will be much easier to score here. The CS2103T module handbook (a 200-page document/textbook companion) is a must-read for scoring well for the exams. It helps to reinforce the concepts learnt and clears the small gaps in understanding.</p>

<p>On a personal note, I learnt a lot through this module. My team and I managed to create quite a cool desktop application called “FINI”. The name inspired from French, in which Fini refers to finished or accomplished. We felt that this accurately represents the goal of our app and it was easy to remember too! 
These are some of the screenshots of the application:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/rwUcDNl.png" alt="FINI's Welcome Screen" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/c6qWEbI.png" alt="FINI's Overview" /></p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/OIFjxyi.png" alt="FINI's Screenshot" /></p>

<p>Over time, my team and I became really passionate about what we were doing and we even made a cool video for our Oral Presentation 2 in CS2101 and to also serve as an introductory product demo video during our CS2103T demonstration. Here it is:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/utI1N5hhFSs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Video Credits: Jonas, Team FINI</p>

<p>FINI is available for download and use here: <a href="https://github.com/cs2103aug2015-t16-1j/fini/releases/tag/v0.5">GitHub Link</a></p>

<p>Overall, an interesting yet hectic module. If you love creating cool stuff, you will love this module.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆	☆ ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> EE2020 - Digital Fundamentals </h2>

<p>This is a 5MCs module which is split into 2 parts. The first part is relatively easier to understand and introduces the basic building blocks of computers such as logic gates. The second part is focused mostly on slightly more intricate topics such as Finite State Machines (FSMs).</p>

<p>There are also lab and project components in this module. The labs are mostly manageable and primarily introduces the use of FPGAs and the hardware description language known as Verilog. The project is done individually and it involved creating an oscilloscope out of the FPGA. This was really cool because oscilloscopes generally cost many hundreds of dollars. Using a simple FPGA to create an oscilloscope was indeed interesting!</p>

<p>Most of it involved writing Verilog for the FPGA to interpret and display the incoming signal from the signal generators in the lab. The project was graded individually with a range of criteria. Two main influencing factors are the number of features (such as scaling, translating, displaying words/labels, pointers) and the uniqueness of the features <em>as compared to your peers</em>.</p>

<p>There are no final exams. Instead there is a midterm quiz and final quiz (each 20%) and the rest of the assessment is based on labs and projects.</p>

<p>On the whole, a manageable module. Be creative with the project.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆ ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> EE2021 - Devices and Circuits </h2>

<p>This module has a lot of theory and formulas on semiconductors. Personally, I found it quite intensive and usually took me the most time out of all my modules to revise and gain a complete understanding of what was being taught.</p>

<p>The assessment for this module is Homework (10%), Midterm test (20%), Quiz (5%), Final Exam (65%), though I do not remember taking a quiz for the 5%.</p>

<p>The topics covered were very structured starting from the building blocks and slowly moving on to bigger components: Semiconductors -&gt; PN junctions -&gt; Bipolar Junction Transistors (BJT) -&gt; Metal Oxide Semiconductors Field Effect Transistors (MOSFET) -&gt; CMOS Logic -&gt; Single Stage Amplifiers -&gt; Multistage Amplifiers -&gt; Opamps.</p>

<p>This was really overwhelming and was like a bit of PC1432 again. The first part (before midterms) is usually much easier to understand than the second part. So make sure you ace the midterms.</p>

<p>On the whole, a difficult module indeed due to the time commitment for understanding and revision. If you can appreciate what you learn, it will greatly help in the learning process.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆ ☆ ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> LAF1201 - French 1 </h2>

<p>I took this module out of curiosity and the eagerness to learn a new language. I had shortlisted Chinese, Hindi and French and finally decided on French.</p>

<p>Why? Firstly, we need to understand that learning a language takes considerable time and effort to both learn, grasp and then practice speaking it. And doing all this while juggling other modules during a period of 1 semester is not a joke. French is apparently written with English alphabets with some accented ones. Also, it is similar to English or rather English is similar to French. As compared to other languages like Chinese and Hindi, this meant that I do not need to spend extra time learning to write the new alphabets which would help to save a considerable amount of time.</p>

<p>I must say French was really awesome. The people I met were mostly from FASS, but there were a few of them like me from Engineering or some from Pharmacy and Business. I really liked like environment. It was very interactive and my lecturer Dr Daniel Chan made sure everyone participated in each lesson. The interaction and fun during lessons made me like French even more. To ensure this interaction, all lessons are tutorials (no lectures).</p>

<p>Workload wise, since there are no final exams, you will be having tests / quizzes / homework more frequently than you would have expected to. There are quizzes on the French culture, vocabulary, grammar, audio recording of a self-introduction, writing of an email for an imaginative scenario etc. The final test is an oral conversation between 2 you and two others from your group in front of the lecturer.</p>

<p>I would say it is relatively easy to score for the tests if you have consistently practised French (both writing and speaking). That being said, also means that your peers will score well. Personal advice is to revise the notes posted on IVLE and use Google Translate to its fullest capability. I also utilised the <a href="https://www.duolingo.com">Duolingo</a> app (web &amp; mobile) to learn much of the content. Oh yes, if you have an iPhone, you can set the language for Siri as French and converse with it in French. It’s quite cool and you can also check on your pronunciation by seeing if Siri understands what you just said.</p>

<p>All in all, a very enjoyable module taught by a great lecturer.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CP3108B - Independent Work (Orbital Programme) </h2>

<p>I participated in the Orbital programme during the summer break before my semester 1. I have written a post on the Orbital experience which is available <a href="http://harishv7.github.io/blog/education/nus/college/techstuff/2015/08/19/Orbital%202015/">here</a> and <a href="https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/08/20/orbital-2015">here</a>.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆	☆</p>

<hr />

<h2> CFG1001 - Headstart Module </h2>

<p>While this is a 0 MCs module to prepare you for your career, there is a reason I have written about it here. Before attending the sessions, I was a little complacent and thought of this module as something that is snatching my precious time away. However, upon attending the module, I thought differently.</p>

<p>This module helps to expose how it is like in the “real” world outside of NUS. Preparing for a career also includes preparing for the various interviews, networking with others etc. And it helped me understand and appreciate the importance of many skills and pointers which will definitely come in handy during my interview applications etc.</p>

<p>This module is graded with a Completed Satisfactorily (CS) or CU (Completed Unsatisfactorily) grade. You’ll just need to attend all the 2-3 face-to-face sessions to get a CS grade.</p>

<p>Difficulty (out of 5): (Nil)</p>

<hr />

<p>And, I just realised I have 4 consecutive exams in the coming semester!</p>

<p>Guess I need to mentally prepare for it. After all, the only easy semester was the last semester!</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Orbital 2015</title>
	  <link>/blog//Orbital-2015</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-08-19T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Orbital-2015</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5EjaKFa.png" alt="Friendezvous" /></p>

<p>After 3 months of hard work, the Orbital programme came to a close on 19th Aug 2015. It was a great experience and I picked up many skills of both front and back end development. I did the project with Al who was very supportive during the 3 months though he was on vacation.</p>

<p>The project’s inspiration came from our shared experiences in daily college life. Many of the times we tend to organise meetings manually. A typical process goes like this (A,B,C are persons).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A–&gt;B: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? <br />
B–&gt;A: Yup, that’ll be good I guess. <br />
A–&gt;C: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? <br />
C–&gt;A: Oh no, I don’t think I’ll be free. How about some other day? <br />
A (thinks to him/herself): Darn, got to ask B and C for another timing again! <br /></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As shown above, the typical manual process is tedious where we often WhatsApp or message one another for free slots and try to match it all up for a common time to meet. In the point of view of the meeting administrator, it is a rather painstaking process when he/she has to repeatedly ask the team members for a suitable time to meet.</p>

<p>To solve this issue, I suggested to Al that we should maybe develop a platform which can make the organising of meetings simpler and redefine the ways of doing so. And from there, Friendezvous was born. Friendezvous is an amalgamation of the words Friend and Rendezvous (a meeting at an agreed time and place). So essentially Friendezvous refers to meetings with friends, colleagues etc. And we decided on a relevant tagline as well: “Organising meetings, redefined.”.</p>

<p>I think I should describe a little of the technical aspects of Friendezvous as well. Friendezvous was built using the good old LAMP stack. We used PHP and MySQL along with front-end technologies/frameworks such as HTML, CSS, jQuery, jQuery UI, Bootstrap (modified), Angular JS. The development itself was not the difficult part. The hardest part of this journey was to think as an user of this platform. How would an user using Friendezvous feel about the workflow of this app? Is it too complicated? Can we improve on the workflow to minimise the number of steps/clicks an user is required to make to achieve an objective? These are the various questions which were running on our minds all the time. After all, software/app development is not just about blinding writing code.</p>

<p>There is much more to that.</p>

<p>We are dealing with real life users here. Then, we decided to conduct a survey to analyse the perception of our target audience towards the platform. We did it with a closed circle of friends and received very positive feedback. It was definitely a morale booster to our idea and efforts. More than anything, we were passionate about what we did. Even if we made a positive difference in a single person’s life, it would mean a lot to us.</p>

<p>Orbital Splashdown, where all the teams (from beginner, intermediate &amp; advanced levels) came together to showcase their work, was held on 19th August 2015. It was exhilarating to see so many applications built by students like myself. I was inspired by many apps, with their technical aspects as well as the business models they were planning to develop.</p>

<p>I was extremely joyful when the visitors to my booth exclaimed “Wow, that is one app I think I would use!” or “This is an excellent app bro!”. They were also impressed at the various features like notification tracking and location suggestions Friendezvous offered.</p>

<p>On the whole, Orbital 2015 was an exciting journey. I am going to make it a point to develop an application every summer. I find fulfilment in learning so many technologies.</p>

<p>As for Friendezvous, currently it is available here: <a href="http://friendezvous.herokuapp.com">Friendezvous</a>.</p>

<p>Development is very active and Al and myself aim to launch Friendezvous as a commercial platform soon (in about 3-5 months). After which, we are planning on porting this towards an Android and iOS application as well.</p>

<p>Do try Friendezvous if you can and send me your comments in the comment box on my blog or to my <a href="&#109;&#097;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#111;:&#104;&#097;&#114;&#105;&#115;&#104;&#050;&#048;&#055;&#064;&#108;&#105;&#118;&#101;&#046;&#099;&#111;&#109;">email</a>.</p>

<p>Details on the Orbital programme is <a href="http://orbital.comp.nus.edu.sg/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS First Year | Semester 4 | (Special Term 2) in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-First-Year-Semester-4</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-First-Year-Semester-4</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://www.wreporter.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/CyberSecurity.jpg" alt="Computer Security" /></p>

<p>Being quite free during the summer vacation period, I decided to take up CS2107: Introduction to Information and System Security in Special Term 2. It was one of the most interesting modules I have taken taught by an ever youthful professor Hugh. His energy and enthusiasm and deep knowledge on computer security made me even more curious in the various aspects of computer security.</p>

<p>This module covers a wide range of topics from cryptography/ciphers, to common hacking methods (SQLi, Buffer overflows), protection mechanisms against such malcious attacks etc. The assessment was split into the following:</p>

<table>
	<tr>
		<td>Homework &amp; Assignments</td>
		<td>Project Work</td>
		<td>Final Exam</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>10%</td>
		<td>40%</td>
		<td>50%</td>
	</tr>
</table>

<p>There were a total of 3 assignments (about 5-10 questions) which were to be done at home. They were largely manageable. Google is your best friend. Computer security is a broad topic and the more you learn, the better you understand and appreciate the various concepts.</p>

<p>The project work was indeed an interesting experience. My team consisted of Sri (not his real name), QY and myself. It was a tight timeline considering that the project was to be completed over a span of just 6 weeks. We embarked on the project about 2 weeks before submission, but we made the structure of the report very clear. Regular consultation with Prof Hugh was crucial in helping us achieve a clear understanding of the expectations of this project. As a team, we are really thankful for his advice and guidance.</p>

<p>Our project was on “Common attacks on PC/UNIX/Mac devices”. Here focused on DDoS, Buffer Overflow exploitation and side-channel attacks. I personally involved myself largely towards the buffer overflow section in which I did code sample runs to check the implementation of a feature known as Address Space Layout Randomisation (ASLR) on Windows 8, Mac OS X 10.10 and Ubuntu 15.04. We also compared the effectiveness the various operating systems against the aforementioned attacks and concluded Windows offered the best protection (of course, in reality there will be a wide range of external factors to be considered as well).</p>

<p>The final exam was manageable. I was able to refer to the relevant sections of the notes since it was an open-book examination. Some questions are specifically targeted at your understanding and some were on concepts mentioned in lectures. I guess it paid off to attend each and every lecture and tutorial.</p>

<p>I am really glad I took this module. It is one of the best modules I have taken in NUS thus far and am currently contemplating taking CS3235 (Introduction to Computer Security) sometime later. Then again, the number of required breadth electives for CEG students has been reduced to just 1 which means I need to plan my modules well.</p>

<p>Also taking it in Special Term was great since it allowed me to concentrate fully on one subject. In the regular semester, with 5-6 modules, juggling time between these modules itself is a huge task for most students.</p>

<p>Difficulty: <strong>Manageable</strong> <br />
Grade obtained: <strong>A-</strong> <br />
Remarks: Pretty interesting module taught by an amazing professor. Take it!</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
V.Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS First Year | Second Semester in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-First-Year-Semester-2</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-06-04T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-First-Year-Semester-2</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>It has been a long freshman year and I am surprised I am already writing a review for my 2nd semester at NUS. Semester 2 was much tougher than Semester 1, but ironically my grades were slightly better (yes, I can’t believe it too!).Thanks to the bell curve I suppose. Anyway, here is the module review:</p>

<hr />

<h2>CG1108: Electrical Engineering</h2>

<p>A good module that introduces the basic concepts of electrical engineering. I found the pace of the lectures very manageable compared to other modules. The total number of chapters covered is actually not a lot, and hence it allows you enough time to fully comprehend and grasp the basic concepts before moving onto the next chapter.</p>

<p>My lecturer for this module was Dr Sahoo. He is a very approachable lecturer and teaches very well. I find it important to attend his lectures (never missed any) since most of the working and examples are done in the lecture itself. Though the slides with the digitally written solutions are uploaded, it is much easier to follow through the lecture and examples in real time rather than at home where you have to figure them out all by yourself.</p>

<p>The assessment of the module is shared equally between the hands-on segment and the theory section. Hands-on segment includes the labs (10% attendance and 10% lab test) and the exciting Arduino car project (25%). Labs are manageable and you will be guided by your group’s assigned mentor. The lab test is very similar to whatever content you have learnt during the practical labs and make sure to watch the equipment briefing video uploaded by the ECE department to have a complete knowledge of the equipment and how to use them.</p>

<p>The car project was what many of us were looking forward to. There was a lot of time given for us to work on the car project. It is of high importance that you select your groupmates carefully. They must appreciate your suggestions and be willing to help each other out and put in a good amount of effort to work together and achieve the target.</p>

<p>What I did not like about the car project was the lack of constant results. The car basically takes input from the light-dependent resistors (LDR) and these resistors are very sensitive to the ambient light which makes it difficult to get consistent results. Nevertheless, I think the car project was one of the most exciting parts of the module. I still remember my friends’ and my reaction when our car worked for the first time!</p>

<p>The theory section includes the mid-term test (10%) and final exam (40%). Both exams were manageable and as long as the basic concepts and application has been mastered it should not be a problem to score well. For the final exam, practising past year papers is crucial in understanding the type of questions to expect.</p>

<p>Grade obtained: <strong>A</strong> <br />
Difficulty: Average</p>

<hr />

<h2>GEK1549: Critical Thinking and Writing</h2>

<p>GEK1549 was quite enjoyable. Like many, I did not like this module initially, but as time went, I began appreciating what was being taught. It is very systematic and really probes your thinking. The theme for our batch was on “Sustainable Cities”.</p>

<p>There are no lectures, only tutorials. My tutor was Dr Sadorra. She is really nice and approachable and gave me and my teammates very constructive comments and suggestions during the course of the module. She also prepares her own slides and provides good external references to clarify concepts.</p>

<p>Assessment is divided into 3 parts. Assignment 1 (30%) requires the submission of a graphic organiser, summary and evaluation of a given article. Assignment 2 (30%) is a position paper that is done in groups. And Assignment 3 (10%) is essentially class participation. The other 30% comes from the final exam.</p>

<p>I was able to do particularly well in both Assignments 1 &amp; 2 and made effort to participate in class as much as possible. I felt the final exam was doable, but I was restricted due to the lack of time. Make sure you have good teammates for Assignment 2. Always have a clear foundation and roadmap as to what you will be doing for the position paper. In my case, for the problem-solution paper, I made sure that the problem and solutions are clearly linked. And to make our paper stand out, my teammates and I ensured that the proposed solutions were specific to the city and are feasible in the implmentation. Not an easy task, but you’ll get there after some considerable time into research and analysis. Be sure to utilise NUS Libraries website. The resources there will surely aid in obtaining reliable sources for the paper.</p>

<p>All in all a very manageable module, provided you put in good effort in understanding the tutorials.</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: <strong>A</strong> <br />
Difficulty: Average</p>

<hr />

<h2>CS1020: Data Structures and Algorithms I</h2>

<p>This was my favourite module of this semester due to my personal interest in computer programming. But, this was definitely not a easy module. The content covered were heavy and it requires a lot of practise and understanding to get used to the concepts taught. And before you are familar with one concept another concept will be taught. It requires discipline and effort to do some programming and to study for the module daily.</p>

<p>Lecturers for this module are Mr Aaron Tan and Dr Low. Both lecturers are very good in terms of teaching new concepts. They give plenty of examples to ensure our understanding is complete. It is important to attend and understand tutorials. Even when I couldn’t do or finish a particular tutorial, I made it a point to attend classes to ensure I do not neglect the tutorial. It kept me on track.</p>

<p>Assessment for the module was divided into many parts:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Tutorial Attendance/Participation</td>
<td>7%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lab Attendance</td>
<td>3%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Take-Home Labs</td>
<td>11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sit-in Labs</td>
<td>24%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mid-term Test</td>
<td>15%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Final Exam</td>
<td>40%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The least you can do is to secure the marks from tutorial/lab attendance and take-home labs. This is greatly help in achieving a good grade. Take-home labs are often challenging, but you will given at least a week before the submission. Hence, ensure that you are able to solve these labs. Else, seek help during the lab sessions. The tutors are really helpful when you ask questions.</p>

<p>It’s a fast paced module. On any given week, you will most probably either have a sit-in lab or a take-home lab due. Consistent work and practice is of vital importance.</p>

<p>The final exam was slightly tough for me. I realised I have made many careless mistakes after completing the exam. Otherwise, the difficulty of the questions asked were similar to those in tutorials. Focus on important topics such as recursion, hashing, sorting etc. These are major concepts that have a higher probability of being tested.</p>

<p>All in all, a tough and fast paced module that definitely requires more effort than what you normally put in for a 4MC module. Discipline to revise and practice questions (on Codecrunch) on a regular basis is important from the start of the module.</p>

<p>Some of my codes are hosted <a href="http://harishv7.github.io/portfolio/">here</a> and on <a href="https://github.com/harishv7">Github</a>.</p>

<p>Cheatsheet for final exam is now hosted <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BwSVKyZQM1obbzVJUTBXWFIzVkk/view?usp=sharing">here</a>. (Please do write your own, this is only for reference, not reproduction).</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: <strong>A-</strong> <br />
Difficulty: Tough</p>

<hr />

<h2>PC1432: Physics IIE</h2>

<p>This was the toughest module for me. The rate at which chapters and concepts were covered was astonishing. I could barely keep up with the pace and was lost even before the recess week. It did not help that many of the chapters were inter-linked.</p>

<p>There were a total of 3 lecturers. All of them were engaging and taught really well. But, it required a lot of effort from my side to fully grasp what they were saying and taking time to practice extra questions outside the tutorials. The questions from the tutorials are NOT enough as practice. The recommended textbook was really helpful for me to get a better understanding of the concepts.</p>

<p>Assessment was divided into practical viva/reports (10%), online assignment from Mastering Physics (10%), mid-term test (20%) and final exam (60%).</p>

<p>Ensure that you do your best for the practicals and online assignments as these are relatively easier to score. The mid-term was manageable except for the time restriction. Planning your time during the examination is crucial.</p>

<p>I found the final exam very hard and was afraid I did not do as well as I expected.</p>

<p>All in all, a fast-paced and tough module.</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: <strong>A-</strong> <br />
Difficulty: Very Hard</p>

<hr />

<h2>MA1506: Mathematics II</h2>

<p>MA1506 was much more manageable than MA1505, which I took in semester 1. This module covers a great depth into Differential Equations and linear algebra, linear transformations and Laplace transforms. Many of these concepts are crucial for engineering students.</p>

<p>Assessment is divided into mid-term test (20%) and final exam (80%).</p>

<p>The first part involving differential equations (DE) was fairly manageable and was even fun when modelling systems. All it requires is a good understanding of the various ways to solve DEs which can be achieved with sufficient practice from tutorials. The mid-term test was fully MCQ (10 questions in one hour) and was quite easy. I was able to score full marks for this one.</p>

<p>After recess week, the pace of lectures started to increase together with the difficulty of concepts. Webcasted lectures were really helpful when I was revising to clarify my doubts.</p>

<p>Final exam was manageable. Make sure you have sufficient practice form the past year papers (check NUS Library website or IVLE). Since there are solutions provided, it helps to understand the structure of the questions. Questions are usually similar year to year.</p>

<p>Make sure the help sheet (2 sides of 1 A4 sheet) is well prepared. You can see my help sheets <a title="MA1505 &amp; MA1506 Help Sheets" href="https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/05/26/ma1505-ma1506-help-sheets/" target="_blank">here for reference</a> or <a title="MA1505/MA1506 Helpsheets" href="http://harishv7.github.io/nus/2015/05/26/MA1505%20&amp;%20MA1506%20Help%20Sheets/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<p>All in all, a manageable module, provided sufficient effort is put in to understand fundamental concepts.</p>

<p>Grade Obtained: <strong>B+</strong> <br />
Difficulty: Manageable</p>

<p>Hope the above reviews and tips were helpful! Comments are welcome (use the Disqus thread below).</p>

<p>Cheers,
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS Gradeless First Semester</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-Gradeless-First-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-29T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-Gradeless-First-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>NUS has introduced gradeless first semester since AY2014/15. And I am from AY14/15 batch. Though gradeless semester seems enticing, there’s really more to it. There are some conditions and pointers to take note which will leave you confused if you’re not used to the NUS system.</p>

<p>Some things to know: NUS utilises the Cumulative Average Point (CAP) to determine the performance of a student.</p>

<p>Formula for determining CAP: <img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-126" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/screen-shot-2014-12-24-at-1-29-19-pm.png?w=300" alt="Screen Shot 2014-12-24 at 1.29.19 pm" width="300" height="32" /></p>

<p>Basically the numerator is the sum of the product of module credits and grade points and the denominator is the sum of the module credits for ALL the modules taken so far. It’s crucial to note the cumulative function of the CAP. Hence, it is not determined on a per semester basis, but rather for the 3-4 years of modules taken.</p>

<p>To maximise the S/U options given during the gradeless semester, there are some things to note first.</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the class of degree you're aiming for.
<ul>
<li>Degrees awarded are classified as shown (taken from NUS website):
<table border="5" style="width:100%">
<tr>
<td><strong>Honours Degree Classification</strong></td>
<td><strong>Criteria</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Highest Distinction)</td>
<td>CAP 4.50 and above</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Distinction)</td>
<td>4.0 to 4.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Merit)</td>
<td>3.5 to 3.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours</td>
<td>3.0 to 3.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pass</td>
<td>2.0 to 2.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fail</td>
<td>Below 2.0</td>
</tr>
</table>

<li>Note the Grade Point table:
<table border="1" style="width:100%">
<tr>
<td><strong>Letter Grades:</strong></td>
<td>A+</td><td>A</td><td>A-</td><td>B+</td><td>B</td><td>B-</td><td>C+</td><td>C</td><td>D+</td><td>D</td><td>F</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Grade Points:</strong></td>
<td>5.0</td><td>5.0</td><td>4.5</td><td>4.0</td><td>3.5</td><td>3.0</td><td>2.5</td><td>2.0</td><td>1.5</td><td>1.0</td><td>0.0</td>
</tr>
</table>
</li>
<li>If the target is Honours (Highest Distinction), then a CAP of 4.50 and above is required by the end of your 3-4 years. To achieve this, the average grade for the modules you took for 4 years must be at least an A-.</li>
<li>Therefore, during the S/U option, S/U anything below A- is a good option, since it will increase the number of modules with grades A- and above</li>

</li>
<li>If the first semester is a good indication of the performance for the rest of the semesters, then S/Uing any modules with a gradepoint below your CAP is a good idea. For example, your CAP is 4.44, and your grades are A,A-, A,B+,B+, then S/U modules below 4.44 which are the 2 B+.</li>
<li>The gradepoints allocated to the grades, for example 4.0 for a B+ means it will pull your overall CAP towards the 4.0. Hence, unless the overall CAP is below 4.0, then B+ would not really help with pushing the CAP upwards.</li>

</ul></li></ol>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS CAP Calculator</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-CAP-Calculator</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-28T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-CAP-Calculator</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Here is a CAP calculator I made in excel. Just a simple excel sheet that helps to keep track of your grades. Feedback welcome and updates will be made to add other functions.</p>

<p>Click here to download <a href="assets/cap-calculator1.xlsx">CAP Calculator v1.0</a>.</p>

<p>Update! : V1.1: <a href="assets/cap-calculator2.xlsx">CAP Calculator v1.1</a></p>

<p>(Note: this was done to be just used as a guide. Check with faculty for degree requirements and the NUS FASS calculator if necessary).</p>

<p>Inspired from <a title="Agagooga's CAP Calculator" href="http://gssq.entori.net/files/capcalc.htm" target="_blank">Agagooga’s CAP calculator</a>.</p>

<p>A better CAP calculator with better user interface is coming, for the web, desktop and mobile platforms. Stay tuned! :)</p>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS First Year | First Semester in Review</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-First-Year-First-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-25T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-First-Year-First-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>It’s has been a great semester. Well, it was stressful, but it was particularly fulfilling. University life is exciting as I get to learn what I am most passionate about. The gradeless semester is another point that allowed me to read the modules without worrying too much about grades. Nevertheless, I was never aiming to SU any modules. Here is a quick review of the modules I took in Semester 1. All of them are pre-allocated since I am a Computer Engineering student, except the GEM I took.</p>
<hr />

<h2>CG1001: Introduction to Computer Engineering</h2>

<p>The title of this module sums it up all. This module is meant to provide an overview of Computer Engineering for freshmen and allow them to have a clear understanding of what areas they can specialise in during their senior years. Basically, the workload is not much. <br />
I was tasked with 2 reports (based on the specialisation areas in Computer Engineering) and a project video. The reports are 25% each and the video is 50%. Reports are done in pairs (randomly grouped by the professor). Similarly, for the project video, you will be assigned a group of four randomly. Then you have present a video (about 5 mins long) which presents the topic chosen in a creative and informative way. My group chose the topic on 4G LTE networks. We personally did it in the form of an advertisement and incorporated animation to make the video more interactive. This module is meant to help you pull up your CAP (though it is only 2 MCs). Give it your best, especially for the reports. Be creative and analytical when discussing the selected topic.</p>

<p>Grade I obtained: <strong>A</strong><br />
Very much delighted to have obtained an A. I had really given my best for the reports and the video (especially the animation and planning).</p>

<hr />

<h2>CS1010: Programming Methodolody</h2>

<p>This was my most favourite module of this semester. I have no experience programming in C language. However, I was familiar with other languages like Python, Javascript and HTML. I personally like programming very much. The natural interest motivated me to do my best for this module. However, do not worry if you have no previous programming experience. Make sure you start learning the basics well, and do one practice task per day (there’s plenty of tasks on the CS1010 website). My lecturer was Mr Gary Tan. He is one amazing lecturer. He makes learning enjoyable and he is really funny. I am really happy to learn under him. He offered us a lot of help (separate group discussions and marking my past-year CS1010 papers I did for practice). <br /></p>

<p>The lectures are taught in a flipped-classroom method. You are expected to revise the slides and notes before the lectures (held in computer labs). This is very important indeed. Despite the long lecture, it’s not enough to cover all the concepts thoroughly. It requires many hours of practise to get the programming concepts and fluency expected of you. The module grading is broken up into 2 practical exams (10%, 25%), 1 mid-term test (15%), take home lab assignments (5%), attendance (5%) and the final exam (40%). I did not do well for the 2 practical exams. The first one was especially bad. Though I had good practice, the exam stress itself and the pressure under time restrictions made me panic. As a result, I was not able to complete the 2 tasks on time. <br /></p>

<p>Another mistake was that I focused on code logic and clarity, thinking that these criteria were also awarded significant marks. However, only after the exam did I know that close to 60% will be awarded for the correct output. Hence, focus on obtaining the right output. Your code may be inefficient, but it is your output that is being considered. Therefore, note that you are being awarded the marks for your ability to complete the task. The take home lab assignments are quite challenging. Try your best to complete it during the weekends. Last-minute stress is never good. Consult your friends and lecturers if you do not know how to do them. Lastly, and most importantly, finish the task within the suggested time limit (comes in helpful for the practical exams). Attendance and the lab marks (5% each) are really a giveaway for this module. Utilise it well and don’t skip tutorials unless you have a valid MC. The final exam was quite easy for me, except for one question. I guess it helped me to make up for the practical exams which I did not do as expected. <br /></p>

<p>Final grade for CS1010: <strong>A-</strong> <br /></p>

<p>Not exactly very happy with A-. Being my favourite module, I had really wanted an A+. But the practical exams pulled my overall grade down. :/</p>

<hr />

<h2>CS1231: Discrete Structures</h2>

<p>I personally did not like this module when I first started. But as it progressed, I began to appreciate this module. It provides a different view to common concepts. You learn to prove everything. For example, you learn to prove that an even number plus another even number is even. Such seemingly simple things which we just assume to be true must be proven. One of the coolest things you’ll learn is to prove that 1+1 = 2. Well, if before this module, someone asked me to prove that I would have been stunned. But now, I do have an answer that proves this to be true. <br /></p>

<p>Lecturers for the module were Prof Stephen Bressan and Prof Bryan Low. Both of them were good. Prof Stephen likes to ask interesting questions on the topic and invites your opinions and answers. But he does cover the chapters very quickly (especially the proofs). Prof Bryan Low was good too. He actually goes through every proof that is in his notes and makes sure that you understand it clearly. Both lecturers are really approachable. Make sure to clear your doubts immediately after the lecture (before you forget them). That being said, this module is really demanding as the pace of the lectures is extremely fast. The tutorials are really crucial for you to grasp the application of the concepts learnt during lectures to the questions in your tutorials. Personal advice: Do NOT skip the tutorials. The recommended textbook is Discrete Mathematics Demystified. I found it barely enough to understand all the concepts taught. Nevertheless, it helped me greatly to comprehend the basic concepts in each chapter. For challenging exercises, see past year questions or ask your tutor. <br /></p>

<p>The module is graded based on a video project, a mid-term test and the final exam. As for the video project, my team focused on exploring the game of Tic Tac Toe. The video has been embed here:</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Mo1_F806J_I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The video project is meant to help you to pull your grade up. Do give your best in terms of analysing and presenting the chosen topic. The mid-term test was quite easy and the final exam was moderately difficult. Some questions only required common sense, while others really tested the concepts and formulas you’ve been taught. All in all, a content-heavy module that can be done well with consistent practise and dedication to learning the concepts well.</p>

<p>Final grade: <strong>A</strong> <br /></p>

<p>Really happy with the grade as I did not expect it. :)</p>

<hr />

<h2>GEM2027: Public Speaking</h2>

<p>I had to choose to do a SS/GEM/breadth module in the first semester. Public speaking was the only module that fitted my timetable and the skill itself seemed really useful. Plus a bonus was that there were no exams. Of course, instead of the final exam, you will be graded on some of the speeches and there will be a module quiz at the end as well as a video project to be delivered. Lecturer for the module is Ms Cardoza. She is a very good lecturer and I like her enthusiasm in each lecture. She is very approachable (both personally and on forums) and encouraged me to give my best in my speeches. The lectures basically introduces some tips and pointers for effective public speaking. Some are really common sense, but the thing is that many of us fail to follow them. We need to remember simple things like body language (eg: do not put your hands in your pockets) and tone which will be critiqued by your tutor. Such seemingly simple pointers will be reinforced again and again throughout the module. <br /></p>

<p>The graded speeches are Informative (15%), Persuasive (20%) and Responders-Critique (15%). The other 50% is for the quiz and video. While there was plenty of time given for each speech, personally it really took up loads of time to prepare a good speech. It wasn’t as easy as writing the speech alone. Firstly, the speech category is broad. Hence, you will naturally spend quite a bit of time thinking on which topic you should speak about. Second, the preparation requires hours of research and analysis to support your points (any claim you make must be supported to establish your credibility to the audience). Third, you need to make your speech interesting, add some funny elements etc. Fourth, you need to practise again and again to ensure good body language and fluency of your speech. Fifth, if visual aids like PowerPoint is being used, you need to create the slides and practise controlling the slides. As you see, you need many hours of preparation before each speech. I usually use up my whole weekend doing the above. It wasn’t helpful that all my modules had tight deadlines to meet. Of course, if you’re someone who can manage your time easily or have prior experience in public speaking, this comes easy. <br /></p>

<p>Another factor is that the marks awarded for the speeches largely depend on how strict is your tutor is. Well, my tutor did have very high expectations since he speaks frequently at events and has a lot of experience in public speaking. Naturally, he expected a much more. Hence, the grade you get depends very much on your tutor too! Nevertheless, give your best and you will get what you deserve. The video project was really fun! We were free to do any video to express the ideas we have learnt in the course. My group created a comic-book type of video that is presented in terms of a storyboard. I enjoyed the project. Since it is due near the last week of the semester, you will barely have time to meet up for the project. Another downside was that my team members were all from different years of study (all of them were in Year 4 and from different faculties/majors). <br /></p>

<p>Hence, it was almost impossible to get a time-slot to meet and discuss. We had to do it right away after class. Surprisingly, our video got shortlisted as one of the top ten! But we did not win the top prize though. <br /></p>

<p>You can view the video <a title="Public Speaking - No Longer Clarkie's Kryptonite! " href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hOZsQ18Ufhs&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/hOZsQ18Ufhs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>Tips:</strong></p>
<ol>
	<li>Always take a topic you are well knowledgeable about and confident with.</li>
	<li>Try to be clear of the structure of your entire speech before deciding on it.</li>
	<li>It may help to write out the entire speech and then do the Preparation Outline (PO). All you would need to do is to copy and paste the relevant sections from the speech into the PO (with some rephrases, of course).</li>
	<li>Try to buy a clicker to control the PowerPoint slides when presenting, or ask your close friend to lend you one (like I did).</li>
	<li>Creativity is greatly rewarded in this module. Especially for your video project, presenting the learning points in a creative manner can help you achieve good marks!</li>
</ol>
<p>Final grade: <strong>B+</strong> <br /></p>

<p>Not very satisfied with this grade. I expected an A-. Nevertheless, I am sure I have given my best for this module. Public speaking is a skill you have keep developing anyway. Overall, it was a great experience.</p>

<hr />

<h2>MA1505: Mathematics I</h2>

<p>There are many concepts you need to understand for this module. Whenever you have free time, learn to utilise it to revise the upcoming topics. Though the lectures are nicely-paced, the amount of concepts to grasp requires quite some time. The last few topics (line and surface integrals may be difficult to grasp). The module is graded with a mid-term test (20%) and the final exam (80%). My lecturer for this module was Prof Leung Pui Fai (Fred). He is a very good lecturer. He takes the time to explain concepts very patiently. He is also very approachable. Make sure to pay good attention during the lectures. If you find the pace slow or you missed the lecture then you can always use the webcast on IVLE. <br /></p>

<p>Initial topics revolve around the ‘A’ level content such as differentiation, integration, functions, vectors etc. Hence, you might not need much time to grasp these concepts. However, for other topics like line integrals and surface integrals, you must be able to visualise what the formula you are using actually means. Everything you do will involved 3D manipulation. So, you have to visualise in 3D as well. This is the hardest part. Initially, I was a little lax about practise since I was able to do all the tutorial questions. <br /></p>

<p>The mid-term test was an eye-opener. The questions really test your understanding and are tricky. Mid-term questions are tricky and requires good thinking and speed to complete on time. Make sure to practise all the past-year papers which are available at IVLE and NUS e-library. It is a tough module, but with consistent practise you can do well. The one A4 paper (2-sided) cheat sheet really helps! Make sure to prepare your cheat sheet well. Ensure it is comprehensive and note that they are strict with the term “2-sided A4 sheet”. Only use a single A4 white paper to write notes on both sides. <br /></p>

<p>Final grade: <strong>B+</strong> <br /></p>

<p>I could have done better (especially in the MCQ mid-term test), but a B+ is not too bad I guess.</p>

<hr />

<p>All in all, it was a good semester. Despite the 3 video projects (video projects really take up a lot of time!), I learnt a lot through the term. I could have done better in MA1505 and CS1010, but it is all in the learning experience to not repeat your mistakes. Most importantly, I have learned to manage my time better and study for the love of learning. Not just for the grades. Looking forward to the next semester. Till then,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Stay Hungry, Stay Foolish!</p>
</blockquote>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>I Need an Internship!</title>
	  <link>/blog//I-need-an-Internship</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-09T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//I-need-an-Internship</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Every computer engineer who is passionate about what he does will want to create or inspire a change that makes a difference in this world. Many a times, these inspirations, to even start, does not come from just pure academics, but rather from the practical experiences we gain.</p>

<p>Recently, I came across the this post which shows the best places where we can develop ourselves and get the inspiration we have always been looking for.</p>

<p>As listed on Business Insider, the top tech internships are offered by:</p>

<p>Google
Qualcomm
Microsoft
Intel
Cisco
IBM
Amazon
Apparently, the interview difficulty in getting the internship increases as we climb the list. Well, at the same time the salary increases (ranges between $5k – 6k) too. So you get what you work for despite the stiff competition.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, it is not only the best tech giants that can provide good internships. A good internship is one where we can learn to the fullest, about the process of not only creating ideas, but implementing it into a practical solution that yields tangible and visible results.</p>

<p>The best place where we can get such an experience will definitely be the start-up sectors. Here is where true entrepreneurship flourishes. Here is where we can learn the nitty gritty details of kicking off from the ground, to flying the plane, and landing at the destination. And here is where, you learn to unveil the entrepreneur in you.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.aminariana.com/essays/ultimate-internship">Related article</a></p>

<p>Let’s take the unconventional path to do the greater good in the world. Where’s the fun when everyone wants to the conventional things in life. Risk-taking and courage are truly the qualities of the successful leaders we see today.</p>

<p>A small quote from Apple:
<img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg" />Image Credits: <a href="https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg">staticflickr.com</a></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
