<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>NOC Interview (Round 1)</title>
	  <link>/website//NOC-Interview-Round-1</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-05-25T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//NOC-Interview-Round-1</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I went for the NOC interview a few weeks back, just before my final examinations for semester 2. As it was mentioned in the confirmatione email, it was agroup interview indeed. My session was on the morning of Thursday and had about 8 people including me.</p>

<p>We were divided into 2 groups and given a hypothetical situation to discuss upon. In my case, we were given 2 simple business models (not as complex as you think) and then we had to discuss which business model will be more successful in the long run. The interviewers were very friendly and approachable. It is crucial to note that the interviewers are NOT looking for a correct answer. In fact, there is no right or wrong answer and it depends entirely upon how you feel. As long as you and your groupmates agree upon a common model and explain in as much detail as possible why it is the better one, you would have done your job.</p>

<p>In such group interview situations, the best way to make an impression is to try and lead the discussion from the start, which I did. So, instead of sitting around and looking at each other in awkward silence, initate the discussion and the overview. It was a good thing that all members of my team agreed uniformly on the model I had in mind. Then, immediately after settling the main topic of discussion, I tried to model the scope of the discussion by listing out the relevant factors to the topic. After which, I decided on the factors I will be presenting and the subsequent allocation of the other factors for my group members to present.</p>

<p>Overall the presentation went very well and at the end of the discussion it seemed that the interviewers did agree with our choice of model. I was happy to receive the news that I have successfully passed the first stage of the selection and am current anticipating the second round of interview coming soon in August/September.</p>

<p><strong>Points I learnt: </strong>
You are being noted once you step into the interview room. Everything that you say and do will have an impact on the impression the interviewers have on you.
Learn to be concise. It’s not necessary to talk as much as possible to show that you are good. Being concise will show that you have a clear mind and are focused on what you are doing.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
