<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Thoughts with Mass???</title>
	  <link>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-01-17T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif"><img class="size-medium wp-image-140" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/uni6.gif?w=250" alt="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif" width="250" height="300" />Image Credits: https://helenmagnani.wordpress.com/</a></p>

<p>As I was reading The Lost Symbol, by Dan Brown, there was an interesting idea shared which immediately awed me. It deals with the hypothetical question: “Do thoughts have mass?”. Though, on a weighing scale, thoughts may possess mass ranging in the nano to femto scale, if they do have a mass, there will be many implications.</p>

<p>One of which was presented in the book was on gravity. If our thoughts had some mass, they will be bound by the laws of physics. Which meant, they will exert a gravitational force on other matter (though the force is of a very very small scale). Despite the insignificant amount force by a single thought, when a group of people come together to think on the same idea, this collective force becomes significant. It might then start to attract others towards this idea or notion. And that, will be powerful, when a thought can attract others and influence them to think in a certain way too.</p>

<p>Although it is a hypothetical question, the implications simply awed me. Upon further thinking: With thoughts having some mass, they will also be bounded by the Law of Conservation of Energy. Thoughts cannot be destroyed entirely. Instead, the thoughts are simply converted from one thought/idea to another. Or, they may become converted into another form of energy (likely chemical energy) in the brain.</p>

<p>Indeed, it is fascinating to imagine the implications if such a hypothesis was proven to be real. Whether it is true if thoughts have mass or not, only time will tell.</p>

<p>A few of my favourite quotes on the power of thoughts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Change your thoughts and you change your world. <br />
<strong>Norman Vincent Peale</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are what our thoughts have made us; so take care about what you think. Words are secondary. Thoughts live; they travel far. <br />
<strong>Swami Vivekananda</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Concentrate all your thoughts upon the work at hand. The sun’s rays do not burn until brought to a focus. <br />
<strong>Alexander Graham Bell</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>A positive attitude causes a chain reaction of positive thoughts, events and outcomes. It is a catalyst and it sparks extraordinary results. <br />
<strong>Wade Boggs</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
