<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me/</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life, code and everthing in between.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>NUS Gradeless First Semester</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-Gradeless-First-Semester</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-29T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-Gradeless-First-Semester</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>NUS has introduced gradeless first semester since AY2014/15. And I am from AY14/15 batch. Though gradeless semester seems enticing, there’s really more to it. There are some conditions and pointers to take note which will leave you confused if you’re not used to the NUS system.</p>

<p>Some things to know: NUS utilises the Cumulative Average Point (CAP) to determine the performance of a student.</p>

<p>Formula for determining CAP: <img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-126" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/screen-shot-2014-12-24-at-1-29-19-pm.png?w=300" alt="Screen Shot 2014-12-24 at 1.29.19 pm" width="300" height="32" /></p>

<p>Basically the numerator is the sum of the product of module credits and grade points and the denominator is the sum of the module credits for ALL the modules taken so far. It’s crucial to note the cumulative function of the CAP. Hence, it is not determined on a per semester basis, but rather for the 3-4 years of modules taken.</p>

<p>To maximise the S/U options given during the gradeless semester, there are some things to note first.</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the class of degree you're aiming for.
<ul>
<li>Degrees awarded are classified as shown (taken from NUS website):
<table border="5" style="width:100%">
<tr>
<td><strong>Honours Degree Classification</strong></td>
<td><strong>Criteria</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Highest Distinction)</td>
<td>CAP 4.50 and above</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Distinction)</td>
<td>4.0 to 4.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours (Merit)</td>
<td>3.5 to 3.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Honours</td>
<td>3.0 to 3.49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Pass</td>
<td>2.0 to 2.99</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fail</td>
<td>Below 2.0</td>
</tr>
</table>

<li>Note the Grade Point table:
<table border="1" style="width:100%">
<tr>
<td><strong>Letter Grades:</strong></td>
<td>A+</td><td>A</td><td>A-</td><td>B+</td><td>B</td><td>B-</td><td>C+</td><td>C</td><td>D+</td><td>D</td><td>F</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Grade Points:</strong></td>
<td>5.0</td><td>5.0</td><td>4.5</td><td>4.0</td><td>3.5</td><td>3.0</td><td>2.5</td><td>2.0</td><td>1.5</td><td>1.0</td><td>0.0</td>
</tr>
</table>
</li>
<li>If the target is Honours (Highest Distinction), then a CAP of 4.50 and above is required by the end of your 3-4 years. To achieve this, the average grade for the modules you took for 4 years must be at least an A-.</li>
<li>Therefore, during the S/U option, S/U anything below A- is a good option, since it will increase the number of modules with grades A- and above</li>

</li>
<li>If the first semester is a good indication of the performance for the rest of the semesters, then S/Uing any modules with a gradepoint below your CAP is a good idea. For example, your CAP is 4.44, and your grades are A,A-, A,B+,B+, then S/U modules below 4.44 which are the 2 B+.</li>
<li>The gradepoints allocated to the grades, for example 4.0 for a B+ means it will pull your overall CAP towards the 4.0. Hence, unless the overall CAP is below 4.0, then B+ would not really help with pushing the CAP upwards.</li>

</ul></li></ol>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>NUS CAP Calculator</title>
	  <link>/blog//NUS-CAP-Calculator</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-28T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//NUS-CAP-Calculator</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h3 id="update">UPDATE</h3>

<p>New Web CAP Calculator has been released here: <a href="http://harishv.me/capcalc/">NUS CAP Calculator</a></p>

<h3 id="archive">Archive</h3>

<p>Here is a CAP calculator I made in excel. Just a simple excel sheet that helps to keep track of your grades. Feedback welcome and updates will be made to add other functions.</p>

<p>Click here to download <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obZ3UzZ0lBcFllMUE">CAP Calculator v1.0</a>.</p>

<p>Update! : V1.1: <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obNW16cmZPNzlmaHM">CAP Calculator v1.1</a></p>

<p>(Note: this was done to be just used as a guide. Check with faculty for degree requirements and the NUS FASS calculator if necessary).</p>

<p>Inspired from <a title="Agagooga's CAP Calculator" href="http://gssq.entori.net/files/capcalc.htm" target="_blank">Agagooga’s CAP calculator</a>.</p>

<p>A better CAP calculator with better user interface is coming, for the web, desktop and mobile platforms. Stay tuned! :)</p>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
