<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me/</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life, code and everything in between.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Top 5 Protein Sources Vegetarians Need to Know</title>
	  <link>/blog//Top-Five-Protein-Sources-Vegetarians-Need-to-Know</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-05-09T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Top-Five-Protein-Sources-Vegetarians-Need-to-Know</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><small>
<em>Quick Bite</em> <br />
Why a elephant as a cover photo? - The elphant, one of the strongest animals in the animal kingdom, sustains itself on a “vegetarian” diet since it is <a href="https://www.wikipedia.com/en/Herbivore">herbivorous</a>.</small></p>

<p>You don’t need to eat meat if you’re bodybuilding. Of course, it is easier to find protein from sources such as fish and chicken. But if you’re a vegetarian, you can definitely get your protein source from these amazing vegetarian sources!</p>

<h3 id="greek-yogurt">1. Greek Yogurt</h3>

<p>My favourite source of protein is <a href="http://www.thekitchn.com/whats-the-difference-between-regular-and-greek-yogurt-ingredient-intelligence-204137">Greek yogurt</a>. As compared to regular yogurt, Greek yogurt has a thicker texture as it undergoes extensive straining to remove the liquid and lactose present. This results in double the amount of protein as what regular yogurt contains! Also, Greek yogurt is readily available in most supermarkets and they are fairly priced. 150g of Greek yogurt typically costs anything between USD 1.20 to USD 3.00 depending on the brand and where you purchase it. My favourite is the Emmi Swiss Premium Greek Style Yogurt (Natural) shown here.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/PySI3G4.png" alt="Greek Yogurt" /></p>

<p>This small tub contains 150g of Greek yogurt, is non-fat and has 10% protein. That is equivlant to 84 calories and 15g of protein. Comparatively, a whey protein shake is about 20g of protein with 122 calories.</p>

<p>If you’re like mean, you probably won’t like the yogurt raw. A simple trick is to add a tablespoon of honey (Manuka honey is really good!) to it before consuming.</p>

<p>See here for more benefits of Greek yogurt: <a href="http://www.livestrong.com/article/86488-benefits-greek-yogurt/">Livestrong.com</a></p>

<h3 id="chickpeas">2. Chickpeas</h3>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/g8VeUHf.png" alt="Chickpeas" /></p>

<p>Chickpeas, also known as grams or garbanzo bean are also rich in protein. Just one cup of chickpeas can provide <a href="http://www.livestrong.com/article/528633-the-protein-in-chickpeas/">12 grams of protein</a>. Chickpeas can be made easily by soaking it in water overnight or  boiling it. Easy protein for all vegetarians!</p>

<p>Unlike animal protein, chickpeas (and most plant-based proteins) do not have all the amino acids to give the complete protein you need. But, you can easily combine chickpeas with other food to “complete” your protein requirements.</p>

<h3 id="lentils">3. Lentils</h3>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/Kfq9yPN.png" alt="Lentils" /></p>

<p>Coming from an Indian family, lentils are commonplace in most of my dishes. They are perfect for anyone to get various nutrients all at one go. One cup of lentils can provide up to 18 grams of protein and contains many other nutrients like iron, potassium and zinc. In fact, lentils are considered to be one of the world’s healthiest foods! Combining lentils with your daily meals is a great way to meet your protein requirements. They are surely a <a href="http://www.thesweetbeet.com/lentil-nutrients/">great replacement for fish and meat</a>.</p>

<h3 id="milk">4. Milk</h3>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/WCNGfyn.png" alt="Milk" /></p>

<p>Milk primarily contains 3-4 types of caseins. Having a glass of milk daily, in the morning can help kickstart your metabolism for the day. You seem to be wondering how much of protein there is in a glass of milk. One glass (around 200 ml) can easily provide 10 - 11g of protein with about 120 calories. My daily breakfast consists of a glass of milk with Milo and 2 slices of wholemeal bread. That gives me 17.6g of protein with 368 calories.</p>

<h3 id="nuts">5. Nuts</h3>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/DrDjJCx.png" alt="Nuts" /></p>

<p>This post would not be complete without the mention of nature’s wonders: nuts. Walnuts, almonds, grams, cashews, sunflower seeds, peanuts <em>(beware: high fat content too!)</em>, pine nuts, pecan nuts. Take a handful of a mix of whichever of these nuts you can find to get a wholesome nutrient source with a good amount of protein! However, some nuts, like peanuts, can also have a high fat content. So do check out the nutritional labels on the fat content for the nuts to decide how much would fit your daily expectations or goals. My favourite combination includes roasted grams, peanuts, almonds and sunflower seeds! I usually like to supplement my workout with a handful of nuts.</p>

<p>You might be wondering why I did not mention soy, which also provides for an excellent source of protein. Protein alone may not give someone the clear and overall picture. In my readings, I have often found that soy, despite being high in proteins, contain phytoestrogens which might disrupt hormone levels. While this is a debatable topic, I prefer to steer away from soy products. There are so many other options which appeal to me more than soy anyway!</p>

<p>Hope this was helpful! Share the goodness.</p>

<p>Cheers.</p>

<p><small><em>General Disclaimer</em>: Dietary requirements would vary depending on your current health status. Some products mentioned may contain additional ingredients which may not be suitable for all. Do consult a nutritionist to be well-advised.</small></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Great Quotes Close to My Heart</title>
	  <link>/blog//Great-Quotes-Close-to-My-Heart</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-24T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Great-Quotes-Close-to-My-Heart</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
  <p>When you truly and deeply want something, all of the universe conspires in helping you achieve it. - The Alchemist by Paulo Coelho</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s always good to work with people who make you feel insecure about yourself. That way, you will constantly keep pushing your limits.” - Sundar Pichai, CEO, Google</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>To be yourself in a world that is constantly trying to make you something else is the greatest accomplishment. - Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The only thing standing between you and your goal is the story you keep telling yourself as to why you can’t achieve it.” - Jordan Belfort</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Most people quit because they look how far they have to go, not how far they have come.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Silence the angry man with love. Silence the liar with truth”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“A person who is happy is not because everything is right in his life, he is happy because his attitude towards everything in his life is right.” - Sundar Pichai</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Everything around you that you call life was made up by people, and you can change it.” - Steve Jobs</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most people settle for what they think they are capable of. But if you don’t overestimate yourself, you will never uncover what you are really capable of. - Harish V</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you don’t go after what you want, you’ll never have it. If you don’t ask, the answer is always no. If you don’t step forward, you’re always in the same place.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Sometimes it is the people who no one imagines anything of who do the things that no one can imagine.”- Alan Turing</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Happiness can be found even in the darkest of times, if one only remembers to turn on the light” - Albus Dumbledore</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sometimes there are battles that we have to keep fighting alone. - Harry Potter</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It is our choices, Harry, that show what we truly are, far more than our abilities.” - Dumbledore to Harry</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If you want to know what a man’s like, take a good look at how he treats his inferiors, not his equals.” - Harry Potter</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Working hard is important, but there’s something that matters even more. Believing in yourself.” - Harry Potter</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Time is the only real currency”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In the jargon of the computer programmer, a hacker is someone who strives to solve problems in elegant and ingenious ways.” - NUS Hackers</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Time you enjoy wasting, was not wasted” - John Lennon</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>SUCCESS = LUCK + (REAL VALUE * MARKETED VALUE)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Harry, there is never a perfect answer in this messy, emotional world. Perfection is beyond the reach of humankind, beyond the reach of magic. In every shining moment of happiness is that drop of poison: the knowledge that pain will come again. Be honest to those you love, show your pain. To suffer is as human as to breathe.” - Excerpt From: Rowling, J.K. “Harry Potter and the Cursed Child.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Impossible is just a big word thrown around by small men who find it easier to live in the world they’ve been given than to explore the power they have to change it.” - Muhammad Ali</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>‘I do not fear for I am treading on the path laid by my Lord’ - Harish V</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If you can’t fly, then run. If you can’t run, then walk. If you can’t walk, then crawl, but whatever you do you have to keep moving forward.” - Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“What is important is seldom urgent and what is urgent is seldom important.” - Dwight Eisenhower</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You have to figure out what your own aptitudes are. If you play games where other people have the aptitudes and you don’t, you’re going to lose. And that’s as close to certain as any prediction that you can make. You have to figure out where you’ve got an edge. And you’ve got to play within your own circle of competence.” - Warren Buffett</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>On the street I saw a naked child, hungry and shivering in the cold. I became angry and said to God, “Why do you permit this? Why don’t you do something?”
For a while God said nothing. That night he replied, quite suddenly, “I certainly did something. I made you.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Victory is sweetest when you’ve known defeat.” - Malcom Forbes</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I will be keeping this list updated. Stay tuned!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>I Have a Dream</title>
	  <link>/blog//i-have-a-dream</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-21T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//i-have-a-dream</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I am sharing one of the most inspiring speeches in human history - ‘I have a dream’, by Martin Luther King Jr. Even today when I read or watch this, I am truly inspired by the passion Martin Luther King Jr. shows when he speaks every single word with conviction. What an amazing leader!</p>

<hr />

<p>I am happy to join with you today in what will go down in history as the greatest demonstration for freedom in the history of our nation.</p>

<p>Five score years ago, a great American, in whose symbolic shadow we stand today, signed the Emancipation Proclamation. This momentous decree came as a great beacon light of hope to millions of Negro slaves who had been seared in the flames of withering injustice. It came as a joyous daybreak to end the long night of their captivity.</p>

<p>But one hundred years later, the Negro still is not free. One hundred years later, the life of the Negro is still sadly crippled by the manacles of segregation and the chains of discrimination. One hundred years later, the Negro lives on a lonely island of poverty in the midst of a vast ocean of material prosperity. One hundred years later, the Negro is still languished in the corners of American society and finds himself an exile in his own land. And so we’ve come here today to dramatize a shameful condition.</p>

<p>In a sense we’ve come to our nation’s capital to cash a check. When the architects of our republic wrote the magnificent words of the Constitution and the Declaration of Independence, they were signing a promissory note to which every American was to fall heir. This note was a promise that all men, yes, black men as well as white men, would be guaranteed the “unalienable Rights” of “Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness.” It is obvious today that America has defaulted on this promissory note, insofar as her citizens of color are concerned. Instead of honoring this sacred obligation, America has given the Negro people a bad check, a check which has come back marked “insufficient funds.”</p>

<p>But we refuse to believe that the bank of justice is bankrupt. We refuse to believe that there are insufficient funds in the great vaults of opportunity of this nation. And so, we’ve come to cash this check, a check that will give us upon demand the riches of freedom and the security of justice.</p>

<p>We have also come to this hallowed spot to remind America of the fierce urgency of Now. This is no time to engage in the luxury of cooling off or to take the tranquilizing drug of gradualism. Now is the time to make real the promises of democracy. Now is the time to rise from the dark and desolate valley of segregation to the sunlit path of racial justice. Now is the time to lift our nation from the quicksands of racial injustice to the solid rock of brotherhood. Now is the time to make justice a reality for all of God’s children.</p>

<p>It would be fatal for the nation to overlook the urgency of the moment. This sweltering summer of the Negro’s legitimate discontent will not pass until there is an invigorating autumn of freedom and equality. Nineteen sixty-three is not an end, but a beginning. And those who hope that the Negro needed to blow off steam and will now be content will have a rude awakening if the nation returns to business as usual. And there will be neither rest nor tranquility in America until the Negro is granted his citizenship rights. The whirlwinds of revolt will continue to shake the foundations of our nation until the bright day of justice emerges.</p>

<p>But there is something that I must say to my people, who stand on the warm threshold which leads into the palace of justice: In the process of gaining our rightful place, we must not be guilty of wrongful deeds. Let us not seek to satisfy our thirst for freedom by drinking from the cup of bitterness and hatred. We must forever conduct our struggle on the high plane of dignity and discipline. We must not allow our creative protest to degenerate into physical violence. Again and again, we must rise to the majestic heights of meeting physical force with soul force.</p>

<p>The marvelous new militancy which has engulfed the Negro community must not lead us to a distrust of all white people, for many of our white brothers, as evidenced by their presence here today, have come to realize that their destiny is tied up with our destiny. And they have come to realize that their freedom is inextricably bound to our freedom.</p>

<p>We cannot walk alone.</p>

<p>And as we walk, we must make the pledge that we shall always march ahead.</p>

<p>We cannot turn back.</p>

<p>There are those who are asking the devotees of civil rights, “When will you be satisfied?” We can never be satisfied as long as the Negro is the victim of the unspeakable horrors of police brutality. We can never be satisfied as long as our bodies, heavy with the fatigue of travel, cannot gain lodging in the motels of the highways and the hotels of the cities. We cannot be satisfied as long as the negro’s basic mobility is from a smaller ghetto to a larger one. We can never be satisfied as long as our children are stripped of their self-hood and robbed of their dignity by signs stating: “For Whites Only.” We cannot be satisfied as long as a Negro in Mississippi cannot vote and a Negro in New York believes he has nothing for which to vote. No, no, we are not satisfied, and we will not be satisfied until “justice rolls down like waters, and righteousness like a mighty stream.”</p>

<p>I am not unmindful that some of you have come here out of great trials and tribulations. Some of you have come fresh from narrow jail cells. And some of you have come from areas where your quest – quest for freedom left you battered by the storms of persecution and staggered by the winds of police brutality. You have been the veterans of creative suffering. Continue to work with the faith that unearned suffering is redemptive. Go back to Mississippi, go back to Alabama, go back to South Carolina, go back to Georgia, go back to Louisiana, go back to the slums and ghettos of our northern cities, knowing that somehow this situation can and will be changed.</p>

<p>Let us not wallow in the valley of despair, I say to you today, my friends.</p>

<p>And so even though we face the difficulties of today and tomorrow, I still have a dream. It is a dream deeply rooted in the American dream.</p>

<p>I have a dream that one day this nation will rise up and live out the true meaning of its creed: “We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal.”</p>

<p>I have a dream that one day on the red hills of Georgia, the sons of former slaves and the sons of former slave owners will be able to sit down together at the table of brotherhood.</p>

<p>I have a dream that one day even the state of Mississippi, a state sweltering with the heat of injustice, sweltering with the heat of oppression, will be transformed into an oasis of freedom and justice.</p>

<p>I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character.</p>

<p>I have a <strong>dream</strong> today!</p>

<p>I have a dream that one day, down in Alabama, with its vicious racists, with its governor having his lips dripping with the words of “interposition” and “nullification” – one day right there in Alabama little black boys and black girls will be able to join hands with little white boys and white girls as sisters and brothers.</p>

<p>I have a <strong>dream</strong> today!</p>

<p>I have a dream that one day every valley shall be exalted, and every hill and mountain shall be made low, the rough places will be made plain, and the crooked places will be made straight; “and the glory of the Lord shall be revealed and all flesh shall see it together.”</p>

<p>This is our hope, and this is the faith that I go back to the South with.</p>

<p>With this faith, we will be able to hew out of the mountain of despair a stone of hope. With this faith, we will be able to transform the jangling discords of our nation into a beautiful symphony of brotherhood. With this faith, we will be able to work together, to pray together, to struggle together, to go to jail together, to stand up for freedom together, knowing that we will be free one day.</p>

<p>And this will be the day – this will be the day when all of God’s children will be able to sing with new meaning:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My country ‘tis of thee, sweet land of liberty, of thee I sing.</p>

  <p>Land where my fathers died, land of the Pilgrim’s pride,</p>

  <p>From every mountainside, let freedom ring!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And if America is to be a great nation, this must become true.</p>

<p>And so let freedom ring from the prodigious hilltops of New Hampshire.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Let freedom ring from the mighty mountains of New York.</p>

  <p>Let freedom ring from the heightening Alleghenies of Pennsylvania.</p>

  <p>Let freedom ring from the snow-capped Rockies of Colorado.</p>

  <p>Let freedom ring from the curvaceous slopes of California.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But not only that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Let freedom ring from Stone Mountain of Georgia.</p>

  <p>Let freedom ring from Lookout Mountain of Tennessee.</p>

  <p>Let freedom ring from every hill and molehill of Mississippi.</p>

  <p>From every mountainside, let freedom ring.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And when this happens, and when we allow freedom ring, when we let it ring from every village and every hamlet, from every state and every city, we will be able to speed up that day when all of God’s children, black men and white men, Jews and Gentiles, Protestants and Catholics, will be able to join hands and sing in the words of the old Negro spiritual:</p>

<p><em>Free at last! Free at last!</em></p>

<p><em>Thank God Almighty, we are free at last!</em></p>

<p>By <strong>Martin Luther King Jr.</strong></p>

<p>An American pastor, activist, humanitarian. People know him for leading the African-American Civil Rights movement using nonviolent civil disobedience.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</title>
	  <link>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>We all talk about productivity and efficiency today. So here is my way of getting my things done.</p>

<p>I primarily use two platforms to get my stuff done: <a href="https://workflowy.com">Workflowy</a> and <a href="https://calendar.google.com/">Google Calendar</a>. Workflowy is an amazing platform that is buuilt on a simple idea: making lists. At first look, it may look so simple and plain and even no greater than a Notepad like web-app. But, it is amazing intuitive to use and I am usually able to structure and plan according the the priority of tasks.</p>

<p>I usually think in a structured, top-down way and I would probably attribute that to my engineering-based education. So a typical structure I impose in Workflowy is this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Urgent</li>
  <li>Important</li>
  <li>Upcoming</li>
  <li>KIV</li>
</ol>

<p>These are listed in order of priority and shows me which task I need to get done next.</p>

<p>Under each of these categories, I make tasks and their relevant sub-tasks. For example, I have an Engineering exam this coming week, I create a task called “Engineering Exam”. Under this task, I include a label called “Details” which indicates the time, date and location of this task and “Revision” which then contains the relevant sections and chapters to revise as sub-sub-tasks.</p>

<p>One of the greatest things about Workflowy is that you can create many many layers of sub-sub-sub-sub-…. tasks. However, an important feature that is missing is reminders.</p>

<p>For this, I use Google Calendar. All deadlines and events immediately go into my Google Account with a default alert set for 1 and 2 days before the actual date. This together with my list of tasks of Workflowy keeps me organised.</p>

<p>I check this list at the start of the day and update it as and when tasks come in. At the end of the day, I check if all intended tasks for the day have been completed. If yes, I complete them. If no, I move and reschedule them on the level of priority. Before sleeping, I spend 5 minutes working out the relevant tasks and agenda for tomorrow by simply adding a hashtag (#tomrrow) beside the tasks in Workflowy.</p>

<p>This system has worked great so far and I believe it has been a key reason for my productivity too.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Thoughts with Mass</title>
	  <link>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-01-17T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif"><img class="size-medium wp-image-140" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/uni6.gif?w=250" alt="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif" width="250" height="300" />Image Credits: https://helenmagnani.wordpress.com/</a></p>

<p>As I was reading The Lost Symbol, by Dan Brown, there was an interesting idea shared which immediately awed me. It deals with the hypothetical question: “Do thoughts have mass?”. Though, on a weighing scale, thoughts may possess mass ranging in the nano to femto scale, if they do have a mass, there will be many implications.</p>

<p>One of which was presented in the book was on gravity. If our thoughts had some mass, they will be bound by the laws of physics. Which meant, they will exert a gravitational force on other matter (though the force is of a very very small scale). Despite the insignificant amount force by a single thought, when a group of people come together to think on the same idea, this collective force becomes significant. It might then start to attract others towards this idea or notion. And that, will be powerful, when a thought can attract others and influence them to think in a certain way too.</p>

<p>Although it is a hypothetical question, the implications simply awed me. Upon further thinking: With thoughts having some mass, they will also be bounded by the Law of Conservation of Energy. Thoughts cannot be destroyed entirely. Instead, the thoughts are simply converted from one thought/idea to another. Or, they may become converted into another form of energy (likely chemical energy) in the brain.</p>

<p>Indeed, it is fascinating to imagine the implications if such a hypothesis was proven to be real. Whether it is true if thoughts have mass or not, only time will tell.</p>

<p>A few of my favourite quotes on the power of thoughts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Change your thoughts and you change your world. <br />
<strong>Norman Vincent Peale</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are what our thoughts have made us; so take care about what you think. Words are secondary. Thoughts live; they travel far. <br />
<strong>Swami Vivekananda</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Concentrate all your thoughts upon the work at hand. The sun’s rays do not burn until brought to a focus. <br />
<strong>Alexander Graham Bell</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>A positive attitude causes a chain reaction of positive thoughts, events and outcomes. It is a catalyst and it sparks extraordinary results. <br />
<strong>Wade Boggs</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Most Powerful Thing in the World</title>
	  <link>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-20T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Have you ever wondered what is the most powerful thing in the world?</p>

<p>Well, its not money, not wealth, maybe love, but really I think its an idea.</p>

<p>Yup, an idea. Every single day, we see ideas that change and craft the world. From the phone in your hand to the computer you’re reading this blog on, every thing around us took root from the idea that came up in someone’s brain.</p>

<p>But when you think about it, an idea isn’t something tangible. Not any physical product you can touch and understand. Nevertheless, you can feel it. And if an idea is powerful enough, it can change the world for the better, or for the worse.</p>

<p>I particularly felt galvanised watching Inception. Inception is basically about implanting someone else’s idea into a target’s subconscious, deep enough, that it changes their way of thinking. Well, an idea seems like a simple thing. But the potential and the potency of an idea goes beyond itself. It creates a chain reaction so complex that without that single idea in a person’s brain, the world might have been different.</p>

<p>The idea right now, in your head is something so powerful. Make sure it is put to good use. To make a change for the better.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you really want something, all the Universe conspires in helping you achieve it. -The Alchemist, Paulo Coelho</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a quote I always remember. What you are, who you are is defined by your ideas, your actions. If you have a good idea, and truly believe in it, then give it your best shot. Make your ideas come alive.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Revolution 2020 - Love, Corruption, Ambition by Chetan Bhagat</title>
	  <link>/blog//Revolution-2020</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-14T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Revolution-2020</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/44/Revolution_2020.jpg" alt="Revolution 2020" /></p>

<p>Rating: ★ ★ ★</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Revolution_2020">Revolution 2020</a> was a particularly interesting read from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chetan_Bhagat">Chetan Bhagat</a>. In this novel, the timeline spans across 3 main periods, his childhood then on to his teenage years and finally his adulthood in Varanasi.</p>

<p>The book starts by introducing Chetan Bhagat as a Guest-of-Honor (GOH) to a commemorative event, where he gets introduced to Gopal the Director of the University GangaTech. One thing leads to another, and a reluctant Chetan Bhagat sits in for a drink at Gopal’s place. Gopal shows off his big house and his extravagant spending character. However, Gopal after drinking too much collapses. And in the hospital he begins his narration of his life.Gopal’s childhood days are one that an ordinary school student can relate to. Though from a poor family, he has friends Raghav and Aarti who can be considered decently rich. This period mainly focuses on how the friendship blossoms between the trio, while concentrating more on Gopal and Aarti.</p>

<p>Gopal’s teenage years exhibit his profound love for Aarti, mainly understood by his thoughts. However, when Gopal proposes, Aarti refuses to reciprocate his love for her, citing that she is not ready for a relationship yet. Meanwhile, Gopal flunks both his AIEEE and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Institute_of_Technology">IIT</a> JEE exams. This causes some upset since his good friend Raghav manages to become one of the top scorers in the district. After his father insists that he goes to Kota to join a tuition to mould him well for a 2nd time try in both the exams.</p>

<p>While in Kota, Gopal learns of a shocking relationship between Aarti and Raghav. Moreover, he also fails to get the required ranking to get into the University a 2nd time. Gopal’s father dies soon after, unable to take in his son’s failure again. After this part, Gopal is left to be an orphan. His relatives start pressurising him to sell his ancestral land under dispute for a meagre sum of money. Feeling lost, and unable to think of any solution to move forward in life, Gopal barely drags himself. While searching for a cheap private University, Gopal gets introduced to the MLA, Shukla.</p>

<p>From then, it seems like a turning point in Gopal’s life. He comes under the protective showers of the MLA. Motivated by the money that a private University can reek in, the MLA promises to settle the land dispute and have Gopal to run the private University (named GangaTech) in which he will be a ‘trustee’. Raghav, on the other hand, takes a contrasting route by forsaking his Engineering seat to pursue journalism, which he claims to be his passion.</p>

<p>Soon, Raghav begins publishing the MLA’s wrongdoings which leads to strained ties between Raghav and Gopal after disputes. Meanwhile, Gopal and Aarti get to become closer. After some time and persuasion, it is shown that Aarti is in love with Gopal. MLA Shukla is soon forced to resign after his wrongdoings go viral in Raghav’s newspaper named ‘Revolution 2020’.</p>

<p>But will Gopal eventually win over Aarti? Or will it remain as Raghav and Aarti?</p>

<p>That is the crust of the story. However, be ready for a rollercoaster ride as further twists and turns are revealed in the end.</p>

<p>While it was a good read, it was certainly quite difficult to accept the climax. Once again, Chetan Bhagat has produced a finely written story, with extra spices, making it ready for the big screens.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Aashiqui 2</title>
	  <link>/blog//Aashiqui-2</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-12T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Aashiqui-2</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>My Rating: ★ ★ ★ ★</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aashiqui_2">Aashiqui 2</a>. The remake of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aashiqui">old hit movie</a>. And it was simply worth every minute. A visual pleasure and an auditory treat, this movie was an outstanding production and brought your emotions to live as well. Despite the characters being newcomers into the industry, their performance was simply outstanding. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shraddha_Kapoor">Shraddha Kapoor’s</a> innocence and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aditya_Roy_Kapur">Aditya Roy Kapoor’s</a> charm simply carries away the hearts of many. The chemistry between the characters was simply intense, pure and at times heart-wrenching. The actors have proved their caliber in this movie by giving their best. Expecting their next release soon.</p>

<h2 id="a-plot-summary">A Plot Summary:</h2>

<p>Rahul Jaykar, a successful musician and singer is introduced as the film begins with his performance. Despite his success, his weakness, alcohol addiction is shown to be limiting his career. The show ends with Rahul in a fight with Aryan, who throws a bottle at him near the end of his first song, Sunn Raha Hain Na. He leaves the show abruptly following this and drives to the local bar. He witnesses a young girl, Aarohi singing his own song in the bar. He is thoroughly impressed with the girl’s potential and believes that she will be the next superstar in singing. He follows her and promises her to transform her into a superstar and asks her never to sing in local bars again.</p>

<p>Trusting Rahul, Aarohi leaves her job at the bar and travels to Mumbai. She calls Rahul, just as he told her to when she reaches Mumbai. However, unfortunately, Rahul gets attacked by a group of thugs and is severely injured in the ensuing brawl. He is subsequently admitted to the hospital where he is under treatment for a month. In the time, Aarohi tries many times to reach Rahul. However, Rahul’s friend and manager, Vivek tells her that Rahul is on an overseas trip for a performance and neglects further calls from her. Aarohi gets despaired by these events and starts to believe that she was cheated. After 2 months of fruitless attempts to reach Rahul, Aarohi gets heart-broken and gives up. She goes back to working at the bar due her family’s financial problems.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Rahul keeps asking Vivek about Aarohi, but Vivek lies to Rahul that he received no calls or whatsoever. Once Rahul recovers, he leaves determined to find Aarohi. He finds her in a bar and realizes that Vivek has been lying to him all these while. Rahul sacks Vivek and convinces Aarohi that he will help her and recounts his situation for the past 2 months. Aarohi decides to trust Rahul for one last time, and agrees to go with him. Soon Rahul gives vocal training for Aarohi and helps her to attain a music contract with his production company. Aarohi becomes a very successful singer and a sensation. While everything seems fine, rumors spread about Rahul and Aarohi.</p>

<p>Rahul becomes distraught about this and gives in to his alcohol addiction. Aarohi who loves him, comforts him and moves in with Rahul despite her mother’s disapproval of her actions. Aarohi slowly helps Rahul to gain control over himself from his addiction. Rahul does fine and involves himself in other activities to keep him away from his addiction. However, an encounter with a journalist who accuses him of using Aarohi for his gains, causes him to turn back to his alcohol addiction for relief. He becomes violent and aggressive.</p>

<p>A saddened Aarohi soon decides that she will take a hiatus from her career to help Rahul. Rahul realises that he is the obstacle in Aarohi’s life and will eventually cause her downfall in her career. One morning, Rahul promises Aarohi that he is going to change himself and focus on diet and a gym regime and drives off following a good-bye with Aarohi. However, it seems that it was his last good-bye as he commits suicide by jumping off a bridge. A devastated Aarohi decides to give up on everything and begins to move out with her parents. Rahul’s friend Vivek meets her, and encourages her to pursue her music career for which Rahul sacrificed his life and assures that it was what Rahul truly wanted.</p>

<p>Aarohi decides to continue her music career and is successful. The film ends with Aarohi signing an autograph for her fans as “Aarohi Rahul Jaykar”.</p>

<h2 id="comments">Comments:</h2>

<p>A must-watch movie that brings back the emotions and liveliness of a true love story. Despite the sorrow, the movie is able to reach deep within the audience. The songs, both “Tum Hi Ho” and “Sunn Raha Hai” are both amazing and addictive.</p>

<p><a href="/blog/Tum-Hi-Ho-Guitar-Chords">Click here for the Guitar Strum Pattern and Chords for Tum Hi Ho</a></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Immortals of Meluha by Amish Tripathi</title>
	  <link>/blog//The-Immortals-of-Meluha</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-11T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//The-Immortals-of-Meluha</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/0e/The_Immortals_Of_Meluha.jpg" alt="The Immortals of Meluha" /></p>

<p>My Rating: ★ ★ ★ ★</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Immortals_of_Meluha">The Immortals of Meluha</a> is the first book of the Shiva Trilogy written by <a href="http://www.authoramish.com/">Amish Tripathi</a>, which portrays a fictional story of the revolution led by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shiva">Lord Shiva</a>. The author has done a great job in accurately incorporating the characters such as Nandi into the story which provides a sense of realism of reading an actual novel on Lord Shiva. In fact, many traditional customs and terms used, such the caste system, adds to the authenticity of the book. It was an enjoyable read, particularly due to the touches of ancient Indian traditions which we still can relate to.</p>

<p>The book has frequent references to the old 4-type caste system.</p>

<p>In this book, it follows the character of Shiva, a Tibetan tribal leader through his destiny. Shiva’s best friend is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virbhadra">Veerbhadra</a>. Shiva is the so-called warrior that everyone in a city called Meluha awaits to save them from the troubles they face. For one, the much sacred <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarasvati_River">Saraswati river’s</a> water flow is dwindling. Shiva moves to Meluha with his tribe, where he thinks his tribe will be able to enjoy a better life and a stop from the frequent battles between his tribe and another. The services rendered to their tribe at Meluha simply overwhelms all of them.</p>

<p>On the first night of stay, everyone from Shiva’s tribe start to experience weird symptoms like profuse sweating and high fever. Soon, the Chief of Medicine, Ayurvati, begins the healing process for all the tribe members. However, unexpectedly, Shiva is completely lacks these symptoms that others are showing and in turn, shows that his throat has turned blue. Upon this shocking news, Ayurvati brings it to the attention of the King of Meluha, Daksha, who declares Shiva as the Neelkanth, the exact warrior’s arrival the city has awaited for decades and even centuries.</p>

<p>Throughout these, Shiva meets <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nandi_%28bull%29">Nandi</a>, a Captain, who he becomes very close to. Shiva also meets Princess Sati (aka Parvati), with whom he is attracted to. Shiva realises that Meluhans are the Suryavanshis and their enemies are the Chandravanshis. He is told of the brutal attacks carried out by the Chandravanshis on the innocent people of Meluha, especially the Brahmins, whom refuse to fight back as they practise non-violence. Shiva is also constantly exposed to the scenes of threats, many of which, he strives to save Princess Sati. The violence angers Shiva, who decides to accept the destiny of being the Neelkanth and seeks to take revenge on the Chandravanshis to put a stop to the battles and attacks.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, Shiva is also introduced to the sacred elixir of life, Somras, through which all Meluhans attain lifelong immunity to any diseases, keeping them alive for many years. Their aging stops when they take the exilir, hence, most Meluhans are very youthful. Shiva comes across Brahaspati, the Chief Scientist working at Mount Mandar. They form a close brother-like relationship. Shiva also meet Parvateshwar, the Chief of the Meluhan Army.</p>

<p>Sati slowly begins to reciprocate Shiva’s love and soon they get married. This is after initial hesitations of Sati and the others due to Sati being a vikarma (describes people who are considered to be sinful due to the sins committed in their earlier life). The Vikarma law, considered to be unfair to all becomes abolished by Shiva who is considered above the King in Meluha. Soonafter, Brahaspati is killed in a brutal attack by the Nagas at Mount Mandar, committed by the Nagas who were believed to be affliated with the Chandravanshis. This angers Shiva badly, leading to the declaration of war against Chandravanshis.</p>

<p>The war occurs and the Suryavanshis eventually win the Chandravanshis through their smart techniques, collaboratively formed by Shiva and Parvateshwar, though outnumber more than a ratio of 1:10 to the Chandravanshis. The Chandravanshi King is captured and brought before Shiva. The king then leaves, profoundly shocked by the sight of Shiva and his blue throat. It is then revealed by the King’s daughter that, they too believed earnestly in the legend of the Neelkanth, who will be the saviours of Chandravanshis. Upon hearing this, Shiva is crestfallen and unable to fathom his own actions.</p>

<p>In a distressed state, he then visits the temple dedicated to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rama">Lord Ram</a> in Ayodhya, where the Pandit (the priest) counsels him and advises him of the actions he chose and his destiny. The book ends with Shiva rushing to save Princess Sati, waiting outside the temple, from the Naga, who is hidden among the tress behind Sati.</p>

<p><em>Related Articles</em></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://adityaviyer.com/2013/01/06/the-immortal-secret-of-amish-tripathi-inktalks/">The (Immortal) Secret of Amish Tripathi #INKtalks (adityaviyer.com)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://iamalienman.wordpress.com/2013/01/06/chanakyas-chant-book-review/">Chanakya’s Chant / Book Review (iamalienman.wordpress.com)</a></li>
</ul>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>One Night at the Call Center by Chetan Bhagat</title>
	  <link>/blog//One-Night-at-the-Call-Center</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-10T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//One-Night-at-the-Call-Center</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/7/79/One_Night_%40_Call_Center.jpg" alt="One Night @ the Call Center" /></p>

<p>My Rating: ★ ★ ★ ★</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One_Night_@_the_Call_Center">One Night @ the Call Center</a> is a story penned by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chetan_Bhagat">Chetan Bhagat</a>. The story revolves around the characters working in a call center at night. The characters are Shyam, Priyanka, Esha, Vroom, Radhika, Military Uncle and Bakshi (the evil boss). The story is narrated from Shyam’s point of view.</p>

<p>Each of the character are facing problems in their life.</p>

<p>Shyam was earlier attached to Priyanka, but now have broken up. Despite, having feelings for her, he is in a daze when he comes to know, she is getting engaged to a NRI named Ganesh Gupta, a high-flier who works in Microsoft. Apart from this, Shyam seems to have lost all his esteem and self-confidence through the nature of treatment he receives from others and constantly degrading remarks from his evil boss, Bakshi. Bakshi is portrayed as a selfish boss who takes full credit for other work, only concentrating on his own self-improvement but not the call center company (Connexions).</p>

<p>Priyanka is initially happy about her new engagement. However, she is unhappy about her parents’ haste in marrying her the coming month itself. She feels is not yet ready for marriage and mulls over this. Meanwhile, Shyam and Vroom, who are good friends, unveil that Ganesh hid his baldness from Priyanka by showing her some online photos of Ganesh. This further saddens Priyanka.</p>

<p>Esha is an attractive girl, whose dream is to become a model. However, to achieve this, she went to the limits of sleeping with the designer to get the contract. The designer however, cheats her by saying she is an inch shorter than expected, and compromises by offering money. Esha feels deep guilt and hatred over herself for her actions. She is unable to accept herself anymore.</p>

<p>Vroom is a fun-loving guy who has many aspirations. However, he works in the call center, subduing to everyone else, just to earn enough money to keep up with his rich friends and their hobbies. In the midst of the night, Vroom gets to know that Bakshi has taken credit for all the 6 months of hard work, that he and Shyam has put in to develop a customer service website. This angers him greatly, but he is unable to avenge his anger due to fears of losing his job. Meanwhile, he overhears Esha pouring her guilt to her other friends. Vroom who loves Esha, feels sickened after this.</p>

<p>Radhika is already married. She has great trust and love for her husband. She endures all the trouble her mother-in-law gives her and succumbs to the traditional roles that her mother-in-law expects her to do, even preparing the daily milk with crushed almonds for her in the morning when she is rushing for work. Though Radhika, does not complain about this, her mother-in-law is still unhappy and complains all the time to her husband. Later on, Radhika accidentally comes to know that her husband has cheated on her. This greatly shocks and hurts her.</p>

<p>Military Uncle broke up with his son’s family some years ago. When he tries to maintain contact with his grandson by sending some photos, he receives an email from his son, asking him to cut all contact with the family. Military Uncle gets deeply saddened by this.</p>

<p>While all of them have their troubles, something unusual makes them realise the importance and appreciation of the life they are living. Facing some systems error, all the agents are unable to take calls. Vroom decides that they go out to a bar to relieve their stress. While on the return journey, Vroom decides to take a shortcut to reach office quickly and the van ends up crashing into a construction site. The van is left dangling precariously on the edge of a some steel rods above a abyss. When all hope seems lost, they receive a phone call in the no-reception area. The call was from GOD.</p>

<p>The rest of the story follows what happens after God speaks to them and saves them by giving them some tips to escape out of the situation. God makes them stay true to their heart and promise that they will do what they have to do to achieve that.</p>

<p>It was an interesting read, especially the parts after the call from God were particularly inspiring in one way or another. The characters were easy to relate to and thus made much of the reading very comfortable.</p>

<p>Might be a litte draggy at parts. Nonetheless, a great read!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
