<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>HarishV's Blog</title>
 <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/"/>
 <updated>2016-06-09T23:38:49+08:00</updated>
 <id>harishv7.github.io/blog</id>
 <author>
   <name>Harish V</name>
   <email>harish207@live.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>NUS Second Year, Second Semester in Review</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/education/2016/06/09/NUS%20Second%20Year%20Second%20Semester%20in%20Rev/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-09T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/education/2016/06/09/NUS Second Year Second Semester in Rev</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following post is also available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CS2010: Data Structures &amp;amp; Algorithms II &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module is one of my favourite modules in this semester. Usually CS2010 is taught by Prof Steven Halim, but it was Dr Brown this semester who is teaching this module for the first time in NUS. Dr Brown was really great and funny as well. He tried to bring across the concepts taught very well and in my opinion one of the coolest professors I have seen. Once I required an extension to one of the important lab assignments and he was so chill about it and totally understands students’ positions. Also, this is a must-take module for any computer science person as it introduces the key algorithms that has made the tech world around us possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course weight he is divided into assignments, labs, lecture quizzes, mid term and final exams. Yes, the weightage is pretty diversified across the various components. It’s important to be consistent in this module as the further weightage for each lab or assignment would also vary depending on the difficulty. The rough breakdown of the course weightage is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In-lecture exercises (8%) – Mini-assignments done during lecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lab exercises (12%) – Similar to assignments but shorter and easier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Four Assignments (40%) – Weighted differently depending on difficulty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exams (40%) – Midterm + Final&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course structure is basically an introduction to trees, heaps, hash tables in the first half followed by a heavy focus on graphs in the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall a great and crucial module to take for  any computer science or engineering student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: A&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; EE2024: Programming for Computer Interfaces &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module was one of the heaviest, if not, the heaviest module I have ever taken. The course mainly focuses on Assembly language in the first half and low-level C programming for computer interfaces in the second half. Both halves consist of a related project done in pairs. While the first project is largely manageable, the second project is huge and is extremely time intensive. In fact, I don’t remember doing anything other than this module in the last 3-4 weeks of the semester. My partner and myself came to NUS at 10am and left at 10pm daily for these weeks. It was an extremely challenging period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip for projects is to 1) Start early &amp;amp; 2) Use the resources around you to learn fully (both online &amp;amp; offline).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this module is definitely useful as it gives great in depth understanding of how devices around us were programmed and interfaced, the content was so heavy that I couldn’t get enough time to appreciate everything I learnt. Nevertheless, the module helped me understand the importance of several technologies such as UART, master-slave protocols etc and their applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final exams were slightly hard as expected. Nevertheless, Prof Rajesh went through all the past year papers one by one during the last few weeks as solutions to the papers are not released. That really helped to clarify a lot of the learning gaps and also on the expectations for the final paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: A-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CG2271: Real-Time Operating Systems &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall a great module. Took this under Prof Tulika. This is actually the CEG counterpart module of the CS version of Operating Systems. Hence most of the focus was on the lower level areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The module is structured into labs, midterms and finals. Also, there is a small component for tutorial attendance. Most of the earlier labs are manageable. However, as we moved along into the later parts, I found the labs to be harder not because of the concepts but mostly the debugging of programs and identifying where we went wrong. Hence, it became a little time-intensive too. Labs are done in pairs using a Spark fun (Arduino) kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending lectures (or watching webcasts) is important to help in the understanding. I actually enjoyed this module quite a bit. And after the module was completed, I began appreciating the use of many of the concepts I have learnt. Concepts such as semaphores, mutexes are so crucial and they are being used everywhere around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final exams were pretty hard as compared to the midterms, but manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: A&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; ST2334: Statistics &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics is a useful and slightly easier than the other modules I took this semester. However, easier means others will also find it easy. I guess the competition for the module was a little high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notes were pretty self explanatory out of the times and there are plenty of problems to practice. Both midterms and final exams were pretty okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Module structure is mostly based on IVLE quizzes, tutorial attendance, tutorial participation, midterms and finals. Important tip for this module is to be consistent. And the lecturer did make sure we are consistent by giving online quizzes each week and tutorials on alternate weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: B+&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CG2023: Signals &amp;amp; Systems &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signals and Systems was an intimidating module for me at first. Looking at so much math and complex terms didn’t help in motivating myself to study. However as time went by, I realised it wasn’t that hard after all. The only requirement to do well in this module is the investment of time. Understanding of the concepts comes over time and dedication  to read the notes again and again. Do this till you understand. Whenever I felt unsure, I used the recommended textbook to write down a few problems and solve then to check my understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For midterms and finals, it is very crucial to practice a lot of the past year papers to clarify on the difficulty level and on what is expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The professors were also kind and helpful whenever we approach them with questions. For this module, we just need the discipline to sit down and invest some time in the understanding of the concepts taught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆☆☆☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: A&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, it was the most hectic semester I’ve had. Till next time, cheers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Harish V&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ask NOC - Honestbee & Shopback Sharing Session</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/entrepeneurship/2016/01/28/askNOC%20Session%20Review/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/entrepeneurship/2016/01/28/askNOC Session Review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I attended 2 talks during askNOC. There were two invited guests: Jonathan Low from Honestbee and Henry Chan from Shopback. Both companies are startups, having only been in the market for around a year or so. Today’s sharing was largely focused on their business and how they overcame the various challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestbee is a concierge and online delivery service for grocery shopping. So essentially, customers can place orders online for groceries or items found at common supermarkets such as NTUC. The ‘bees’ from the company are actuallly people who will shop the necessary items and deliver them to you in an hour. I personally found this a great idea for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, there is a huge incentive for consumers to use this product because there are no additional costs. The items are bought at the same prevailing price at the supermarket. Secondly, consumers can order from the convenience of their home. Thirdly, as mentioned by Jonathan, this is an asset light model. There are no storage or warehouse involved. Every purchase is made directly at the supermarket which means storage is well taken care of. Essentially, the only services that they are providing will be the shopping and delivery of items. They are able to grow well with the use of technology. For example, internally they use an Android app that allows ‘bees’ to receive orders. Nevertheless, Jonathan mentioned that currently it is still exists as a manual process. This can definitely be automated to reduced much of the overhead costs. An order can immediately be routed to a free ‘bee’ together with the list of items etc. Doing so will help save time and manpower costs as well as allow them to garner good analytics into the demographics and patterns of their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about how Honestbee works, Jonathan also provided some good insights into the business model. They utilise a revenue share model. Taking an example of an order of $100, they will be able to obtain a 20% commission. Out of this $20, their overall profit is only $10 as shown below.
$20-$5(shopper cost)-$5(delivery  cost) = $10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several teams in Honestbee which work together. These include: business, customer service, product (engineering, design, data), operations teams. He emphasised the crucial need for each of these teams to work hand in hand and communicate effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan also shared the various challenges he faced. Factoring in the customer acquisition costs, each customer only turns profitable from the fifth order onwards. Also, he mentioned the poor visibility they have on stock availability. This is especially true due to their reliance on the supermarket to have the various products they are looking for.
Also, delivery costs are only minimised with economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk was by Henry Chan from Shopback. Shopback is based on the idea of customers getting cashbacks on their online purchases. Henry provided some great insights on e-commerce as a whole. He pointed out that e-commerce in Southeast Asia has a very low penetration rate which essentially means a huge growth opportunity for the next 5-6 years. One of the key markets to tap on will be Indonesia where online shopping and mobile penetration rates are growing rapidly. Henry also emphasised that entrepreneurs must be willing to learn and have the hunger to achieve and that expanding your business is all about having the right people around you. This pointed out the importance of networking, about having good contacts in the business world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked how his business adapts to smaller markets where technology is generally less advanced, he said that such a situation is indeed a good opportunity where you can have greater expansion and tap deeper into the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the interesting questions was if both the founders give employees stock options. I felt that this is a great way to align employees’ interests together with the company’s goals. While stock options may not guarantee any value, this orientation towards a common goal is crucial in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, both of them provided an important tip for budding entrepreneurs:Don’t be shy in validating your idea. One of them even mentioned, that they requested people in Starbucks to test drive their prototype and gain feedback. I am sure validation is a crucial part every new product has to achieve and this must be done early in the prototyping stage itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learnt a lot from this session and definitely looking forward to the next session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Second Year, First Semester in Review</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/education/2015/12/22/Second%20Year,%20First%20Semester%20in%20Review/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/education/2015/12/22/Second Year, First Semester in Review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following blog post is also available on my Wordpress site &lt;a href=&quot;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/12/24/second-year-first-semester-in-review/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past semester is definitely the busiest semester I have been through. There was literally no time for anything else other than studies and projects. Part of the reason (as you will see), is that I took 8 modules this time. However, one of them, CP3108B - Orbital has already been completed. Two of the other modules CP2201 and CFG1001 lasted only for the first half of the semester, thankfully. This allowed for a slightly relaxed timetable in the second half of the semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I am really glad that I managed to do my best through the semester. And for those who are anticipating such a semester, I felt you might find a review of the modules handy. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CP 2201: Journey of the Innovator &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a module about entrepreneurship and is worth 2 MCs. The grading is also in the form of Completed Satisfactorily (CS) or Completed Unsatisfactorily (CU) which means that the grade obtained will not affect the current CAP you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I found this module to be very engaging and entertaining. It provided me with what I wanted to learn about entrepreneurship. Each week, there were invited guest speakers who share their experience on entrepreneurship. A typical outline of the module looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Week 1: Introduction to module and some basic information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Week 2: Guest speakers from PropertyGuru and Reebonz with Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Week 3: Guest speakers from upcoming startups: Klinify, Lomotif and InvestingNote with Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Week 4: Guest speakers from Red Dot Ventures and Golden Gate Venture with Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each week, there will be a short assignment which requires some reflection on various aspects of entrepreneurship as well as the guest speakers and the companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all a great module to learn from entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: Oh did I mention that there is a buffet dinner and networking session for 30 mins weekly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CS2101: Effective Communication for Computing Professionals &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a twinned module with CS2103T (see below). Basically, this module teaches you to write and present your ideas in an effective manner. Communication skills, writing skills and presentation skills are the 3 most crucial skills required to do well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this module good as I was able to pick up on the above-mentioned skills. However, there are a number of continual assessments for this module since there are no final exams. This means you will be kept busy almost every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, some of the CAs are simple activities like doing a reflection on communication or your oral presentations. Some of the assessments I remember doing are:
- Reflection on Communication Skills &amp;amp; Commenting on others’ reflections
- Oral Presentation 1 (OP1)
- Writing a Project Proposal
- Writing of a Progress Report on the software project
- Oral Presentation 2 (OP2)
- Reflection 2 on OP2 &amp;amp; Commenting on others’ reflections
- Writing of a Project Manual (Developer and User Guide)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do well in this module, it is crucial to have the enthusiasm and appreciation for what you are doing. Of course, that will also help you to be more participative in your class (participation is also counted for grading). Also, I cannot emphasise enough on having a good team who can support you in these tasks. This is definitely not a one-man-army type of module for you to do alone. Effective teamwork is important in bringing out the best in most parts of the module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CS2013T - Software Engineering &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been looking forward to this module for some time. Personally, I love software engineering and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module was personally very enriching and I got to learn a lot in terms of the various software engineering principles. That being said, this is one of the most hectic modules. As a team of 4, we were tasked to build a desktop-based task manager from scratch which had a primary input through the keyboard. By task manager, I mean a productivity software akin to popular ones like Google Keep, Todoist, Wunderlist, Any.do etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grading of the module was divided into 3 main areas: Project (50%), Final Exam (40%) and Participation (10%). As such, the project hold the majority of the weightage and that makes this module different from conventional ones. We apply what we learn. Every week, the lecture introduces new principles and concepts relevant to software engineering. Much of these knowledge can be immediately applied to the project we are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CS2103T is also twinned with CS2101 (as described above). Hence, many of the things we do such as developer’s guide, user guide etc. are relevant to the project. The use of version control (Git or GitHub) is extremely crucial for the project and came in really handy. We are prone to introduce bugs/errors when 3-4 people “operate” on the code simultaneously. Having revision control allowed such to keep track of these changes and simply revert our changes if we found them to be buggy later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The participation segment is the easiest to score and you should definitely score the full 10% here. Points can be earned through the proper completion of pre-tutorial and in-tutorial activities, answering questions in lectures, successful completion of weekly lectures quizzes on IVLE etc. There is maximum cap of 200 points which means that any points exceeding the 200th mark will not contribute to the participation points for grading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final exam tests the skills we have learnt throughout the semester. If you have learnt and applied these concepts well for the software project, it will be much easier to score here. The CS2103T module handbook (a 200-page document/textbook companion) is a must-read for scoring well for the exams. It helps to reinforce the concepts learnt and clears the small gaps in understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I learnt a lot through this module. My team and I managed to create quite a cool desktop application called “FINI”. The name inspired from French, in which Fini refers to finished or accomplished. We felt that this accurately represents the goal of our app and it was easy to remember too! 
These are some of the screenshots of the application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/rwUcDNl.png&quot; alt=&quot;FINI&#39;s Welcome Screen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/c6qWEbI.png&quot; alt=&quot;FINI&#39;s Overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/OIFjxyi.png&quot; alt=&quot;FINI&#39;s Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, my team and I became really passionate about what we were doing and we even made a cool video for our Oral Presentation 2 in CS2101 and to also serve as an introductory product demo video during our CS2103T demonstration. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/utI1N5hhFSs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video Credits: Jonas, Team FINI&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FINI is available for download and use here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cs2103aug2015-t16-1j/fini/releases/tag/v0.5&quot;&gt;GitHub Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, an interesting yet hectic module. If you love creating cool stuff, you will love this module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆	☆ ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; EE2020 - Digital Fundamentals &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a 5MCs module which is split into 2 parts. The first part is relatively easier to understand and introduces the basic building blocks of computers such as logic gates. The second part is focused mostly on slightly more intricate topics such as Finite State Machines (FSMs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also lab and project components in this module. The labs are mostly manageable and primarily introduces the use of FPGAs and the hardware description language known as Verilog. The project is done individually and it involved creating an oscilloscope out of the FPGA. This was really cool because oscilloscopes generally cost many hundreds of dollars. Using a simple FPGA to create an oscilloscope was indeed interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of it involved writing Verilog for the FPGA to interpret and display the incoming signal from the signal generators in the lab. The project was graded individually with a range of criteria. Two main influencing factors are the number of features (such as scaling, translating, displaying words/labels, pointers) and the uniqueness of the features &lt;em&gt;as compared to your peers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no final exams. Instead there is a midterm quiz and final quiz (each 20%) and the rest of the assessment is based on labs and projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, a manageable module. Be creative with the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆ ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; EE2021 - Devices and Circuits &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module has a lot of theory and formulas on semiconductors. Personally, I found it quite intensive and usually took me the most time out of all my modules to revise and gain a complete understanding of what was being taught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assessment for this module is Homework (10%), Midterm test (20%), Quiz (5%), Final Exam (65%), though I do not remember taking a quiz for the 5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topics covered were very structured starting from the building blocks and slowly moving on to bigger components: Semiconductors -&amp;gt; PN junctions -&amp;gt; Bipolar Junction Transistors (BJT) -&amp;gt; Metal Oxide Semiconductors Field Effect Transistors (MOSFET) -&amp;gt; CMOS Logic -&amp;gt; Single Stage Amplifiers -&amp;gt; Multistage Amplifiers -&amp;gt; Opamps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was really overwhelming and was like a bit of PC1432 again. The first part (before midterms) is usually much easier to understand than the second part. So make sure you ace the midterms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, a difficult module indeed due to the time commitment for understanding and revision. If you can appreciate what you learn, it will greatly help in the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆ ☆ ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; LAF1201 - French 1 &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took this module out of curiosity and the eagerness to learn a new language. I had shortlisted Chinese, Hindi and French and finally decided on French.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Firstly, we need to understand that learning a language takes considerable time and effort to both learn, grasp and then practice speaking it. And doing all this while juggling other modules during a period of 1 semester is not a joke. French is apparently written with English alphabets with some accented ones. Also, it is similar to English or rather English is similar to French. As compared to other languages like Chinese and Hindi, this meant that I do not need to spend extra time learning to write the new alphabets which would help to save a considerable amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must say French was really awesome. The people I met were mostly from FASS, but there were a few of them like me from Engineering or some from Pharmacy and Business. I really liked like environment. It was very interactive and my lecturer Dr Daniel Chan made sure everyone participated in each lesson. The interaction and fun during lessons made me like French even more. To ensure this interaction, all lessons are tutorials (no lectures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workload wise, since there are no final exams, you will be having tests / quizzes / homework more frequently than you would have expected to. There are quizzes on the French culture, vocabulary, grammar, audio recording of a self-introduction, writing of an email for an imaginative scenario etc. The final test is an oral conversation between 2 you and two others from your group in front of the lecturer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say it is relatively easy to score for the tests if you have consistently practised French (both writing and speaking). That being said, also means that your peers will score well. Personal advice is to revise the notes posted on IVLE and use Google Translate to its fullest capability. I also utilised the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.duolingo.com&quot;&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt; app (web &amp;amp; mobile) to learn much of the content. Oh yes, if you have an iPhone, you can set the language for Siri as French and converse with it in French. It’s quite cool and you can also check on your pronunciation by seeing if Siri understands what you just said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very enjoyable module taught by a great lecturer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CP3108B - Independent Work (Orbital Programme) &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I participated in the Orbital programme during the summer break before my semester 1. I have written a post on the Orbital experience which is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://harishv7.github.io/blog/education/nus/college/techstuff/2015/08/19/Orbital%202015/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/08/20/orbital-2015&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): ☆ ☆	☆&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; CFG1001 - Headstart Module &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is a 0 MCs module to prepare you for your career, there is a reason I have written about it here. Before attending the sessions, I was a little complacent and thought of this module as something that is snatching my precious time away. However, upon attending the module, I thought differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module helps to expose how it is like in the “real” world outside of NUS. Preparing for a career also includes preparing for the various interviews, networking with others etc. And it helped me understand and appreciate the importance of many skills and pointers which will definitely come in handy during my interview applications etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module is graded with a Completed Satisfactorily (CS) or CU (Completed Unsatisfactorily) grade. You’ll just need to attend all the 2-3 face-to-face sessions to get a CS grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty (out of 5): (Nil)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, I just realised I have 4 consecutive exams in the coming semester!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess I need to mentally prepare for it. After all, the only easy semester was the last semester!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Skye Boat Song</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/music/2015/12/16/Skye%20Boat%20Song/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/music/2015/12/16/Skye Boat Song</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to play the popular Skye Boat Song. It is a traditional piece and recently there is a Skye Boat Song from the popular British TV series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Outlander_(TV_series)#/Accolades&quot;&gt;Outlander&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is played in the key of D major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/237518275&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
V.Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Minuet in G</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/music/2015/12/15/Minuet%20in%20G/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/music/2015/12/15/Minuet in G</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to play the popular Minuet in G by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&quot;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/a&gt;. As suggested by the title, this piece is played in the key of G major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/237517046&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
V.Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Solving Einstein's Riddle</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2015/12/07/Solving%20Einstein's%20Riddle/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-07T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2015/12/07/Solving Einstein's Riddle</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/IgXHPOF.jpg &quot; alt=&quot;Einstein&quot; style=&quot;width: 200px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting riddle written by Einstein in the last century. He claimed that &lt;strong&gt;98%&lt;/strong&gt; of the people in the world will not be able to solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-riddle&quot;&gt;The Riddle:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are 5 different houses, each of a different colour.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a owner of a different nationality in each house.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each of the owner drinks a specific type of drink.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each of the house owner smokes a specific type of cigarettes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each of the house owner has a specific type of pet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;None of the owners drink the same drink / smoke the same cigarette brand / have the same type of pets / have same nationality / live in the same house.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-clues&quot;&gt;The Clues:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Brit lives in the red house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Swede keeps dogs as pets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Dane drinks tea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the green house is on the left of the white house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the green house’s owner drinks coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the person who smokes Pall Mall rears birds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the owner of the yellow house smokes Dunhill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the man living in the center house drinks milk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Norwegian lives in the first house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the man who smokes blends lives next to the one who keeps cats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the man who keeps horses lives next to the man who smokes Dunhill&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the owner who smokes BlueMaster drinks beer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the German smokes Prince&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Norwegian lives next to the blue house&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the man who smokes blend has a neighbor who drinks water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenge&quot;&gt;The Challenge:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are challenged to find out who has the fish using the above information and clues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to understand is that though the information seems sparse and disjointed, there is indeed a logical path for you to work out the riddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine the houses layed out in a horizontal manner with the first house on your left to the last house on your right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BwSVKyZQM1obZ1VNWm8waHp2NUU/preview&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we list out all the possibilities for each category. The categories are nationality, colours, drinks, pets, house number and cigarette brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nationality
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Norwegian&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Brit&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dane&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Swede&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;German&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colours
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blue&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Red&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;White&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Yellow&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Green&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drinks
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coffee&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tea&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Beer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Water&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Milk&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pets
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dogs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cats&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Birds&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Horses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fishes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;House Number
1,2,3,4,5 respectively for each house from left to right&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cigarette Brand
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dunhill&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blends&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;BlueMaster&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pall Mall&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prince&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we write whatever we know in a table form. As we gather more and more information from the clues, we fill the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that the Norwegian lives in the first house. Next, we know that the Norwegian lives next to the blue house. This means that the 2nd house in the row is blue. The man in the center house drinks milk. And we are told that the green house is on the left of the white house and that the green house’s owner drinks coffee. The clue that the green house is on the left of the white house tells that the 4th and 5th houses have to be green and white respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Brit lives in a red house. The first house has already been occupied by the Norwegian and we know the colours of the 2nd, 4th and 5th houses. This leads us to the fact that the center house is red and the Brit lives there. Also, this leaves the first house to be yellow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green house’s owner drinks coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting together all these information, we have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/UkHinqI.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px&quot;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Nationality&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Drink&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Smokes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Pets&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Color&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;House No.&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;German&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dane&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Tea&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Red&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Swede&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dogs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Norwegian&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the owner of the yellow house smokes Dunhill, we know the Norwegian smokes Dunhill. Therefore, the 11th clue tells us that the man in the blue house keeps horses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 12th clue tells us that the man who smokes BlueMaster and drinks beer must be in the 2nd or 5th house (since the first house is occupied by the Norwegian and men in 3rd and 4th house drink milk and coffee respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the first house. The options of drinks left for the Norwegian are water, beer and tea. Since the Dane drinks tea, that option is out. Since the Norwegian smokes Dunhill, beer is out. We are left with water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last clue makes it evident that the man in the 2nd house smokes blend. That means the man in the last (5th) house smokes BlueMaster and drinks beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leaves us with the option of tea for the 2nd house and hence, it means the Dane lives in the 2nd house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current table looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Zi95yp8.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px&quot;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Nationality&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Drink&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Smokes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Pets&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Color&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;House No.&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;German&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dane&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Tea&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Blend&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Horses&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Blue&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Milk&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Red&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Swede&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dogs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Norwegian&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Water&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dunhill&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Yellow&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 13th clue now shows that the only option for the German who smokes Prince is in the 4th house. This leaves the last house for the Swede who has dogs as pets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 6th clue shows that the Brit smokes PallMall and rears birds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10th clue shows that either the first or third house has cats. Since the third house has birds, this means that the Norwegian keeps cats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finished table will look like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px&quot;&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col style=&quot;width: 120px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Nationality&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Drink&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Smokes&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Pets&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Color&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;House No.&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;German&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Coffee&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Prince&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Fish&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Green&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dane&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Tea&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Blends&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Horses&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Blue&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brit&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Milk&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;PallMall&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Birds&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Red&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Swede&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Beer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;BlueMaster&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dogs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;White&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Norwegian&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Water&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Dunhill&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Cats&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Yellow&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This only leaves us with the German who must have the fish. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gamecraft 2015!</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/2015/12/06/Gamecraft%202015/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-06T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/2015/12/06/Gamecraft 2015</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/KnFi8cM.png &quot; alt=&quot;TwistedMaze Logo&quot; style=&quot;width: 200px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently participated in Gamecraft 2015. This is my 2nd time participating this is “game-hackathon”. This time my team consisted of Al, Ted, Chris &amp;amp; myself. The theme for this year was “Twist”. As usual, the interpretation of this theme in relation to the game was left open to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things that came to my mind was a maze that twists. As I was imagining this idea, I suddenly had this inspiration from this book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Maze_Runner&quot;&gt;The Mazerunner&lt;/a&gt;. It is a book where a group of “hostages” have to escape from a ever-changing labyrinth. There has also been a movie released with the same name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggested this idea and we tried brainstorming a few ideas before settling and finalising on this one. After this decision, we focused our efforts towards the game development. Me and Chris took on the roles of the game design where we made the shifting maps for the maze and the necessary sprites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ted was the sound engineer and gather suitable sounds for use in the game. Al, being the lead programmer of the group, devoted his attention to the game physics and the actual coding of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We utilised Unity for the game and eventually (after 24 hrs) managed to come up with a finished game, TwistedMaze. TwistedMaze is available for download (both Mac and Windows versions) at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/harishv7/TwistedMaze/releases&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future work on porting the game to Android and iOS is currently being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you enjoy playing the game as much as we enjoyed creating it. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2015/12/03/My%20Getting%20Things%20Done%20(GTD)%20Framework/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2015/12/03/My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We all talk about productivity and efficiency today. So here is my way of getting my things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I primarily use two platforms to get my stuff done: &lt;a href=&quot;https://workflowy.com&quot;&gt;Workflowy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.google.com/&quot;&gt;Google Calendar&lt;/a&gt;. Workflowy is an amazing platform that is buuilt on a simple idea: making lists. At first look, it may look so simple and plain and even no greater than a Notepad like web-app. But, it is amazing intuitive to use and I am usually able to structure and plan according the the priority of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually think in a structured, top-down way and I would probably attribute that to my engineering-based education. So a typical structure I impose in Workflowy is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Urgent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Important&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upcoming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KIV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are listed in order of priority and shows me which task I need to get done next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under each of these categories, I make tasks and their relevant sub-tasks. For example, I have an Engineering exam this coming week, I create a task called “Engineering Exam”. Under this task, I include a label called “Details” which indicates the time, date and location of this task and “Revision” which then contains the relevant sections and chapters to revise as sub-sub-tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest things about Workflowy is that you can create many many layers of sub-sub-sub-sub-…. tasks. However, an important feature that is missing is reminders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this, I use Google Calendar. All deadlines and events immediately go into my Google Account with a default alert set for 1 and 2 days before the actual date. This together with my list of tasks of Workflowy keeps me organised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I check this list at the start of the day and update it as and when tasks come in. At the end of the day, I check if all intended tasks for the day have been completed. If yes, I complete them. If no, I move and reschedule them on the level of priority. Before sleeping, I spend 5 minutes working out the relevant tasks and agenda for tomorrow by simply adding a hashtag (#tomrrow) beside the tasks in Workflowy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This system has worked great so far and I believe it has been a key reason for my productivity too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Lessons from Entrepreneurs</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2015/12/02/Lessons%20from%20Entrepreneurs/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-02T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2015/12/02/Lessons from Entrepreneurs</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past semester, I undertook a module in NUS known as “Journey of the Innovator” (CP2201). More than just a module, it was conducted in an interesting and engaging seminar style. Each week, many lessons on entrepreneurship were shared and in one of the weeks, 3 startup founders were invited to share their views and insights into entrepreneurship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;klinify&quot;&gt;Klinify&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first talk was by Krish, the CEO and Founder of Klinify. Personally, I found Klinify’s mission to “provide the freedom of paper with the power of digital technology” intriguing. It aims to propagate a change within the medical industry and empower doctors to harness the strengths of technology to further improve the medical services being delivered. During his talk, Krish mentioned some importants points on entrepreneurship that he has learnt thus far. I have combined those pointers, together with my learning points from the talk:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Focus on a specific sector: Klinify’s target audience are very specific. It is specifically targeted at the providers of medical service, doctors. While their ultimate goal is to extend the platform of Klinify globally, their current milestone is to establish themselves in Singapore and in Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Klinify offers hybrid storage: This might be a little technical. Conventionally, a patients records (in paper) are only available physcially in the hospital. However, by digitalizing medical recors, now patient records are both available locally and on the cloud. By sharing it on the cloud, the medical records are now more accessible than ever. This could even offer a centralised patient records system to help doctors view and understand the patient’s medical history well before treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reasons for Klinify’s potential success: Klinify does not aim to change doctors’ natural way of doing things. Their workflow remains the same. Doctors are still able to write like they do on paper. They have customised templates. They can attach photos and even annotate. All these features help doctors to transition from their current pen-and-paper workflow to the digital platform with ease.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some concerns on Klinify: Security. Technology rules today’s world. However, the growth of technology has brought about potential incentives for people to expose data. Medical records are meant to be private. In an event of a security breach, millions of medical records can be leaked. However, during the talk, Krish did mention their focus to ensure the safety and privacy of patient records. And only a strong defence system can deter such security compromises.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lomotif&quot;&gt;Lomotif&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk was by Paul from Lomotif. Lomotif is essentially a mobile application that allows users to create a video from their stash of videos and even add songs to it. After using it, a clear winning point of Lomotif was the usability factor. It was very simple to use and even a novice mobile user will be able to use it easily. 
Some pointers from Paul:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Market saturation: There will be a point in time when your target market becomes saturated. And Paul mentions that we should definitely anticipate this. To overcome this, we need to try and leverage on another market. I think this can be done in a couple of ways. Various markets are segmented by factors such as age, culture and perception. Hence, an expansion into another market requires a change in the app / technology that addresses one or more of these factors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some interesting features of Lomotif: It’s collaborative, expressive and fun. This fun factor is one of the main reasons which helps Lomotif stand out from its competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;3 Crucial Factors:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Good Team&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Customer Acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Making your customers happy.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;investing-note&quot;&gt;Investing Note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third talk was by Shanison from InvestingNote. InvestingNote is a social network site targeted specifically at investors in Singapore and in the regional space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon using the InvestingNote platform, I like the user-friendly interface and the summarised view of stocks/shares and other information. Personally, I believe that such a social-platform can be of great use to investors. Facilitating communication among investors is something new I have seen and if brought about to the target market correctly, I believe this can be a good success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel the above pointers are critical in ensuring the success of the start-up. While it may be true that most start-ups fail eventually, I think keeping the above pointers in mind will definitely aid them to beat the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
V.Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hey Siri, Give me a hint!</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/techstuff/2015/08/29/Hey%20Siri,%20Give%20me%20a%20hint!/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/techstuff/2015/08/29/Hey Siri, Give me a hint!</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Visited Apple’s events page today and was greeted by this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/AppleEvent/webpage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Apple&#39;s Events Page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And true enough, Siri responded with it’s usual level of cuteness:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;images&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; src=&quot;http://imgur.com/F6PcUgU.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; src=&quot;http://imgur.com/C44CeZq.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/cPPGI8Y.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Nm4rD5C.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/3YCMIUk.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/rfc5tdG.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/yjFhbHU.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;siri&quot; align=&quot;middle&quot; src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/10ELJWN.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;applelogo&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/AppleEvent/apple.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.images{
    text-align:center;
}
.applelogo{
	width:160px;
	height: 240x;
	padding-top: 50px;
}
.siri{
	width: 160px;
		height: 284px;
		display:inline-block;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Entrepreneurship - Yay or Nay?</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/techstuff/entrepreneurship/2015/08/24/Entrepreneurship%20Yay%20or%20Nay%3F/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/techstuff/entrepreneurship/2015/08/24/Entrepreneurship Yay or Nay?</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today was an exciting day. Having taken the CP2201 module, Journey of the Innovator, today was the first 2 talks by self-made entrepreneurs and businessmen, Steve Melhuish from PropertyGuru and Samuel Lim from Reebonz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire session focused on how they built their business from scratch and the hurdles they went through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;several-important-points-were-highlighted-throughout-the-session-such-as&quot;&gt;Several important points were highlighted throughout the session, such as:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For an entrepreneur, his focus should be on innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having a solid business model is crucial. The growth in online traffic (for web/mobile based businesses) helps to convert losses to profits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think big, and expand big.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionalise your business and scale appropriately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in a good team with good leaders (CFO, CTO, CEO etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With the best content and most traffic you can make it to be #1 in the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;firstly-to-summarise-my-learning-from-propertyguru&quot;&gt;Firstly, to summarise my learning from PropertyGuru:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of PropertyGuru was to allow transparency of information in the property market by placing the entire market online to solve a real-world issue: Everyone needs a home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several growth tactics were used to leverage on the growing population in emerging countries, rising smartphone and broadband penetration rates and increasing trend of online marketplaces and online transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is crucial to ensure that there is ongoing PR to keep the publicity going with the media, so that people are aware of you and your business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick the ideal investor who is not only interested in the money made by the business, but rather willing to support the business with growth and opportunities. A strategic investor should bring intelligent information to provide insight on the current situation of the market.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Size and Valuation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pitch Documents: Keep some documents ready at hand, both a 2-page document and a 20-page version, to pitch to others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Competitive tension: If many investors are interested, we can potentially increase the valuation of the business. Get as many parties interested as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good M&amp;amp;A lawyer: It is important to have a good Mergers &amp;amp; Acquisition (M&amp;amp;A) lawyer to prevent ‘unwanted’ takeovers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business today will face challenges on different levels, such as:
- Scaling (Revenue &amp;amp; Costs involved)
- Increasing levels of competition: No longer limited to the local scale, but rather we are competing on a regional or even global scale.
- Staying nimble&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some great quotes I found during the presentation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Good companies meet needs, Great companies create markets”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“As an entrepreneur always be paranoid of competitors and them taking away your market!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-second-part-of-the-presentation-was-focused-on-reebonz&quot;&gt;The second part of the presentation was focused on Reebonz:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important points for aspiring entrepreneurs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Little cash/capital is no longer a worry today. Innovation is largely valued and ideas can be executed with web/mobile apps which have minimal costs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on market adoption. Even if your ideas are novel and you have your product ready, the market must be ready to adopt it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For a business to survive in the long run, we need to adapt to the market landscape.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on cutting loss. Ideas may need to change, don’t fall in love with your idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth is dependent on cash/capital. Find and learn to manage venture capital.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay true to your core beliefs and idea. Build the business model around this idea.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adopt niche areas, where you can differentiate from other businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value and invest in customer relationships. This will help in gaining faster adoption and long-term customers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maximise existing resources to create value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some great quotes from the second-half of the session:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You don’t need the best team, but the right team”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“The hardest about evolving a business model is keeping true to your core brand idea”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Instead of finding places where there is already competition, find niche areas where you can dominate the business”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“See opportunities in problems”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Get a MVP, or beta model and launch it. Only then you will receive feedback on what the market wants.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Only the paranoid survives” – Quoted from Andrew Grove, Co-Founder of Intel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a very fruitful session that stirred up the entrepreneur within me. The world needs change, and only innovation can drive that change. And entrepreneurs can lead that innovation. In that regard, I am motivated to become an entrepreneur myself to help make positive difference in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Orbital 2015</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/education/nus/college/techstuff/2015/08/19/Orbital%202015/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/education/nus/college/techstuff/2015/08/19/Orbital 2015</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/5EjaKFa.png&quot; alt=&quot;Friendezvous&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 3 months of hard work, the Orbital programme came to a close on 19th Aug 2015. It was a great experience and I picked up many skills of both front and back end development. I did the project with Al who was very supportive during the 3 months though he was on vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project’s inspiration came from our shared experiences in daily college life. Many of the times we tend to organise meetings manually. A typical process goes like this (A,B,C are persons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A–&amp;gt;B: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? &lt;br /&gt;
B–&amp;gt;A: Yup, that’ll be good I guess. &lt;br /&gt;
A–&amp;gt;C: Hey, are you free tomorrow for a project meeting at 2-4pm? &lt;br /&gt;
C–&amp;gt;A: Oh no, I don’t think I’ll be free. How about some other day? &lt;br /&gt;
A (thinks to him/herself): Darn, got to ask B and C for another timing again! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown above, the typical manual process is tedious where we often WhatsApp or message one another for free slots and try to match it all up for a common time to meet. In the point of view of the meeting administrator, it is a rather painstaking process when he/she has to repeatedly ask the team members for a suitable time to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this issue, I suggested to Al that we should maybe develop a platform which can make the organising of meetings simpler and redefine the ways of doing so. And from there, Friendezvous was born. Friendezvous is an amalgamation of the words Friend and Rendezvous (a meeting at an agreed time and place). So essentially Friendezvous refers to meetings with friends, colleagues etc. And we decided on a relevant tagline as well: “Organising meetings, redefined.”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I should describe a little of the technical aspects of Friendezvous as well. Friendezvous was built using the good old LAMP stack. We used PHP and MySQL along with front-end technologies/frameworks such as HTML, CSS, jQuery, jQuery UI, Bootstrap (modified), Angular JS. The development itself was not the difficult part. The hardest part of this journey was to think as an user of this platform. How would an user using Friendezvous feel about the workflow of this app? Is it too complicated? Can we improve on the workflow to minimise the number of steps/clicks an user is required to make to achieve an objective? These are the various questions which were running on our minds all the time. After all, software/app development is not just about blinding writing code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is much more to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are dealing with real life users here. Then, we decided to conduct a survey to analyse the perception of our target audience towards the platform. We did it with a closed circle of friends and received very positive feedback. It was definitely a morale booster to our idea and efforts. More than anything, we were passionate about what we did. Even if we made a positive difference in a single person’s life, it would mean a lot to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orbital Splashdown, where all the teams (from beginner, intermediate &amp;amp; advanced levels) came together to showcase their work, was held on 19th August 2015. It was exhilarating to see so many applications built by students like myself. I was inspired by many apps, with their technical aspects as well as the business models they were planning to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was extremely joyful when the visitors to my booth exclaimed “Wow, that is one app I think I would use!” or “This is an excellent app bro!”. They were also impressed at the various features like notification tracking and location suggestions Friendezvous offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, Orbital 2015 was an exciting journey. I am going to make it a point to develop an application every summer. I find fulfilment in learning so many technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for Friendezvous, currently it is available here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://friendezvous.herokuapp.com&quot;&gt;Friendezvous&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development is very active and Al and myself aim to launch Friendezvous as a commercial platform soon (in about 3-5 months). After which, we are planning on porting this towards an Android and iOS application as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do try Friendezvous if you can and send me your comments in the comment box on my blog or to my &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#104;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#104;&amp;#050;&amp;#048;&amp;#055;&amp;#064;&amp;#108;&amp;#105;&amp;#118;&amp;#101;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details on the Orbital programme is &lt;a href=&quot;http://orbital.comp.nus.edu.sg/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NUS First Year, Semester 4 <br> (Special Term 2) in Review</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/education/nus/college/2015/08/01/NUS%20First%20Year,%20Semester%204%20(Special%20Term%20%7C%7C)/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-01T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/education/nus/college/2015/08/01/NUS First Year, Semester 4 (Special Term ||)</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.wreporter.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/CyberSecurity.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Computer Security&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being quite free during the summer vacation period, I decided to take up CS2107: Introduction to Information and System Security in Special Term 2. It was one of the most interesting modules I have taken taught by an ever youthful professor Hugh. His energy and enthusiasm and deep knowledge on computer security made me even more curious in the various aspects of computer security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This module covers a wide range of topics from cryptography/ciphers, to common hacking methods (SQLi, Buffer overflows), protection mechanisms against such malcious attacks etc. The assessment was split into the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Homework &amp;amp; Assignments&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Project Work&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Final Exam&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;50%&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a total of 3 assignments (about 5-10 questions) which were to be done at home. They were largely manageable. Google is your best friend. Computer security is a broad topic and the more you learn, the better you understand and appreciate the various concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project work was indeed an interesting experience. My team consisted of Sri (not his real name), QY and myself. It was a tight timeline considering that the project was to be completed over a span of just 6 weeks. We embarked on the project about 2 weeks before submission, but we made the structure of the report very clear. Regular consultation with Prof Hugh was crucial in helping us achieve a clear understanding of the expectations of this project. As a team, we are really thankful for his advice and guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project was on “Common attacks on PC/UNIX/Mac devices”. Here focused on DDoS, Buffer Overflow exploitation and side-channel attacks. I personally involved myself largely towards the buffer overflow section in which I did code sample runs to check the implementation of a feature known as Address Space Layout Randomisation (ASLR) on Windows 8, Mac OS X 10.10 and Ubuntu 15.04. We also compared the effectiveness the various operating systems against the aforementioned attacks and concluded Windows offered the best protection (of course, in reality there will be a wide range of external factors to be considered as well).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final exam was manageable. I was able to refer to the relevant sections of the notes since it was an open-book examination. Some questions are specifically targeted at your understanding and some were on concepts mentioned in lectures. I guess it paid off to attend each and every lecture and tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really glad I took this module. It is one of the best modules I have taken in NUS thus far and am currently contemplating taking CS3235 (Introduction to Computer Security) sometime later. Then again, the number of required breadth electives for CEG students has been reduced to just 1 which means I need to plan my modules well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also taking it in Special Term was great since it allowed me to concentrate fully on one subject. In the regular semester, with 5-6 modules, juggling time between these modules itself is a huge task for most students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty: &lt;strong&gt;Manageable&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Grade obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A-&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Remarks: Pretty interesting module taught by an amazing professor. Take it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
V.Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Virtual Reality - Google Cardboard</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/techstuff/2015/07/12/Virtual%20Reality/"/>
   <updated>2015-07-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/techstuff/2015/07/12/Virtual Reality</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got a Google Cardboard yesterday. The Google Cardboard comes as a laser-cut template (which you have fold and fix yourself), two 45mm biconvex lenses, 2 neodymium magnets, 2 pairs of velcro and a rubberband.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really simple to fold and use and all you’ve to do is to download a VR app onto the phone and slot it into the font of the Cardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great thing about the Google Cardboard is that it utilises the magnetic switch as a trigger. So while using an app, using the ‘button’ will allow you to interact the same way as you touch your phone’s screen. As compared to other VR devices, such as the VR One, the magnetic switch is something exclusive to the Cardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many apps such as the Cardboard app (which allows you to watch movies, use Google Earth etc.), VR Roller Coaster (which takes you on a ride through the roller coaster) and the apps are definitely growing in number in the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtual Reality is definitely here to stay and it’s development excites me. It opens up many new and different possibilities that people have only dreamt of. We can start to enjoy experiences which previously required us to be physically present elsewhere. The nascent virtual reality is rapidly developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether virtual reality is good or bad, that depends. There will always be people who might use VR technologies to enjoy in the world they want, without any grasp of reality. But on the other hand, VR’s potential can surely bring quality and happiness to many lives. For now, let’s hope that VR will bring us a more enjoyable future in the coming years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#images&quot;&gt;Below&lt;/a&gt; are pictures of the Google Cardboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;images&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;cardboard&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image2.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;cardboard&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image3.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;cardboard&quot; style=&quot;height:450px&quot; src=&quot;/blog/assets/GoogleCardboard/image6.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style type=&quot;text/css&quot;&gt;
	.cardboard{
		width: 500px;
		border-radius: 15%;
	}
&lt;/style&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Elephant (Cover)</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/music/2015/07/03/The%20Elephant/"/>
   <updated>2015-07-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/music/2015/07/03/The Elephant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;An attempt to play the popular piece, “The Elephant” from the Carnival of the Animals on keyboard (transposed) in Piano mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/213071671&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Clean & Green Hackathon 2015</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2015/06/22/Clean%20&%20Green%20Hackathon/"/>
   <updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2015/06/22/Clean & Green Hackathon</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.cgs.sg/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/For-Event-Subpages.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image Credits: http://www.cgs.sg/events/calendar/hackathon/workshop/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I participated in the Clean &amp;amp; Green Hackathon this weekend. This is second hackathon I participated in after Gamecraft (Organised by NUS Games Development Group) last year. It was particularly a very enriching experience. Held on a larger scale (nation-wide) and open to all ideas and hacks (including hardware, software, apps, games etc.) and people from all age groups, I was able to understand what to expect in a hackathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike a continuous 24 hours hackathon, we were allowed to go home and return the next morning. It took place over a period of 3 days, starting from Friday (Ideation and pitching) till Sunday (when the judging and prize presentation was held).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to know many people from different backgrounds and learn a lot from their ideas as well. Some were just there for the pure fun of it, to exchange ideas and make good friends. Some ideas were just excellent and gave me many new insights into further development of my own idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, my team (Kenny, Yong Zhi &amp;amp; myself) came up with the idea of a web &amp;amp; mobile ready platform called “The Greenlist”. It is basically a peer-to-peer connecting app where one can post his/her old items (eg: laptops, handphones, toys, books, furniture etc.) up for donation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who needs this item but are willing to have it secondhand (and for free) can simply claim this item, and thereafter proceed to collect the item from the donor themselves. Each successful donation earns the donor some reward points which can then be redeemed for vouchers. To fund the operating costs (which are minimal), we proposed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In-App Advertising&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In-App Purchases (Eco-friendly items etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sponsorship for vouchers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Optional donation before claiming an item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the idea was formed, we made a prototype both for the web and mobile platform (using Justinmind software).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, as the group leader, I made the pitch for our idea and gave a demo of our prototype. Given only 3 minutes for the pitch, it was crucial to make the most out of each and every second to create an everlasting impression of the idea &amp;amp; product/service. Though nervous, having take some public speaking training and course in NUS allowed me to focus on the pitch and do my best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the learning points was that I realised that I might have focused too much on the demo of the prototype itself. I should have instead allocated a major part towards helping the audience understand and appreciate the relevance and usefulness of the app in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the idea is crucial in a hackathon (even more than the prototype)! An effective idea will definitely win people over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though, my team did not win, we were thankful for the experience. This hackathon gave me some crucial experience that will help me do better in the forthcoming hackathons I will be participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Greenlist” project is hosted &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/harishv7/thegreenlist&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clean &amp;amp; Green Hackathon event was covered by Channel NewsAsia and the coverage &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/ideas-to-solve-littering/1931422.html?cid=fbsg&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photos of the Hackathon are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.842836635769622.1073741869.310427622343862&amp;amp;type=3&quot;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details on the teams and ideas which won and competition details are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.upsingapore.com/events/clean-green-hackathon-2015/#hackathonhome&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Greensleeves</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/music/2015/06/05/Greensleeves/"/>
   <updated>2015-06-05T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/music/2015/06/05/Greensleeves</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is a small attempt to play the popular English folk song Greensleeves (Played in Dmin Key with Time Signature of 3/4) on my keyboard! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the above player does not work, see below for the SoundCloud embed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greensleeves (Melody)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/208950439&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greensleeves with Chords&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/212482253&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greensleeves with Rhythm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/213071440&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NUS First Year, Second Semester in Review</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/education/2015/06/04/NUS%20First%20Year,%20Semester%202%20in%20Review/"/>
   <updated>2015-06-04T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/education/2015/06/04/NUS First Year, Semester 2 in Review</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following post is also available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/06/04/nus-first-year-semester-2-in-review/&quot;&gt;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/06/04/nus-first-year-semester-2-in-review/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a long freshman year and I am surprised I am already writing a review for my 2nd semester at NUS. Semester 2 was much tougher than Semester 1, but ironically my grades were slightly better (yes, I can’t believe it too!).Thanks to the bell curve I suppose. Anyway, here is the module review:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CG1108: Electrical Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good module that introduces the basic concepts of electrical engineering. I found the pace of the lectures very manageable compared to other modules. The total number of chapters covered is actually not a lot, and hence it allows you enough time to fully comprehend and grasp the basic concepts before moving onto the next chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My lecturer for this module was Dr Sahoo. He is a very approachable lecturer and teaches very well. I find it important to attend his lectures (never missed any) since most of the working and examples are done in the lecture itself. Though the slides with the digitally written solutions are uploaded, it is much easier to follow through the lecture and examples in real time rather than at home where you have to figure them out all by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assessment of the module is shared equally between the hands-on segment and the theory section. Hands-on segment includes the labs (10% attendance and 10% lab test) and the exciting Arduino car project (25%). Labs are manageable and you will be guided by your group’s assigned mentor. The lab test is very similar to whatever content you have learnt during the practical labs and make sure to watch the equipment briefing video uploaded by the ECE department to have a complete knowledge of the equipment and how to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The car project was what many of us were looking forward to. There was a lot of time given for us to work on the car project. It is of high importance that you select your groupmates carefully. They must appreciate your suggestions and be willing to help each other out and put in a good amount of effort to work together and achieve the target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I did not like about the car project was the lack of constant results. The car basically takes input from the light-dependent resistors (LDR) and these resistors are very sensitive to the ambient light which makes it difficult to get consistent results. Nevertheless, I think the car project was one of the most exciting parts of the module. I still remember my friends’ and my reaction when our car worked for the first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory section includes the mid-term test (10%) and final exam (40%). Both exams were manageable and as long as the basic concepts and application has been mastered it should not be a problem to score well. For the final exam, practising past year papers is crucial in understanding the type of questions to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Difficulty: Average&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GEK1549: Critical Thinking and Writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GEK1549 was quite enjoyable. Like many, I did not like this module initially, but as time went, I began appreciating what was being taught. It is very systematic and really probes your thinking. The theme for our batch was on “Sustainable Cities”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no lectures, only tutorials. My tutor was Dr Sadorra. She is really nice and approachable and gave me and my teammates very constructive comments and suggestions during the course of the module. She also prepares her own slides and provides good external references to clarify concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assessment is divided into 3 parts. Assignment 1 (30%) requires the submission of a graphic organiser, summary and evaluation of a given article. Assignment 2 (30%) is a position paper that is done in groups. And Assignment 3 (10%) is essentially class participation. The other 30% comes from the final exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to do particularly well in both Assignments 1 &amp;amp; 2 and made effort to participate in class as much as possible. I felt the final exam was doable, but I was restricted due to the lack of time. Make sure you have good teammates for Assignment 2. Always have a clear foundation and roadmap as to what you will be doing for the position paper. In my case, for the problem-solution paper, I made sure that the problem and solutions are clearly linked. And to make our paper stand out, my teammates and I ensured that the proposed solutions were specific to the city and are feasible in the implmentation. Not an easy task, but you’ll get there after some considerable time into research and analysis. Be sure to utilise NUS Libraries website. The resources there will surely aid in obtaining reliable sources for the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all a very manageable module, provided you put in good effort in understanding the tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Difficulty: Average&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CS1020: Data Structures and Algorithms I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my favourite module of this semester due to my personal interest in computer programming. But, this was definitely not a easy module. The content covered were heavy and it requires a lot of practise and understanding to get used to the concepts taught. And before you are familar with one concept another concept will be taught. It requires discipline and effort to do some programming and to study for the module daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecturers for this module are Mr Aaron Tan and Dr Low. Both lecturers are very good in terms of teaching new concepts. They give plenty of examples to ensure our understanding is complete. It is important to attend and understand tutorials. Even when I couldn’t do or finish a particular tutorial, I made it a point to attend classes to ensure I do not neglect the tutorial. It kept me on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assessment for the module was divided into many parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Tutorial Attendance/Participation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lab Attendance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Take-Home Labs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sit-in Labs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mid-term Test&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Final Exam&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The least you can do is to secure the marks from tutorial/lab attendance and take-home labs. This is greatly help in achieving a good grade. Take-home labs are often challenging, but you will given at least a week before the submission. Hence, ensure that you are able to solve these labs. Else, seek help during the lab sessions. The tutors are really helpful when you ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a fast paced module. On any given week, you will most probably either have a sit-in lab or a take-home lab due. Consistent work and practice is of vital importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final exam was slightly tough for me. I realised I have made many careless mistakes after completing the exam. Otherwise, the difficulty of the questions asked were similar to those in tutorials. Focus on important topics such as recursion, hashing, sorting etc. These are major concepts that have a higher probability of being tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a tough and fast paced module that definitely requires more effort than what you normally put in for a 4MC module. Discipline to revise and practice questions (on Codecrunch) on a regular basis is important from the start of the module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my codes are hosted &lt;a href=&quot;http://harishv7.github.io/portfolio/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/harishv7&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheatsheet for final exam is now hosted &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BwSVKyZQM1obbzVJUTBXWFIzVkk/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (Please do write your own, this is only for reference, not reproduction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A-&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Difficulty: Tough&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;PC1432: Physics IIE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the toughest module for me. The rate at which chapters and concepts were covered was astonishing. I could barely keep up with the pace and was lost even before the recess week. It did not help that many of the chapters were inter-linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a total of 3 lecturers. All of them were engaging and taught really well. But, it required a lot of effort from my side to fully grasp what they were saying and taking time to practice extra questions outside the tutorials. The questions from the tutorials are NOT enough as practice. The recommended textbook was really helpful for me to get a better understanding of the concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assessment was divided into practical viva/reports (10%), online assignment from Mastering Physics (10%), mid-term test (20%) and final exam (60%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure that you do your best for the practicals and online assignments as these are relatively easier to score. The mid-term was manageable except for the time restriction. Planning your time during the examination is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the final exam very hard and was afraid I did not do as well as I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a fast-paced and tough module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A-&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Difficulty: Very Hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;MA1506: Mathematics II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MA1506 was much more manageable than MA1505, which I took in semester 1. This module covers a great depth into Differential Equations and linear algebra, linear transformations and Laplace transforms. Many of these concepts are crucial for engineering students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assessment is divided into mid-term test (20%) and final exam (80%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part involving differential equations (DE) was fairly manageable and was even fun when modelling systems. All it requires is a good understanding of the various ways to solve DEs which can be achieved with sufficient practice from tutorials. The mid-term test was fully MCQ (10 questions in one hour) and was quite easy. I was able to score full marks for this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After recess week, the pace of lectures started to increase together with the difficulty of concepts. Webcasted lectures were really helpful when I was revising to clarify my doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final exam was manageable. Make sure you have sufficient practice form the past year papers (check NUS Library website or IVLE). Since there are solutions provided, it helps to understand the structure of the questions. Questions are usually similar year to year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure the help sheet (2 sides of 1 A4 sheet) is well prepared. You can see my help sheets &lt;a title=&quot;MA1505 &amp;amp; MA1506 Help Sheets&quot; href=&quot;https://harishv7.wordpress.com/2015/05/26/ma1505-ma1506-help-sheets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here for reference&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a title=&quot;MA1505/MA1506 Helpsheets&quot; href=&quot;http://harishv7.github.io/nus/2015/05/26/MA1505%20&amp;amp;%20MA1506%20Help%20Sheets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, a manageable module, provided sufficient effort is put in to understand fundamental concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade Obtained: &lt;strong&gt;B+&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
Difficulty: Manageable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope the above reviews and tips were helpful! Comments are welcome (use the Disqus thread below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MA1505 & MA1506 Help Sheets</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/2015/05/26/MA1505%20&%20MA1506%20Help%20Sheets/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-26T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/2015/05/26/MA1505 & MA1506 Help Sheets</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Both MA1505 and MA1506 are common modules undertaken by a vast majority of engineering students. They are not exactly easy, and so I thought I will post the helpsheets I have made for my examinations here in the hope that some of the students may find it useful when doing their own helpsheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do note that it is crucial for students to make their own helpsheets as printed or photocopied helpsheets are strictly not allowed. And from experience, it always helps to make your own helpsheet as it comes in as a form of revision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obbEJiaW4zTFB5T0E&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MA1505 Helpsheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BwSVKyZQM1obQzdodmNwUEtvd2c&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MA1506 Helpsheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NOC Interview (Round 1)</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/2015/05/25/NOC%20Interview%20Round%201/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-25T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/2015/05/25/NOC Interview Round 1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went for the NOC interview a few weeks back, just before my final examinations for semester 2. As it was mentioned in the confirmatione email, it was agroup interview indeed. My session was on the morning of Thursday and had about 8 people including me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were divided into 2 groups and given a hypothetical situation to discuss upon. In my case, we were given 2 simple business models (not as complex as you think) and then we had to discuss which business model will be more successful in the long run. The interviewers were very friendly and approachable. It is crucial to note that the interviewers are NOT looking for a correct answer. In fact, there is no right or wrong answer and it depends entirely upon how you feel. As long as you and your groupmates agree upon a common model and explain in as much detail as possible why it is the better one, you would have done your job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In such group interview situations, the best way to make an impression is to try and lead the discussion from the start, which I did. So, instead of sitting around and looking at each other in awkward silence, initate the discussion and the overview. It was a good thing that all members of my team agreed uniformly on the model I had in mind. Then, immediately after settling the main topic of discussion, I tried to model the scope of the discussion by listing out the relevant factors to the topic. After which, I decided on the factors I will be presenting and the subsequent allocation of the other factors for my group members to present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the presentation went very well and at the end of the discussion it seemed that the interviewers did agree with our choice of model. I was happy to receive the news that I have successfully passed the first stage of the selection and am current anticipating the second round of interview coming soon in August/September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Points I learnt: &lt;/strong&gt;
You are being noted once you step into the interview room. Everything that you say and do will have an impact on the impression the interviewers have on you.
Learn to be concise. It’s not necessary to talk as much as possible to show that you are good. Being concise will show that you have a clear mind and are focused on what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Catching Up</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/others/2015/05/14/Catching%20Up/"/>
   <updated>2015-05-14T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/others/2015/05/14/Catching Up</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been a hectic semester! Seems like the last time I blogged was before my semester. In NUS they always say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The only easy semester was the last semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it might be true. I was a little confident that the first semester would have helped me to adjust to the environment and that the second semester will be much easier to cope. Though I have gotten used to the environment, the workload is definitely on the rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is extremely hard to achieve a work-life balance as there is a lot of pressure to give your best. I realise that I can achieve well when I really appreciate and love what I am learning instead of going through the motion of education at college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully summer is finally here and I hope to get a good break. I have a lot of mini projects to accomplish this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the projects will be Friendezvous, which I am doing for a “module” called Orbital. Please do support me by liking the Facebook page &lt;a href=&quot;www.fb.com/ProjectFriendezvous&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My module reviews for the previous semester are on their way! ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then,&lt;br /&gt;
Cheers&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Thoughts with Mass???</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/thoughts/2015/01/17/Thoughts%20with%20Mass/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/thoughts/2015/01/17/Thoughts with Mass</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-140&quot; src=&quot;https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/uni6.gif?w=250&quot; alt=&quot;https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;Image Credits: https://helenmagnani.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was reading The Lost Symbol, by Dan Brown, there was an interesting idea shared which immediately awed me. It deals with the hypothetical question: “Do thoughts have mass?”. Though, on a weighing scale, thoughts may possess mass ranging in the nano to femto scale, if they do have a mass, there will be many implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of which was presented in the book was on gravity. If our thoughts had some mass, they will be bound by the laws of physics. Which meant, they will exert a gravitational force on other matter (though the force is of a very very small scale). Despite the insignificant amount force by a single thought, when a group of people come together to think on the same idea, this collective force becomes significant. It might then start to attract others towards this idea or notion. And that, will be powerful, when a thought can attract others and influence them to think in a certain way too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is a hypothetical question, the implications simply awed me. Upon further thinking: With thoughts having some mass, they will also be bounded by the Law of Conservation of Energy. Thoughts cannot be destroyed entirely. Instead, the thoughts are simply converted from one thought/idea to another. Or, they may become converted into another form of energy (likely chemical energy) in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is fascinating to imagine the implications if such a hypothesis was proven to be real. Whether it is true if thoughts have mass or not, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of my favourite quotes on the power of thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Change your thoughts and you change your world. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Norman Vincent Peale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are what our thoughts have made us; so take care about what you think. Words are secondary. Thoughts live; they travel far. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Swami Vivekananda&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Concentrate all your thoughts upon the work at hand. The sun’s rays do not burn until brought to a focus. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Alexander Graham Bell&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A positive attitude causes a chain reaction of positive thoughts, events and outcomes. It is a catalyst and it sparks extraordinary results. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Wade Boggs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NUS Gradeless First Semester</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/2014/12/29/NUS%20Gradeless%20First%20Sem/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/2014/12/29/NUS Gradeless First Sem</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NUS has introduced gradeless first semester since AY2014/15. And I am from AY14/15 batch. Though gradeless semester seems enticing, there’s really more to it. There are some conditions and pointers to take note which will leave you confused if you’re not used to the NUS system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things to know: NUS utilises the Cumulative Average Point (CAP) to determine the performance of a student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formula for determining CAP: &lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium wp-image-126&quot; src=&quot;https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/screen-shot-2014-12-24-at-1-29-19-pm.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Screen Shot 2014-12-24 at 1.29.19 pm&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;32&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically the numerator is the sum of the product of module credits and grade points and the denominator is the sum of the module credits for ALL the modules taken so far. It’s crucial to note the cumulative function of the CAP. Hence, it is not determined on a per semester basis, but rather for the 3-4 years of modules taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To maximise the S/U options given during the gradeless semester, there are some things to note first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the class of degree you&#39;re aiming for.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Degrees awarded are classified as shown (taken from NUS website):
&lt;table border=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honours Degree Classification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Criteria&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Honours (Highest Distinction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;CAP 4.50 and above&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Honours (Distinction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.0 to 4.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Honours (Merit)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.5 to 3.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Honours&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0 to 3.49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pass&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0 to 2.99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fail&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Below 2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Note the Grade Point table:
&lt;table border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Letter Grades:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A+&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;B+&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;B-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;C+&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;D+&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;F&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grade Points:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;0.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the target is Honours (Highest Distinction), then a CAP of 4.50 and above is required by the end of your 3-4 years. To achieve this, the average grade for the modules you took for 4 years must be at least an A-.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Therefore, during the S/U option, S/U anything below A- is a good option, since it will increase the number of modules with grades A- and above&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the first semester is a good indication of the performance for the rest of the semesters, then S/Uing any modules with a gradepoint below your CAP is a good idea. For example, your CAP is 4.44, and your grades are A,A-, A,B+,B+, then S/U modules below 4.44 which are the 2 B+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gradepoints allocated to the grades, for example 4.0 for a B+ means it will pull your overall CAP towards the 4.0. Hence, unless the overall CAP is below 4.0, then B+ would not really help with pushing the CAP upwards.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NUS CAP Calculator</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/cap/2014/12/28/NUS%20CAP%20Calculator/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/cap/2014/12/28/NUS CAP Calculator</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here is a CAP calculator I made in excel. Just a simple excel sheet that helps to keep track of your grades. Feedback welcome and updates will be made to add other functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click here to download &lt;a href=&quot;assets/cap-calculator1.xlsx&quot;&gt;CAP Calculator v1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update! : V1.1: &lt;a href=&quot;assets/cap-calculator2.xlsx&quot;&gt;CAP Calculator v1.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: this was done to be just used as a guide. Check with faculty for degree requirements and the NUS FASS calculator if necessary).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspired from &lt;a title=&quot;Agagooga&#39;s CAP Calculator&quot; href=&quot;http://gssq.entori.net/files/capcalc.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Agagooga’s CAP calculator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better CAP calculator with better user interface is coming, for the web, desktop and mobile platforms. Stay tuned! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>First Semester in NUS</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/nus/education/2014/12/25/First%20Semester%20in%20NUS/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-25T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/nus/education/2014/12/25/First Semester in NUS</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s has been a great semester. Well, it was stressful, but it was particularly fulfilling. University life is exciting as I get to learn what I am most passionate about. The gradeless semester is another point that allowed me to read the modules without worrying too much about grades. Nevertheless, I was never aiming to SU any modules. Here is a quick review of the modules I took in Semester 1. All of them are pre-allocated since I am a Computer Engineering student, except the GEM I took.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CG1001: Introduction to Computer Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this module sums it up all. This module is meant to provide an overview of Computer Engineering for freshmen and allow them to have a clear understanding of what areas they can specialise in during their senior years. Basically, the workload is not much. &lt;br /&gt;
I was tasked with 2 reports (based on the specialisation areas in Computer Engineering) and a project video. The reports are 25% each and the video is 50%. Reports are done in pairs (randomly grouped by the professor). Similarly, for the project video, you will be assigned a group of four randomly. Then you have present a video (about 5 mins long) which presents the topic chosen in a creative and informative way. My group chose the topic on 4G LTE networks. We personally did it in the form of an advertisement and incorporated animation to make the video more interactive. This module is meant to help you pull up your CAP (though it is only 2 MCs). Give it your best, especially for the reports. Be creative and analytical when discussing the selected topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grade I obtained: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Very much delighted to have obtained an A. I had really given my best for the reports and the video (especially the animation and planning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CS1010: Programming Methodolody&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my most favourite module of this semester. I have no experience programming in C language. However, I was familiar with other languages like Python, Javascript and HTML. I personally like programming very much. The natural interest motivated me to do my best for this module. However, do not worry if you have no previous programming experience. Make sure you start learning the basics well, and do one practice task per day (there’s plenty of tasks on the CS1010 website). My lecturer was Mr Gary Tan. He is one amazing lecturer. He makes learning enjoyable and he is really funny. I am really happy to learn under him. He offered us a lot of help (separate group discussions and marking my past-year CS1010 papers I did for practice). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lectures are taught in a flipped-classroom method. You are expected to revise the slides and notes before the lectures (held in computer labs). This is very important indeed. Despite the long lecture, it’s not enough to cover all the concepts thoroughly. It requires many hours of practise to get the programming concepts and fluency expected of you. The module grading is broken up into 2 practical exams (10%, 25%), 1 mid-term test (15%), take home lab assignments (5%), attendance (5%) and the final exam (40%). I did not do well for the 2 practical exams. The first one was especially bad. Though I had good practice, the exam stress itself and the pressure under time restrictions made me panic. As a result, I was not able to complete the 2 tasks on time. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another mistake was that I focused on code logic and clarity, thinking that these criteria were also awarded significant marks. However, only after the exam did I know that close to 60% will be awarded for the correct output. Hence, focus on obtaining the right output. Your code may be inefficient, but it is your output that is being considered. Therefore, note that you are being awarded the marks for your ability to complete the task. The take home lab assignments are quite challenging. Try your best to complete it during the weekends. Last-minute stress is never good. Consult your friends and lecturers if you do not know how to do them. Lastly, and most importantly, finish the task within the suggested time limit (comes in helpful for the practical exams). Attendance and the lab marks (5% each) are really a giveaway for this module. Utilise it well and don’t skip tutorials unless you have a valid MC. The final exam was quite easy for me, except for one question. I guess it helped me to make up for the practical exams which I did not do as expected. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade for CS1010: &lt;strong&gt;A-&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not exactly very happy with A-. Being my favourite module, I had really wanted an A+. But the practical exams pulled my overall grade down. :/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CS1231: Discrete Structures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally did not like this module when I first started. But as it progressed, I began to appreciate this module. It provides a different view to common concepts. You learn to prove everything. For example, you learn to prove that an even number plus another even number is even. Such seemingly simple things which we just assume to be true must be proven. One of the coolest things you’ll learn is to prove that 1+1 = 2. Well, if before this module, someone asked me to prove that I would have been stunned. But now, I do have an answer that proves this to be true. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecturers for the module were Prof Stephen Bressan and Prof Bryan Low. Both of them were good. Prof Stephen likes to ask interesting questions on the topic and invites your opinions and answers. But he does cover the chapters very quickly (especially the proofs). Prof Bryan Low was good too. He actually goes through every proof that is in his notes and makes sure that you understand it clearly. Both lecturers are really approachable. Make sure to clear your doubts immediately after the lecture (before you forget them). That being said, this module is really demanding as the pace of the lectures is extremely fast. The tutorials are really crucial for you to grasp the application of the concepts learnt during lectures to the questions in your tutorials. Personal advice: Do NOT skip the tutorials. The recommended textbook is Discrete Mathematics Demystified. I found it barely enough to understand all the concepts taught. Nevertheless, it helped me greatly to comprehend the basic concepts in each chapter. For challenging exercises, see past year questions or ask your tutor. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The module is graded based on a video project, a mid-term test and the final exam. As for the video project, my team focused on exploring the game of Tic Tac Toe. The video has been embed here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Mo1_F806J_I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video project is meant to help you to pull your grade up. Do give your best in terms of analysing and presenting the chosen topic. The mid-term test was quite easy and the final exam was moderately difficult. Some questions only required common sense, while others really tested the concepts and formulas you’ve been taught. All in all, a content-heavy module that can be done well with consistent practise and dedication to learning the concepts well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really happy with the grade as I did not expect it. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GEM2027: Public Speaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to choose to do a SS/GEM/breadth module in the first semester. Public speaking was the only module that fitted my timetable and the skill itself seemed really useful. Plus a bonus was that there were no exams. Of course, instead of the final exam, you will be graded on some of the speeches and there will be a module quiz at the end as well as a video project to be delivered. Lecturer for the module is Ms Cardoza. She is a very good lecturer and I like her enthusiasm in each lecture. She is very approachable (both personally and on forums) and encouraged me to give my best in my speeches. The lectures basically introduces some tips and pointers for effective public speaking. Some are really common sense, but the thing is that many of us fail to follow them. We need to remember simple things like body language (eg: do not put your hands in your pockets) and tone which will be critiqued by your tutor. Such seemingly simple pointers will be reinforced again and again throughout the module. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graded speeches are Informative (15%), Persuasive (20%) and Responders-Critique (15%). The other 50% is for the quiz and video. While there was plenty of time given for each speech, personally it really took up loads of time to prepare a good speech. It wasn’t as easy as writing the speech alone. Firstly, the speech category is broad. Hence, you will naturally spend quite a bit of time thinking on which topic you should speak about. Second, the preparation requires hours of research and analysis to support your points (any claim you make must be supported to establish your credibility to the audience). Third, you need to make your speech interesting, add some funny elements etc. Fourth, you need to practise again and again to ensure good body language and fluency of your speech. Fifth, if visual aids like PowerPoint is being used, you need to create the slides and practise controlling the slides. As you see, you need many hours of preparation before each speech. I usually use up my whole weekend doing the above. It wasn’t helpful that all my modules had tight deadlines to meet. Of course, if you’re someone who can manage your time easily or have prior experience in public speaking, this comes easy. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor is that the marks awarded for the speeches largely depend on how strict is your tutor is. Well, my tutor did have very high expectations since he speaks frequently at events and has a lot of experience in public speaking. Naturally, he expected a much more. Hence, the grade you get depends very much on your tutor too! Nevertheless, give your best and you will get what you deserve. The video project was really fun! We were free to do any video to express the ideas we have learnt in the course. My group created a comic-book type of video that is presented in terms of a storyboard. I enjoyed the project. Since it is due near the last week of the semester, you will barely have time to meet up for the project. Another downside was that my team members were all from different years of study (all of them were in Year 4 and from different faculties/majors). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it was almost impossible to get a time-slot to meet and discuss. We had to do it right away after class. Surprisingly, our video got shortlisted as one of the top ten! But we did not win the top prize though. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can view the video &lt;a title=&quot;Public Speaking - No Longer Clarkie&#39;s Kryptonite! &quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hOZsQ18Ufhs&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/hOZsQ18Ufhs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tips:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Always take a topic you are well knowledgeable about and confident with.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Try to be clear of the structure of your entire speech before deciding on it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It may help to write out the entire speech and then do the Preparation Outline (PO). All you would need to do is to copy and paste the relevant sections from the speech into the PO (with some rephrases, of course).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Try to buy a clicker to control the PowerPoint slides when presenting, or ask your close friend to lend you one (like I did).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Creativity is greatly rewarded in this module. Especially for your video project, presenting the learning points in a creative manner can help you achieve good marks!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Final grade: &lt;strong&gt;B+&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not very satisfied with this grade. I expected an A-. Nevertheless, I am sure I have given my best for this module. Public speaking is a skill you have keep developing anyway. Overall, it was a great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;MA1505: Mathematics I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many concepts you need to understand for this module. Whenever you have free time, learn to utilise it to revise the upcoming topics. Though the lectures are nicely-paced, the amount of concepts to grasp requires quite some time. The last few topics (line and surface integrals may be difficult to grasp). The module is graded with a mid-term test (20%) and the final exam (80%). My lecturer for this module was Prof Leung Pui Fai (Fred). He is a very good lecturer. He takes the time to explain concepts very patiently. He is also very approachable. Make sure to pay good attention during the lectures. If you find the pace slow or you missed the lecture then you can always use the webcast on IVLE. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial topics revolve around the ‘A’ level content such as differentiation, integration, functions, vectors etc. Hence, you might not need much time to grasp these concepts. However, for other topics like line integrals and surface integrals, you must be able to visualise what the formula you are using actually means. Everything you do will involved 3D manipulation. So, you have to visualise in 3D as well. This is the hardest part. Initially, I was a little lax about practise since I was able to do all the tutorial questions. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mid-term test was an eye-opener. The questions really test your understanding and are tricky. Mid-term questions are tricky and requires good thinking and speed to complete on time. Make sure to practise all the past-year papers which are available at IVLE and NUS e-library. It is a tough module, but with consistent practise you can do well. The one A4 paper (2-sided) cheat sheet really helps! Make sure to prepare your cheat sheet well. Ensure it is comprehensive and note that they are strict with the term “2-sided A4 sheet”. Only use a single A4 white paper to write notes on both sides. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final grade: &lt;strong&gt;B+&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have done better (especially in the MCQ mid-term test), but a B+ is not too bad I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was a good semester. Despite the 3 video projects (video projects really take up a lot of time!), I learnt a lot through the term. I could have done better in MA1505 and CS1010, but it is all in the learning experience to not repeat your mistakes. Most importantly, I have learned to manage my time better and study for the love of learning. Not just for the grades. Looking forward to the next semester. Till then,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Stay Hungry, Stay Foolish!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Most Powerful Thing in the World</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2014/12/20/Most%20Powerful%20Thing%20in%20the%20World/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2014/12/20/Most Powerful Thing in the World</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what is the most powerful thing in the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, its not money, not wealth, maybe love, but really I think its an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yup, an idea. Every single day, we see ideas that change and craft the world. From the phone in your hand to the computer you’re reading this blog on, every thing around us took root from the idea that came up in someone’s brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you think about it, an idea isn’t something tangible. Not any physical product you can touch and understand. Nevertheless, you can feel it. And if an idea is powerful enough, it can change the world for the better, or for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I particularly felt galvanised watching Inception. Inception is basically about implanting someone else’s idea into a target’s subconscious, deep enough, that it changes their way of thinking. Well, an idea seems like a simple thing. But the potential and the potency of an idea goes beyond itself. It creates a chain reaction so complex that without that single idea in a person’s brain, the world might have been different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea right now, in your head is something so powerful. Make sure it is put to good use. To make a change for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you really want something, all the Universe conspires in helping you achieve it. -The Alchemist, Paulo Coelho&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a quote I always remember. What you are, who you are is defined by your ideas, your actions. If you have a good idea, and truly believe in it, then give it your best shot. Make your ideas come alive.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>I need an Internship!!</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/education/general/nus/2014/12/09/I%20need%20an%20Internship/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-09T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/education/general/nus/2014/12/09/I need an Internship</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Every computer engineer who is passionate about what he does will want to create or inspire a change that makes a difference in this world. Many a times, these inspirations, to even start, does not come from just pure academics, but rather from the practical experiences we gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I came across the this post which shows the best places where we can develop ourselves and get the inspiration we have always been looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As listed on Business Insider, the top tech internships are offered by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google
Qualcomm
Microsoft
Intel
Cisco
IBM
Amazon
Apparently, the interview difficulty in getting the internship increases as we climb the list. Well, at the same time the salary increases (ranges between $5k – 6k) too. So you get what you work for despite the stiff competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it is not only the best tech giants that can provide good internships. A good internship is one where we can learn to the fullest, about the process of not only creating ideas, but implementing it into a practical solution that yields tangible and visible results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best place where we can get such an experience will definitely be the start-up sectors. Here is where true entrepreneurship flourishes. Here is where we can learn the nitty gritty details of kicking off from the ground, to flying the plane, and landing at the destination. And here is where, you learn to unveil the entrepreneur in you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aminariana.com/essays/ultimate-internship&quot;&gt;Related article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the unconventional path to do the greater good in the world. Where’s the fun when everyone wants to the conventional things in life. Risk-taking and courage are truly the qualities of the successful leaders we see today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small quote from Apple:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg&quot; /&gt;Image Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/7/6238/6225876653_b13ce9b0e9_z.jpg&quot;&gt;staticflickr.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gamecraft 2014</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2014/12/05/Gamecraft%202014/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-05T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2014/12/05/Gamecraft 2014</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently took part in Gamecraft 2014, organised by NUS Games Development Group (GDG). My first so-called “hackathon” experience. Glad to have worked with great teammates, Alvian, Chris &amp;amp; Tio. Learnt a lot from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the given 24 hours and under the theme of “Contact”, we had to design and build a working game! This was a tough task, since we had to ideate within a short span of time and build a working prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, some of my teammates had prior experience with platforms such as Gamemaker and Unity which allowed us to have a clear vision of how exactly are we going to execute our gameplan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the link to final copy of the 2D game, titled “ConTag”, which also won us the 2nd Prize in Gamecraft 2014!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/sh/o2snaeg836jelzr/AAD-Lxa5URgMqDPM-J8G1cr9a?dl=0&quot;&gt;Download ConTag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers, &lt;br /&gt;
Harish&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Welcome!</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2014/12/03/Welcome/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2014/12/03/Welcome</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;Behind every victory, there lies an undying passion.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello. I am Harish. This is my personal blog which I share my projects and reflections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,
Harish V&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Hello World</title>
   <link href="harishv7.github.io/blog/general/2014/12/03/HelloWorld/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
   <id>harishv7.github.io/blog/blog/general/2014/12/03/HelloWorld</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World! This is a mandatory first post!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
