<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</title>
	  <link>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>We all talk about productivity and efficiency today. So here is my way of getting my things done.</p>

<p>I primarily use two platforms to get my stuff done: <a href="https://workflowy.com">Workflowy</a> and <a href="https://calendar.google.com/">Google Calendar</a>. Workflowy is an amazing platform that is buuilt on a simple idea: making lists. At first look, it may look so simple and plain and even no greater than a Notepad like web-app. But, it is amazing intuitive to use and I am usually able to structure and plan according the the priority of tasks.</p>

<p>I usually think in a structured, top-down way and I would probably attribute that to my engineering-based education. So a typical structure I impose in Workflowy is this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Urgent</li>
  <li>Important</li>
  <li>Upcoming</li>
  <li>KIV</li>
</ol>

<p>These are listed in order of priority and shows me which task I need to get done next.</p>

<p>Under each of these categories, I make tasks and their relevant sub-tasks. For example, I have an Engineering exam this coming week, I create a task called “Engineering Exam”. Under this task, I include a label called “Details” which indicates the time, date and location of this task and “Revision” which then contains the relevant sections and chapters to revise as sub-sub-tasks.</p>

<p>One of the greatest things about Workflowy is that you can create many many layers of sub-sub-sub-sub-…. tasks. However, an important feature that is missing is reminders.</p>

<p>For this, I use Google Calendar. All deadlines and events immediately go into my Google Account with a default alert set for 1 and 2 days before the actual date. This together with my list of tasks of Workflowy keeps me organised.</p>

<p>I check this list at the start of the day and update it as and when tasks come in. At the end of the day, I check if all intended tasks for the day have been completed. If yes, I complete them. If no, I move and reschedule them on the level of priority. Before sleeping, I spend 5 minutes working out the relevant tasks and agenda for tomorrow by simply adding a hashtag (#tomrrow) beside the tasks in Workflowy.</p>

<p>This system has worked great so far and I believe it has been a key reason for my productivity too.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Thoughts with Mass???</title>
	  <link>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-01-17T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Thoughts-with-Mass</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif"><img class="size-medium wp-image-140" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/uni6.gif?w=250" alt="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif" width="250" height="300" />Image Credits: https://helenmagnani.wordpress.com/</a></p>

<p>As I was reading The Lost Symbol, by Dan Brown, there was an interesting idea shared which immediately awed me. It deals with the hypothetical question: “Do thoughts have mass?”. Though, on a weighing scale, thoughts may possess mass ranging in the nano to femto scale, if they do have a mass, there will be many implications.</p>

<p>One of which was presented in the book was on gravity. If our thoughts had some mass, they will be bound by the laws of physics. Which meant, they will exert a gravitational force on other matter (though the force is of a very very small scale). Despite the insignificant amount force by a single thought, when a group of people come together to think on the same idea, this collective force becomes significant. It might then start to attract others towards this idea or notion. And that, will be powerful, when a thought can attract others and influence them to think in a certain way too.</p>

<p>Although it is a hypothetical question, the implications simply awed me. Upon further thinking: With thoughts having some mass, they will also be bounded by the Law of Conservation of Energy. Thoughts cannot be destroyed entirely. Instead, the thoughts are simply converted from one thought/idea to another. Or, they may become converted into another form of energy (likely chemical energy) in the brain.</p>

<p>Indeed, it is fascinating to imagine the implications if such a hypothesis was proven to be real. Whether it is true if thoughts have mass or not, only time will tell.</p>

<p>A few of my favourite quotes on the power of thoughts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Change your thoughts and you change your world. <br />
<strong>Norman Vincent Peale</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are what our thoughts have made us; so take care about what you think. Words are secondary. Thoughts live; they travel far. <br />
<strong>Swami Vivekananda</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Concentrate all your thoughts upon the work at hand. The sun’s rays do not burn until brought to a focus. <br />
<strong>Alexander Graham Bell</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>A positive attitude causes a chain reaction of positive thoughts, events and outcomes. It is a catalyst and it sparks extraordinary results. <br />
<strong>Wade Boggs</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Most Powerful Thing in the World</title>
	  <link>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-20T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Have you ever wondered what is the most powerful thing in the world?</p>

<p>Well, its not money, not wealth, maybe love, but really I think its an idea.</p>

<p>Yup, an idea. Every single day, we see ideas that change and craft the world. From the phone in your hand to the computer you’re reading this blog on, every thing around us took root from the idea that came up in someone’s brain.</p>

<p>But when you think about it, an idea isn’t something tangible. Not any physical product you can touch and understand. Nevertheless, you can feel it. And if an idea is powerful enough, it can change the world for the better, or for the worse.</p>

<p>I particularly felt galvanised watching Inception. Inception is basically about implanting someone else’s idea into a target’s subconscious, deep enough, that it changes their way of thinking. Well, an idea seems like a simple thing. But the potential and the potency of an idea goes beyond itself. It creates a chain reaction so complex that without that single idea in a person’s brain, the world might have been different.</p>

<p>The idea right now, in your head is something so powerful. Make sure it is put to good use. To make a change for the better.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you really want something, all the Universe conspires in helping you achieve it. -The Alchemist, Paulo Coelho</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a quote I always remember. What you are, who you are is defined by your ideas, your actions. If you have a good idea, and truly believe in it, then give it your best shot. Make your ideas come alive.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Welcome!</title>
	  <link>/blog//Welcome</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-03T10:18:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Welcome</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>&gt; Behind every victory, there lies an undying passion.
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Hello. I am Harish. This is my personal blog which I share my projects and reflections.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Hello World</title>
	  <link>/blog//HelloWorld</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-03T10:18:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//HelloWorld</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Hello World! This is a mandatory first post!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
