<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life & code.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Solving Einstein's Riddle</title>
	  <link>/website//Solving-Einstein's-Riddle</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-07T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//Solving-Einstein's-Riddle</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/IgXHPOF.jpg " alt="Einstein" style="width: 200px;" /></p>

<p>There is an interesting riddle written by Einstein in the last century. He claimed that <strong>98%</strong> of the people in the world will not be able to solve it.</p>

<h2 id="the-riddle">The Riddle:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>There are 5 different houses, each of a different colour.</li>
  <li>There is a owner of a different nationality in each house.</li>
  <li>Each of the owner drinks a specific type of drink.</li>
  <li>Each of the house owner smokes a specific type of cigarettes.</li>
  <li>Each of the house owner has a specific type of pet.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>None of the owners drink the same drink / smoke the same cigarette brand / have the same type of pets / have same nationality / live in the same house.</em></p>

<h2 id="the-clues">The Clues:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>the Brit lives in the red house</li>
  <li>the Swede keeps dogs as pets</li>
  <li>the Dane drinks tea</li>
  <li>the green house is on the left of the white house</li>
  <li>the green house’s owner drinks coffee</li>
  <li>the person who smokes Pall Mall rears birds</li>
  <li>the owner of the yellow house smokes Dunhill</li>
  <li>the man living in the center house drinks milk</li>
  <li>the Norwegian lives in the first house</li>
  <li>the man who smokes blends lives next to the one who keeps cats</li>
  <li>the man who keeps horses lives next to the man who smokes Dunhill</li>
  <li>the owner who smokes BlueMaster drinks beer</li>
  <li>the German smokes Prince</li>
  <li>the Norwegian lives next to the blue house</li>
  <li>the man who smokes blend has a neighbor who drinks water</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-challenge">The Challenge:</h2>

<p>You are challenged to find out who has the fish using the above information and clues.</p>

<h2 id="the-solution">The Solution:</h2>

<p>The first thing to understand is that though the information seems sparse and disjointed, there is indeed a logical path for you to work out the riddle.</p>

<p>Imagine the houses layed out in a horizontal manner with the first house on your left to the last house on your right.</p>

<iframe src="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BwSVKyZQM1obZ1VNWm8waHp2NUU/preview" width="640" height="480"></iframe>

<p>Next, we list out all the possibilities for each category. The categories are nationality, colours, drinks, pets, house number and cigarette brand.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Nationality
    <ul>
      <li>Norwegian</li>
      <li>Brit</li>
      <li>Dane</li>
      <li>Swede</li>
      <li>German</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Colours
    <ul>
      <li>Blue</li>
      <li>Red</li>
      <li>White</li>
      <li>Yellow</li>
      <li>Green</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Drinks
    <ul>
      <li>Coffee</li>
      <li>Tea</li>
      <li>Beer</li>
      <li>Water</li>
      <li>Milk</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Pets
    <ul>
      <li>Dogs</li>
      <li>Cats</li>
      <li>Birds</li>
      <li>Horses</li>
      <li>Fishes</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>House Number
1,2,3,4,5 respectively for each house from left to right</p>
  </li>
  <li>Cigarette Brand
    <ul>
      <li>Dunhill</li>
      <li>Blends</li>
      <li>BlueMaster</li>
      <li>Pall Mall</li>
      <li>Prince</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Now we write whatever we know in a table form. As we gather more and more information from the clues, we fill the table.</p>

<p>We know that the Norwegian lives in the first house. Next, we know that the Norwegian lives next to the blue house. This means that the 2nd house in the row is blue. The man in the center house drinks milk. And we are told that the green house is on the left of the white house and that the green house’s owner drinks coffee. The clue that the green house is on the left of the white house tells that the 4th and 5th houses have to be green and white respectively.</p>

<p>The Brit lives in a red house. The first house has already been occupied by the Norwegian and we know the colours of the 2nd, 4th and 5th houses. This leads us to the fact that the center house is red and the Brit lives there. Also, this leaves the first house to be yellow.</p>

<p>The green house’s owner drinks coffee.</p>

<p>Putting together all these information, we have:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/UkHinqI.png" alt="" /></p>

<table style="undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
</colgroup>
  <tr>
    <th>Nationality</th>
    <th>Drink</th>
    <th>Smokes</th>
    <th>Pets</th>
    <th>Color</th>
    <th>House No.</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>German</td>
    <td><br /></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Dane</td>
    <td>Tea</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Brit</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Red</td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Swede</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Dogs</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Norwegian</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>1</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>Since the owner of the yellow house smokes Dunhill, we know the Norwegian smokes Dunhill. Therefore, the 11th clue tells us that the man in the blue house keeps horses.</p>

<p>The 12th clue tells us that the man who smokes BlueMaster and drinks beer must be in the 2nd or 5th house (since the first house is occupied by the Norwegian and men in 3rd and 4th house drink milk and coffee respectively).</p>

<p>Now consider the first house. The options of drinks left for the Norwegian are water, beer and tea. Since the Dane drinks tea, that option is out. Since the Norwegian smokes Dunhill, beer is out. We are left with water.</p>

<p>The last clue makes it evident that the man in the 2nd house smokes blend. That means the man in the last (5th) house smokes BlueMaster and drinks beer.</p>

<p>This leaves us with the option of tea for the 2nd house and hence, it means the Dane lives in the 2nd house.</p>

<p>The current table looks like:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Zi95yp8.png" alt="" /></p>

<table style="undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
</colgroup>
  <tr>
    <th>Nationality</th>
    <th>Drink</th>
    <th>Smokes</th>
    <th>Pets</th>
    <th>Color</th>
    <th>House No.</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>German</td>
    <td><br /></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Dane</td>
    <td>Tea</td>
    <td>Blend</td>
    <td>Horses</td>
    <td>Blue</td>
    <td>2</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Brit</td>
    <td>Milk</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Red</td>
    <td>3</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Swede</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Dogs</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Norwegian</td>
    <td>Water</td>
    <td>Dunhill</td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Yellow</td>
    <td>1</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>The 13th clue now shows that the only option for the German who smokes Prince is in the 4th house. This leaves the last house for the Swede who has dogs as pets.</p>

<p>The 6th clue shows that the Brit smokes PallMall and rears birds.</p>

<p>The 10th clue shows that either the first or third house has cats. Since the third house has birds, this means that the Norwegian keeps cats.</p>

<p>And we are done.</p>

<p>The finished table will look like this.</p>

<table style="undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 435px">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
<col style="width: 120px" />
</colgroup>
  <tr>
    <th>Nationality</th>
    <th>Drink</th>
    <th>Smokes</th>
    <th>Pets</th>
    <th>Color</th>
    <th>House No.</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>German</td>
    <td>Coffee</td>
    <td>Prince</td>
    <td>Fish</td>
    <td>Green</td>
    <td>4</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Dane</td>
    <td>Tea</td>
    <td>Blends</td>
    <td>Horses</td>
    <td>Blue</td>
    <td>2</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Brit</td>
    <td>Milk</td>
    <td>PallMall</td>
    <td>Birds</td>
    <td>Red</td>
    <td>3</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Swede</td>
    <td>Beer</td>
    <td>BlueMaster</td>
    <td>Dogs</td>
    <td>White</td>
    <td>5</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Norwegian</td>
    <td>Water</td>
    <td>Dunhill</td>
    <td>Cats</td>
    <td>Yellow</td>
    <td>1</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>This only leaves us with the German who must have the fish. :)</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</title>
	  <link>/website//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>We all talk about productivity and efficiency today. So here is my way of getting my things done.</p>

<p>I primarily use two platforms to get my stuff done: <a href="https://workflowy.com">Workflowy</a> and <a href="https://calendar.google.com/">Google Calendar</a>. Workflowy is an amazing platform that is buuilt on a simple idea: making lists. At first look, it may look so simple and plain and even no greater than a Notepad like web-app. But, it is amazing intuitive to use and I am usually able to structure and plan according the the priority of tasks.</p>

<p>I usually think in a structured, top-down way and I would probably attribute that to my engineering-based education. So a typical structure I impose in Workflowy is this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Urgent</li>
  <li>Important</li>
  <li>Upcoming</li>
  <li>KIV</li>
</ol>

<p>These are listed in order of priority and shows me which task I need to get done next.</p>

<p>Under each of these categories, I make tasks and their relevant sub-tasks. For example, I have an Engineering exam this coming week, I create a task called “Engineering Exam”. Under this task, I include a label called “Details” which indicates the time, date and location of this task and “Revision” which then contains the relevant sections and chapters to revise as sub-sub-tasks.</p>

<p>One of the greatest things about Workflowy is that you can create many many layers of sub-sub-sub-sub-…. tasks. However, an important feature that is missing is reminders.</p>

<p>For this, I use Google Calendar. All deadlines and events immediately go into my Google Account with a default alert set for 1 and 2 days before the actual date. This together with my list of tasks of Workflowy keeps me organised.</p>

<p>I check this list at the start of the day and update it as and when tasks come in. At the end of the day, I check if all intended tasks for the day have been completed. If yes, I complete them. If no, I move and reschedule them on the level of priority. Before sleeping, I spend 5 minutes working out the relevant tasks and agenda for tomorrow by simply adding a hashtag (#tomrrow) beside the tasks in Workflowy.</p>

<p>This system has worked great so far and I believe it has been a key reason for my productivity too.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Thoughts with Mass???</title>
	  <link>/website//Thoughts-with-Mass</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-01-17T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//Thoughts-with-Mass</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif"><img class="size-medium wp-image-140" src="https://harishv7.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/uni6.gif?w=250" alt="https://helenmagnani.files.wordpress.com/2013/05/uni6.gif" width="250" height="300" />Image Credits: https://helenmagnani.wordpress.com/</a></p>

<p>As I was reading The Lost Symbol, by Dan Brown, there was an interesting idea shared which immediately awed me. It deals with the hypothetical question: “Do thoughts have mass?”. Though, on a weighing scale, thoughts may possess mass ranging in the nano to femto scale, if they do have a mass, there will be many implications.</p>

<p>One of which was presented in the book was on gravity. If our thoughts had some mass, they will be bound by the laws of physics. Which meant, they will exert a gravitational force on other matter (though the force is of a very very small scale). Despite the insignificant amount force by a single thought, when a group of people come together to think on the same idea, this collective force becomes significant. It might then start to attract others towards this idea or notion. And that, will be powerful, when a thought can attract others and influence them to think in a certain way too.</p>

<p>Although it is a hypothetical question, the implications simply awed me. Upon further thinking: With thoughts having some mass, they will also be bounded by the Law of Conservation of Energy. Thoughts cannot be destroyed entirely. Instead, the thoughts are simply converted from one thought/idea to another. Or, they may become converted into another form of energy (likely chemical energy) in the brain.</p>

<p>Indeed, it is fascinating to imagine the implications if such a hypothesis was proven to be real. Whether it is true if thoughts have mass or not, only time will tell.</p>

<p>A few of my favourite quotes on the power of thoughts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Change your thoughts and you change your world. <br />
<strong>Norman Vincent Peale</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are what our thoughts have made us; so take care about what you think. Words are secondary. Thoughts live; they travel far. <br />
<strong>Swami Vivekananda</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Concentrate all your thoughts upon the work at hand. The sun’s rays do not burn until brought to a focus. <br />
<strong>Alexander Graham Bell</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>A positive attitude causes a chain reaction of positive thoughts, events and outcomes. It is a catalyst and it sparks extraordinary results. <br />
<strong>Wade Boggs</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cheers.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Most Powerful Thing in the World</title>
	  <link>/website//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2014-12-20T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/website//Most-Powerful-Thing-in-the-World</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Have you ever wondered what is the most powerful thing in the world?</p>

<p>Well, its not money, not wealth, maybe love, but really I think its an idea.</p>

<p>Yup, an idea. Every single day, we see ideas that change and craft the world. From the phone in your hand to the computer you’re reading this blog on, every thing around us took root from the idea that came up in someone’s brain.</p>

<p>But when you think about it, an idea isn’t something tangible. Not any physical product you can touch and understand. Nevertheless, you can feel it. And if an idea is powerful enough, it can change the world for the better, or for the worse.</p>

<p>I particularly felt galvanised watching Inception. Inception is basically about implanting someone else’s idea into a target’s subconscious, deep enough, that it changes their way of thinking. Well, an idea seems like a simple thing. But the potential and the potency of an idea goes beyond itself. It creates a chain reaction so complex that without that single idea in a person’s brain, the world might have been different.</p>

<p>The idea right now, in your head is something so powerful. Make sure it is put to good use. To make a change for the better.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you really want something, all the Universe conspires in helping you achieve it. -The Alchemist, Paulo Coelho</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a quote I always remember. What you are, who you are is defined by your ideas, your actions. If you have a good idea, and truly believe in it, then give it your best shot. Make your ideas come alive.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
