<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me/</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life, code and everything in between.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>7 Questions Every Business Must Answer</title>
	  <link>/blog//7-Questions-Every-Business-Must-Answer</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-25T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//7-Questions-Every-Business-Must-Answer</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Thiel">Peter Thiel</a>, a well-known entrepreneur, political activist and philanthropist shares the seven questions a business needs to answer in his bestseller book, Zero to One. Getting at least 5-6 questions correct might help in ensuring the success of the business.</p>

<p>I felt it was indeed crucial for any to-be-entrepreneurs to think about these questions before they embark on their start-up mission.</p>

<h3 id="the-engineering-question">1. The Engineering Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Can you create breakthrough technology instead of incremental improvements?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-timing-question">2. The Timing Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Is now the right time to start your particular business?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-monopoly-question">3. The Monopoly Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Are you starting with a big share of a small market?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-people-question">4. The People Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Do you have the right team?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-distribution-question">5. The Distribution Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Do you have a way to not just create but deliver your product?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-durability-question">6. The Durability Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Will your market position be defensible 10 and 20 years into the future?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="the-secret-question">7. The Secret Question</h3>
<blockquote>
  <p>Have you identified a unique opportunity that others don’t see?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Peter Thiel mentions that often people try to start a company and just hope for a miracle of success to happen. However, the true success of a start-up occurs when there’s a right mix of a few elements that forms a strong foundation of the company. The right mix happens when the above questions are answered, each with a ‘Yes’.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
