<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>http://harishv.me/</title>
   
   <link>http://harishv.me</link>
   <description>My thoughts - on life, code and everything in between.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Harish V</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>The Art of Fear Setting</title>
	  <link>/blog//The-Art-of-Fear-Setting</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-06-18T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//The-Art-of-Fear-Setting</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>In the recent talk, <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Tim_Ferriss">Tim Ferriss</a> talks about why we should define our fears more than just our goals. I found the quote he shared to be very relevant:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We suffer more often in imagination than in reality”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The quote was by <a href="https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Seneca_the_Younger">Seneca the Yonger</a> was a famous Stoic writer. Based on an exercise known as “premeditatio malorum”, which is essentially visualising the worst-case scenarios of taking a certain action, and thereby the fears which prevent us from taking the action, Tim shares a similar way he devised called “fear-setting”.</p>

<p>The written exercise consists of 3 pages.</p>

<h4 id="first-page">First Page</h4>

<p>The first page looks like this:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Define</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Prevent</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Repair</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">1. I might not win the competition.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">1. I will give my 100% in all the tasks, by dutifully planning my resources.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">1. I will take it as a learning experience for the next year.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">2.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">2.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">2.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">3.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">3.</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">3.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>In the first column, we write all the worst things that could happen from taking that action, about 10-20 of them.</p>

<p>In the second, we write all the actions we can take to prevent those worst-case scenarios from occurring or at the least, reduce the likelihood of that from happening.</p>

<p>In the third, we write the mitigation actions we can take in case that worst-case scenario actually occurs - damage control.</p>

<p>In the above, I considered a fictitious scenario of a person deciding to take part in a competition. It’s a simplistic scenario, but it helps illustrate the thought process.</p>

<h4 id="second-page">Second Page</h4>

<p>The second page looks like this:</p>

<p>We answer the question:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What might be the benefits of an attempt or a partial success?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here, we try to evaluate the what are the benefits of taking that action.</p>

<h4 id="third-page">Third Page</h4>

<p>The third page looks like this:</p>

<p><strong>The Cost of Inaction</strong></p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">6 Months</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">1 Year</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">3 Years</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">I would not have gained any experience to add to my portfolio.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">I might have missed an opportunity to gain the relevant experience for the competition this year.</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">I would have missed out an excellent opportunity which I could have added to my portfolio - which potentially could have landed me a good job or interview chance.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>On this page, we reflect on what are the potential consequences of avoiding this decision or action. We lay this out over a timeline of 6 months to 3 years which actually helps us see what are we truly missing out by neglecting this action.</p>

<p>As I listened to this TED talk, I felt myself thinking about certain decisions I was pondering upon right now. And indeed, when we go deep into reflecting what are the options available, what are our mitigation plans and what are the possible benefits / repercussions associated with that action, we truly gain a sense of understanding and clarity on whether or not to take it.</p>

<p>Tim shared a mantra from one of his favourite modern-day Stoics, Jerzy Gregorek.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Easy choices, hard life. Hard choices, easy life.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is true to some extent. The hardest choices, often those which we fear doing are also those which we most <strong>need</strong> to do.</p>

<p>I plan to try this exercise out for some of the major decisions I have to make. When we truly face our fears and get a strategy to overcome and crush them, then the path to our goals is now clear. This exercise helps us do exactly that. At the least, thinking through this exercise will provide added clarity to a confused situation.</p>

<p>Watch the TED talk here:</p>

<blockquote class="embedly-card"><h4><a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/tim_ferriss_why_you_should_define_your_fears_instead_of_your_goals">Tim Ferriss: Why you should define your fears instead of your goals</a></h4><p>The hard choices -- what we most fear doing, asking, saying -- are very often exactly what we need to do. How can we overcome self-paralysis and take action? Tim Ferriss encourages us to fully envision and write down our fears in detail, in a simple but powerful exercise he calls "fear-setting."</p></blockquote>
<script async="" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/platform.js" charset="UTF-8"></script>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Top Todo App of 2016</title>
	  <link>/blog//Top-Todo-App-of-2016</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-19T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//Top-Todo-App-of-2016</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>There are a multitude of todo apps nowadays. Finding the right tool to keep your day organised is rather an individual choice - but there are definitely some apps which outshine others in terms of their features. The best apps offer advanced features such as notifications, reminders, lists and sublists and the list goes on. </p>

<h2 id="wunderlist">Wunderlist</h2>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/vmpiDq5.png" alt="Wunderlist Main Screen" /></p>

<p>My vote for the best Todo application goes to Wunderlist. The name Wunderlist may be rather familiar to you considering it has been around since 2011. Though Wunderlist adopts a freemium model, I can safely say that the free version itself has plentiful of features that can satisfy any average user. </p>

<p>The best part of Wunderlist is its multi-platform support. The app is available on Windows, macOS, iOS, Android, Windows Phone, Kindle and Chromebook. Wunderlist also offers extensions on your favourite browsers: Chrome, Firefox and Safari. No matter where you are, you are always in sync. Add something on your Mac and it immediately shows up on your mobile phones.</p>

<p><img src="http://imgur.com/2OEZVgz.png" alt="Wunderlist ToDo" /></p>

<p>The second feature that makes Wunderlist the right tool for you is reminders. For every task that you add, you can specify both the due date and a reminder. This is my most used feature of Wunderlist as reminders ensure I am up to all my tasks even when I am not checking the app. Reminders are offered via the app as well as a personal email sent right to your inbox.</p>

<p>Todos added can also be specified to be recurring (daily, weekly, monthly, yearly or custom basis) and it is really simple to keep track of repeating tasks. Under each todo, Wunderlist also offers the support to add sub-tasks and notes. One thing the app does not offer is priority levels. You can also star important tasks which you can use to signify the priority. For more levels of priority, you can create individual priority lists and assign tasks to those. Alternatively, my recommendation is use Wunderlist tags. By appending “#tag_name” to tasks we can tag the task under a certain category. For priority levels for example, we can use <code class="highlighter-rouge">#high</code>, <code class="highlighter-rouge">#medium</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">#low</code>.</p>

<p>A huge plus of Wunderlist is its collaborative feature. I personally love using this feature whenever I am travelling with my friends or family. I simply create a shared list and all my friends or family members can easily edit the lists. They can also comment on the tasks I have added, making communication across the app really simple and easy.</p>

<p>The difference between the free version of Wunderlist and the Pro version is not stark, but it may make a difference for power users. Under the free version, we can add up to 5mb of files as attachments to tasks, assign up to 25 people, create up to 25 subtasks and choose from 20 backgrounds. The Pro version offers unlimited file size, assignments, subtasks and up to 30 backgrounds to choose from. Wunderlist Pro costs $4.99/month, but it seems that the basic or free version will easily satisfy the average user.</p>

<p>Check out the following link to Amazon for more information on Wunderlist, as well as a cool book which details Wunderlist for Writers!</p>

<iframe style="width:120px;height:240px;" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" src="//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;OneJS=1&amp;Operation=GetAdHtml&amp;MarketPlace=US&amp;source=ac&amp;ref=tf_til&amp;ad_type=product_link&amp;tracking_id=harishv7-20&amp;marketplace=amazon&amp;region=US&amp;placement=B01DICYKRU&amp;asins=B01DICYKRU&amp;linkId=955dd407043325294afff9cffcfc76bf&amp;show_border=false&amp;link_opens_in_new_window=false&amp;price_color=333333&amp;title_color=0066c0&amp;bg_color=ffffff">
</iframe>

<p>Wunderlist’s features and great looking user interface certainly makes it one of the most compelling todo apps today. Use it and let us know your comments below!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>My Getting Things Done (GTD) Framework</title>
	  <link>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</link>
	  <author>Harish V</author>
	  <pubDate>2015-12-03T00:00:00+08:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blog//My-Getting-Things-Done-(GTD)-Framework</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>We all talk about productivity and efficiency today. So here is my way of getting my things done.</p>

<p>I primarily use two platforms to get my stuff done: <a href="https://workflowy.com">Workflowy</a> and <a href="https://calendar.google.com/">Google Calendar</a>. Workflowy is an amazing platform that is buuilt on a simple idea: making lists. At first look, it may look so simple and plain and even no greater than a Notepad like web-app. But, it is amazing intuitive to use and I am usually able to structure and plan according the the priority of tasks.</p>

<p>I usually think in a structured, top-down way and I would probably attribute that to my engineering-based education. So a typical structure I impose in Workflowy is this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Urgent</li>
  <li>Important</li>
  <li>Upcoming</li>
  <li>KIV</li>
</ol>

<p>These are listed in order of priority and shows me which task I need to get done next.</p>

<p>Under each of these categories, I make tasks and their relevant sub-tasks. For example, I have an Engineering exam this coming week, I create a task called “Engineering Exam”. Under this task, I include a label called “Details” which indicates the time, date and location of this task and “Revision” which then contains the relevant sections and chapters to revise as sub-sub-tasks.</p>

<p>One of the greatest things about Workflowy is that you can create many many layers of sub-sub-sub-sub-…. tasks. However, an important feature that is missing is reminders.</p>

<p>For this, I use Google Calendar. All deadlines and events immediately go into my Google Account with a default alert set for 1 and 2 days before the actual date. This together with my list of tasks of Workflowy keeps me organised.</p>

<p>I check this list at the start of the day and update it as and when tasks come in. At the end of the day, I check if all intended tasks for the day have been completed. If yes, I complete them. If no, I move and reschedule them on the level of priority. Before sleeping, I spend 5 minutes working out the relevant tasks and agenda for tomorrow by simply adding a hashtag (#tomrrow) beside the tasks in Workflowy.</p>

<p>This system has worked great so far and I believe it has been a key reason for my productivity too.</p>

<p>Cheers, <br />
Harish V</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
